My name is Chong Sian. Currently, I'm a PhD
student University of
Illinois, Urbane Champagne.
So today, I will bring you this workshop of
this. Lifelong agent.
I'm the lead organizer of this workshop,
and also my friend, Junfei,
will also be here maybe, like,
ten minutes later. So he is
also co organizing this workshop with
me. So if you have, like,
any questions today, so
feel free to reach out to me and also
Junpei. We will be here,
all around the workshop. So
yeah. So it's my pleasure to
things off by giving you a brief overview
of today's program and sharing
some of the ideas behind why we
put this event together. So I
will also present some of our recent
work in this space as the
opening. The title of this
opening talk is called Driving the Era of
Lifeline Agent. So we believe the
next frontier of agent
AI actually lies in building agent that
can continuously learn stay
aligned with human goals, and evolve over time.
That is the vision,
actually exactly what motivates this
workshop. Like, we want to bring together
the perspectives from languages, reinforcement
learning, embodied
AI, and systems to explore
how we can move beyond
the static models towards truly Lifelong
Agent. Our workshop, we have
also been in our group,
actually, and also,
I have joined some of my friends' work. We
have all also been exploring this direction,
and I will later share
some of our early insights. So
most importantly, this is the core theme, and
we hope to
So
Okay. So
our workshop
here, we are very excited
to share that we have
100 o five accepted posters
including, like, four oral presentations today,
and all we will also
have the outstanding and the best paper award, at a
closing ceremony. So
the overall acceptance rate is about 45%,
So this percentage is relatively
low, compared with other work
but since we have a
large amount of submissions, thanks to
all of you, so
yeah. So so the exception
rate is, like, below 50%. So even
though the paper, if you are not
accepted, but, but still you are attending
our workshop, I'd appreciate
that. So, we hope we can all
learn something about the life front.
Life long agent today.
Yeah. So this wouldn't
have been possible without the tremendous effort
from our program committee
and also program chairs. So huge
thanks to also all of you guys,
who are audiences here, and if you are also
the reviewers or the submission authors,
you again for your submission.
Okay. So we actually have
a full day program today until
5PM, so the schedule is
quite packed. So today's agenda,
we include seven MITRE
talks, so include
a sponsored talk, and also
four oral presentations. Two
poster sessions, one in the morning, one in
the afternoon. And finally, we
have a student panel discussion and
the closing ceremony. So
all of this information is also available
on the iCleo official website
and it's also available in our
own website. So be
sure to check those platforms and don't miss
the events you are most interested
in.
So today, we have
seven seven diverse speakers. So each of
whom already well known for
the solid contribution to this field.
So, include, like, Sergei,
Astley, and Natasha, etcetera. So
we are excited both the breadth and
the perspectives they will bring to our program
today. Also, for the panel
discussion, we have invited a group of
early or middle career researchers to dive
deeper into the challenges and
opportunities in the field of Lifeline agent.
We hope this will spark meaningful discussions
and fresh perspectives on where the
field is heading.
And, of course, we also want
to give a big thanks
to all of our organizers for their hard
work Meehan and Chen Fei will be
on-site today, so to provide the
support and assistance throughout the
event. So we will be co hosting the workshops
throughout the day. So if you have any
questions or interesting, like, collaborations,
feel free to reach out to any of us. We
are here to support you and make sure you will
have a great experience.
And lastly, we'd like to
thank our partners and the sponsor
team. So please make sure to check
them out, like, Omi, Salesforce
AI Research, Tongcent, and
are all outstanding companies doing
impressive work in the agent space.
Yeah. So that's mainly
the introduction of this opening.
So next I'd like to briefly
introduce our vision of the Lifeline
agent and some of our earlier work
that devoted in this area.
We view a Lifelong agent not only
as a system that is trained once and
then deployed once and fixed, but as
one continuously learn
align, and evolve over time, As shown
in the figure, so you can see the agent
interacts with the user and
the environment. And improves through
feedback and experience. And
gradually updates his internal decision
making and becomes more
capable and reliable over time.
At the same time, this process must remain
grounded in human preferences.
Real world constraints,
efficiency, and the sustainability.
So the VisionConnect, so several directions
we have been working on, including the agent
post training, preference alignment,
self evolution, real world agents, and also
multi agent systems. So
through this workshop, we hope to bring all
these threads together and move towards agent
that can adapt to responsibly and robustly
through the life span.
So the foundation
of the life line age actually begins with
the self awareness and the environment
mental comprehension. So before an agent
can evolve or interact
safely, it must first understand
the boundary of his own internal knowledge
and possess a functioning predictive model
of the world it operates within.
So this phase establishes the baseline
decision making logic that governs
all subsequent agent behaviors.
So let's start by
looking at the very foundation of a Lifelong
agent. So before an agent can
actually learn or evolve it has to answer
one simple question first. So
when should I actually take an
action in the outside world? So
right now, many AI models they
just use the tools by default,
and they search the web or call
APIs even when they don't need to.
So which was a lot of time and also
computing resource, as you can
see in this diagram, we show on
the slides, so we view the agent
as a goal oriented decision maker.
Standing between two worlds. So on the
top, it has the internal cognitive tools.
This is the agent thinking step by step
reflecting and using its own memory.
On the bottom, it has external physical
tool, like doing a web search or
running a calculator or something like that.
So our theory of agent introduces a
simple rule to manage this.
Agent should only cross that two use
decision boundary in the middle when it
absolutely has to. So we
call this epidemic necessity.
So basically, the agent should first
try to solve the problem using what
it already knows inside its head,
only when it hits a wall and it genuinely lacks
the information. That's also when it
reaches the knowledge boundary
should it reach out and use an external
tool. So by perfectly aligning
the decision to act with the limits
of what the agent actually knows,
we stop the agent from overthinking or
overacting And this basic
self awareness makes the agent more efficient
And it is the absolute foundation
of a system that can operate
sustainably over a lifelong period.
So moving on to our next point.
Once the agent decides it needs to take
an action, it should really know what
might happen before it actually does.
So if you look at the top left of
this figure, part a, you will see
this paper search approach. So instead
of learning by trial and
error in the real world, which can be slow,
costly, and risky, we use
the language model itself as a simulated
sandbox. So we call this text
based world model. But how
do we know if the submission
this simulation is any good
so part b outlines our three step
check So first, simulation needs to
be highly accurate and consistent with
reality. And second,
we feed the model more data. It's
ability to predict the future state to scale
us up predictably and gets
even better. And finally, having
the internal sandbox gives a lifelong
agent three huge advantages.
First, it can verify action to
make sure it is safe. Before
before pulling the triggers. And second,
it can generate a synthetic trajectories
which basically means it creates its
own scenarios to practice on.
And third, it provides a warm start for
the reinforcement learning giving the agent
a massive head start so it learns much faster
when it finally enters the
real world. So this ability to safely
practice and predict a game
changer for the continuous learning.
So So now, based on what we
just discussed through my think that the problem
is already solved. Right? So we just give
the agent a world model, and it
will perfectly simulate everything before it
acts. But our very recent
research introduces a crucial reality check
So in this paper, we asked a very simple and
practical question. Do current
agents actually use these sandbox
effectively? And surprisingly, the answer is no.
We discovered a few surprising things
So first, models rarely choose to invoke the world
model on their own. They
prefer to trust a guess or act blindly.
And second, even when they
do use the world model, it
doesn't reliably improve their
performance So the net impact is basically
neutral. So this is a massive
bottleneck It shows us that simply giving
an agent a world model isn't actually
enough. For a lifelong agent
to actually benefit from foresight,
we have to build mechanisms that teach it how
to reliably interact
with these simulations. So
it needs to know when to trust the simulation,
and when to ignore it. And that realization
naturally leads us to our next major
topic. So how to teach agent
self awareness meta cognitions.
So with the epidemic boundaries
and predictive world models, it's
established, the lifeline agent must be aggressively
optimized for deployment in the
world. And real world constraints
demands that the agent
operates with maximal efficiency
actively mitigating the computational cost
and the latency associated with unnecessary tool
cost.
So now let's look at a very practical
challenge for agents.
To operate in the real world. So
this challenge is called tool overuse.
Just because an agent can use
search engine or calculator, it doesn't mean it
always should. So if you look
at the right image, so we solve
this by teaching the agent meta cognition,
which is basically the ability
to think about its own reasoning.
So let's say you ask the agent
about to say, Apple CEO.
But yeah. So
previously, in this paper, we regard it as
a slow changing fact, but recently,
yeah, the Apple just changed its CEO, so
maybe it's not a very good example.
So yeah. But but anyway, so if
it is like the example half a year ago,
so the agent may pause and realize, like, Tim
Cook has been the CEO for a long time, so this
is a slow changing fact.
So it just uses its internal memory.
But if you ask that about Apple's
maybe like absolute newest chip, and
recognized that it is a fast changing
fact. And actively decides to trigger
a web search. So we trained
our smart agent to evaluate his own knowledge
exactly like this. Deciding step by
step when a tool is
genuinely genuinely needed,
So the table at the left shows
why this self awareness is a massive
breakthrough So by teaching the agent
when to not act, achieved
a 24% drop in total two
usage, but there is here's
the best part. Because the agent stopped the
confusing tool use, so
we actually achieved
performance gain. So and our smaller
model can even reach the performance
of the massive 70,000,000,000
counterparts. So for a Lifeline agent to be
sustainable, it can't rely on just
the outside world for everything. So
it has to know what it already
knows.
Alright. So we just talked about,
like, teaching the agent when to use
tools using self awareness, but how do
we bake does the efficiency deepen
to the agent's core habit?
During its actual training phase? So
that brings us to the next piece of work,
acting less is reasoning more. So here
we move into reinforcement learning.
So if you look at the pipeline in the image, you
will see how we train the policy model.
In the past, people usually
just give the agent a reward if
it is eventually got the final
answer right. But for a lifelong agent
operating in the real world, that simply
isn't sustainable. So to say,
if it takes 20 mass and
expensive web searches, order
to find a simple answer, that is actually
a bad behavior we need to fix.
So at the formula at
the top right. So we create
something called the two
two integrated reward. What is
mathematically does is evaluate two
things. At the exact same time.
So first, did you get the
right answer? And second, how
many tools did you use to get there?
So basically, if the agent gets
the correct answer but relies on
tons of unnecessary tool cost,
our penalty function will drastically
shrink. Its reward.
But if it gets the same crack tons or use
using only, like, one necessary two call,
gets a massive reward. So in this way,
we are actively pushing the
overreliance on tools.
So by training agent this way, we saw up
to, 68% drop in
two calls and a huge boost in overall
tool productivity. All without
losing accuracy. So the agent
structurally learns a very powerful
lesson. Acting less frequently
actually forces it to reason more effectively.
So So okay. Let's now move
on to the next phase. So
a lifelong agent does not exist in
vacuum. So it actually exists in,
highly dynamic ecosystem populated
with human users. So its actions
must not only be conceptually efficient,
also strictly aligned
with human preferences. Shifting intent
and also complex multi term conversational
dynamics. So in the next phase,
we explore these sophisticated
reward structures required to achieve
this alignment.
So now that our agent
knows when to we and how
to be efficient, we face
another problem. So how do
we actually grade his homework?
When it interacts with the real world?
So if you look at the formula on the right,
you will see the golden rule for this.
So we split the final reward into
two main buckets, so format
and correctness. And why do we need this?
Because an agent that finds the right answer
but breaks the API code formatting to get
there is completely useless in
a real production environment.
The left image walks through exactly how
this work in practice. So let's say a
user asks, to compare flight
prices from Chicago to LA,
the agent generates a few different attempts.
So first, we create a format. Did
they use the right thinking tags
and two call structures? If
yes, it gets a point. And
then we look at the crackedness.
So we don't just give a simple pass or
fail here. As you can see at the
very bottom, right, grade the
agent piece by piece. So did
it pick the right tool name? Did it
use the correct parameter names? And finally,
did it input the exact correct
values like ORD or LAX
that is the abbreviation for the airport.
So by breaking the reward,
down into these tiny specific
dimensions, the agent gets clearer feedback.
So it knows exactly where it messed up.
So this strict step by step grading
makes the reinforcement learning process
incredibly stable. Leading to a 17%
performance boost over the base model
And for a lifelong agent to align with human
needs, we can't just to reward the
final answer. Instead, we have to reward the
final granularity process.
And And now let's talk about the most unpredictable
part of building a lifelong agent that
is dealing with actual human beings.
So real conversations are almost never
just to one question and just to
one perfect answer. So they are very messy.
Back and forth interactions. So to teach
our agent how to handle this,
look at the left side of this figure.
So we build interactive gene environments
with simulated users to give our
agent a safe place to practice these
long ongoing conversations.
But there is the big question. So how do
we actually grade the agent in these
long chats? If you look at
the right side of the figure, you will see that our
user URL framework doesn't force
just a one strict way of doing this.
Instead of, instead, we build a
highly flexible, customizable
interface. This allows us to easily
test and compare different reward
strategies So specifically, we
look at the difference between term level rewards
and the trajectory level rewards. So
turn level means we grade every
single reply by the agent
right when it happens. But we found that
this isn't always the best approach
Instead, our framework allows us also
to customize the mass to use
trajectory level scoring. So this means
we look at the conversation
as one single unit. By having
the flexibility to compare these approaches,
we observed that rewarding the
complete trajectory is actually much more effective.
It teaches the agent
patience it learns that it is okay
to spend a turn asking a clarifying
question, or adapting
to the user's changing mind. So this is
how we move from an agent that just
has the answer to an agent that
actually collaborates with you.
Now we enter the force
and final phase of our Lifeline agent
journey. So up to this point,
we have talked about how to efficiently
train and align the agent before
deployment. A true lifelong agent must
keep growing after it's
deployment. So in this phase,
we will look at two massive steps
towards it. So first, how
can an agent instantly self improve
on the fly? During a
live task, and how it can eventually teach
itself entirely from scratch
without relying on any human data
at all.
So So let's talk about what
happens when our agent faces a brand new
problem out in the wild. So
even the best trained agent will eventually
encounter encounter a user query that it doesn't
quite understand. So in this
paper, we asked instead of
failing or just guessing, what if the agent could
quickly teach itself to
improve and get the things correct?
So if you look at the flowchart on the right,
you can see how we made this happen.
When a user asks a question, the
agent first uses self awareness
So it basically asks itself, so
am I confident about this? If
it is certain about this question's answer,
then it just give that answer.
But if it is uncertain, it pauses
and moves to the self augmentation
phase. It generates a brand new
similar practice scenario right on the spot.
And finally, the self improvement step
the agent actually fine tunes its own parameters
using the single practice examples
before returning the answer to the user.
The original question.
And well, if you look
at the bar chart on the left, you will see why
this is so powerful. So by teaching
the agent itself using just
one single generated sample at test time,
our framework enhanced the model's accuracy by
an average of 5.48%.
Across multiple tools and benchmarks. And
the agent is literally learning
and patching its own knowledge gaps on the
fly. So this ability to
adapt in real time is
actually a perfect stepping stone to our final
breakthrough an agent that teaches itself
from absolute zero which
brings us the two r zero. Paper.
So up to now, our agent has
relied on us human to provide,
like, GM environments, to provide
practice questions, rewards.
But an agent is truly
on a going to operate
over a lifelong period, it
eventually has to break free from the bottleneck of
the human data and learn to teach it
So if you look at the top figure, you will
see a big shield in the
middle that says, like, 0% human
data. That is our ultimate goal.
So to achieve this, take a single
base language model and split it into two distinct
roles. Which you can see in both images,
the generator on the left, also the solver
on the right. So once separated,
they play a continuous
cooperative game with each other. So the
generator's entire job is
to autonomously since
synthesize brand new, highly specific
to use task. Acting
like a teacher creating
a custom curriculum. So the
solar's job is to figure out how to use this
tool to pass those new generated tests.
So now how do we reward
each? So we reward the generator
for creating the tasks
that are perfectly calibrated.
So meaning that they are just
hard enough to push the solver's boundary
but not impossible to solve
And simultaneously, we
reward the solver for actually
getting the format the final
answer right. By separating these
rows, to avoid learning
for conflicts, the agent engages in an
endless loop of self improvement.
Relying on zero human data, we can still
see a 92.5%
relative improvement to our base models.
And this is the true vision of the Lifeline agent
we are exploring in this workshop today.
System that starts a baseline
knows exactly when to act,
aligns deeply with users,
and ultimately drives its own evolution
forward.
So So as, as
we wrap up this opening, I want to bring
us right back to where we just
started. So this core
vision of the Lifelong agent So
over the past few minutes, we
have walked through a very specific architectural
journey if you look at this diagram again,
you may now see exactly how these
visual puzzle pieces fit together
to make this loop a reality.
Up at the top, managing the act
and the think, we established that
a sustainable agent must respect
its own knowledge boundary. It
uses meta cognition to know
to search and it uses
internal world model sandbox to verify
actions safely and structurally
penalizes itself for inefficient
tool use. So it is grounded,
and is efficient.
So down at the bottom left,
in the align phase, we saw that simple
password fail grading isn't just enough.
By breaking down the rewards into granular
formats, evaluating entire multi
term conversational trajectories,
in custom genes, we align the agent
to not just with prompt, but
also with the complex
shifting human interests. And, finally,
on the right side, in the evolved phase,
we broke the data bottleneck We saw
how an agent can recognize
its own uncertainty to synthesize
practice data and improve on
the fly at test time. And
ultimately, through the
adversarial self play of a generator and a
solver, we saw how an
agent can generate its own curriculum
evolve relying on zero human data.
So this is the paradigm shift we are
here to discuss today. And we
are no longer building systems that are trained once
deployed once. We are building systems that continuously
learn adapt, and
and deeply align with our preferences
And autonomously evolve.
So yeah. Thank you. And let's
get a workshop started today. Thank
you very much.
So our first talk,
MITRE talk today will be given by the
professor Sergi. So that's
welcome.
All right. Thank you all for
coming out here early in the morning.
So today I'm gonna talk about something a
little different. I'm going to talk about robotic
learning with autonomous data. So,
you know, many of you, of course, are
I'm sure interested in language models and use
language model assistance on a regular
basis. Maybe
you might have come home from work someday and decided
well, there's a lot I have to do tonight.
I have to make dinner, I have to clean the house, a
lot to do. Maybe one of these LLM
agents can help me with that as well. So
I tried, asking, popular AI
system one day, you clean the house, fold the laundry,
and make dinner? That
didn't really work, although I got a lot of instructions about what
I think I should do. But it would be really
nice if we could have agents that are not just
generating text but agents that actually act in the
physical world so that when you ask it to
clean the house, fold the laundry, and make dinner,
then it's going to have a busy evening instead of
you. And what I'm gonna talk about
today is how this is not
just a very, practically appealing
idea, but it's something that I think has a lot of
scientific value that if we can figure out how
to build lifelong learning agents, these
kinds of settings, we'll have learned
something more profound about lifelong
learning and autonomous improvement
So the area of
research that is perhaps most closely concerned
with this question is robot foundation
models. The way that robot foundation models
are typically trained is that,
one starts with a foundation model
trained on data from the web. Language
data, vision data, that sort of thing, and then adapts
it do robotic control. This can be
done in a variety of ways, but the most basic recipe
is to adapt a vision language model to
produce actions in response to textual prompts
in the same way that an LM agent
produces. Actions in response to textual
prompts. And this is a very active area
of research these days. It's something that I've
been working on quite a bit. It's, it's
something that my company physical intelligence
works on but it's also something that many other folks
have been, making a lot of progress on both in industry and in
academia. And, it makes sense that this would be very appealing
because in robotics, one of the big challenges of course
is gathering the kind of
broad and deep world knowledge that is needed
to act intelligently in the real physical world.
And to do this right, it's not enough to just have good
trained foundation models. You, of course, also need large
robotic data sets and ability to
get these robotic policies
to actually perform these tasks with a high enough success
rate to be practical useful.
Now, I think that this is something that
researchers should care about if
they're not terribly interested in robots.
Because when it comes to lifelong learning, I think
robotic learning offers us a lot
of both interesting challenges and interesting
opportunities. Because the real world
is very complicated. And
if you're thinking about lifelong learning agents, how
complicated the world that you situate that agent
in is is tremendously important. So,
the opportunities that the real world physical world
gives the AI system a lot to
learn. Think back to for
example, AlphaGo. AlphaGo was a very
impressive system because it could figure out ways
to play the game of Go that were
different what people had thought of. That was really,
really interesting. That was an example of an AI system discovering
something that people hadn't thought But
this, kind of progress didn't actually
make it that that far out of the
game of Go because the system was
predicated on operating in a world with
concise and well understood rules.
A small world that we can delineate very cleanly.
AlphaGo didn't need to worry about what happens if
somebody spills a cup of coffee on
the Go board. That is outside of the set of rules that it
deals with. The real world has a lot of
complexity. It has complex physical phenomena. You're
gonna go out and experiment with things. You can
run little scientific experiments to understand
how the world works. The universe is a
lot bigger than the Internet, it's a lot
bigger than what people have thought of. So if you have an
agent that is doing lifelong learning
and learning from the physical world as it really
is, rather than how people have described it,
there is virtually by
definition, lot more for it to learn.
And I think that's really exciting and really
promising. So robotic learning is useful
for more than just building useful robots. It's
a and lifelong learning
is much more valuable when you live in a world
that is complex enough for you to learn lots
of things from. So hopefully, that motivates
you a little bit to think about robotic learning.
We But, now let's talk about the technical
aspects of this. Okay. So robotic
foundation models, at the end of the day, not that
different from regular foundation models. You're
training a language model, a video generation model, what have
you, typically the recipe follows this kind of
structure. You have a pretraining phase
where you use large amounts of data
sourced from the web, to pretrain
your model. And the purpose of the pretraining phase is to
gain lots of It's not necessarily telling
the model what it should do in response to queries,
but it's baking lots of knowledge about the world into
it. And then you have a post training phase where
the goal is really to take that knowledge and align
it with the objectives of the model to
explain to it how it should follow instructions
satisfy user preferences.
So, in robotics, we have basically the same thing.
There's a pretraining phase where we would like
to use as much data as possible, the most diverse
not necessarily the highest quality data,
data that illustrates many different kinds of
physical interactions. And then we have
a post training phase and this is where
there's room for a lot of really exciting research
we can do many similar things as in an LLM
world in terms of instruction fine tuning and so on.
But we can also do RL. And
RL has, perhaps
even more importance in the world of robotics
than it does in the world of LMs because
for robots, you have to get very
nuanced, sophisticated physical behaviors
that are robust and that succeed reliably
at complex tasks, which is
difficult to do purely from large
scale human generated retraining data.
So it's really this phase of the process that I'm gonna
focus on today and I'll describe some
unique challenges in RL
training of robotic foundation models, and then provide
a few puzzle pieces that perhaps could be put together
in the right way in the future to provide a truly
lifelong learning system.
So why is train why is RL training of robotic
foundation models a challenge? Why can't
we just use everything that we've already,
figured out how to use for,
LLMs and other kinds of systems?
Well, the trouble is that if
the you want to do reinforcement learning
training for robots and you want to do it on top of pre
trained models, there's a very good chance,
and this is not a this is not an obvious statement, but I think there's
a very good chance that you're gonna want to do it on top of pre trained models, it in the real
world. Why?
Well, because if the whole
point of moving towards lifelong learning
in this setting that you can get a lot
out of a rich and complex environment. You have to
actually be using that rich complex environment
in your learning process. So while there's a lot to be
said for, using, let's say,
instrument and training environments in the lab or simulation,
as a way to get started if you really want to
move towards a lifelong system, then you
really have to be learning in situ
in the actual environment you will be tested. And
that's, of course, where a lot of the power will come But
this is difficult. So,
in the real world, it's really great that you
learn about the real world as it really is,
opposed to learning about stuff that you put
into your simulator or into your sandbox.
But the sandbox can be paralyzed.
And you can use algorithms that
are expensive in terms of the number of samples they need
but easily parallelizable such that they can
run on a big server farm.
Whereas in the real world, you need very simple efficient
algorithms to make this practical, even if you
have thousands of different robots,
you would rather put those those thousands of robots
into different places all learning about different
tasks rather than spend all of them to generate samples
for the one task so that you can run an expensive
algorithm. And
generally, there's a confluence of different
factors that make this kind of,
RL training very difficult. If you have big models,
if you want sample efficient RL, you
have difficult tasks, tasks where you don't just want
to, like, refine the strategy
a little bit, but where where you actually want the IRR
process to lead to new and better strategies
the confluence of all three of those factors is
really difficult. If you have just
two of those three, then you can
often set up algorithms that make this possible. But if you have
all three, you have a big model you need sample
efficiency and you have a difficult task so that you actually
need our relative change the behavior substantively,
this becomes very hard. And
what I'm gonna talk about today is how we can actually
get RL for robotic foundation
models to work by basically deleting one of these
circles. And you'll figure out shortly which
circle we're gonna be deleting. We'll bring it
back later. We won't delete permanently. But we'll
take it out temporarily to make things more tractable
and then put it back in actually get a working
system.
Okay. So, let's
describe a recipe for robotic r l
that the beginning, is going to be
separate from robotic foundation models.
This is not going to be a recipe for
training general purpose agents, and it's not actually a recipe
training for lifelong learning.
It's a recipe for training a very
narrow specialist that does
one thing really, really well.
So that's the the red circle. That's the one I'm gonna
take out. So
what you're seeing here is a video, of
an algorithm called RL There
are a variety of ways to do this. I don't I wouldn't claim
that this is the only algorithm that does it, but the point is to
really tweak the algorithm to be very good at
very quickly learning a very specific task
The task you're seeing here is, attaching
a chip to a PCB board. It finishes training
in about fifteen minutes and performs the task at
100% success rate.
So the algorithm's RLP. It's an off policy actor
critic algorithm initialized from
So observations are images
of the pretrained encoder. The reward is a
sparse reward given by an image class So
it's kind of it's basically the real deal. There's no trickery
going on here. And optionally, you can
add in human interventions where if you
don't like what the robot is doing, that
when the screen turns red, there's a person that's intervening
and it's it's almost like a coach giving you a correction
for how to fix your mistake. So for the PCB insertion,
there are no human interventions. That's all autonomous. But if
you have a harder task, like this timing
belt assembly, you can use human interventions.
And there are a number of ways to set up this recipe
so that it works.
You don't have to use soft DockerKritik, for example,
which what this uses. There's other methods that'll work.
The point is to really optimize the whole system
for very efficiently learning a single narrow task.
That is not good enough for training a robotic foundation
model. It is very useful. So I'll
show you a few videos of this, then explain
some of the limitations, I'll talk about
how we can turn this into method
for training our foundation models.
So, here are some more videos of a different
task This is actually a more complex task. It's
using a bimanual CUKA system.
To assemble a car dashboard.
And after trading, this is
the task. There what makes this difficult, see
have to align a number of little plastic pins
so that they line up perfectly with the holes for the
insertion. That's very hard for a robot to do.
Here's the timing belt task from before and,
you know, it's decently robust so somebody
can go in and mess with the timing belt and the robot will
recover from that.
And it's also pretty difficult to do because of the deformable
objects and stuff like that. And
And here's a selection of other tasks. So some of them
are very dynamic like flipping the egg,
or playing with
that Jenga tower. Some of them are deformable
and so on. This is very
fast, This is all trained directly in the
real world from images and the success rate gets to a 100%
on each of these tasks. You also
get policies that are faster than behavior cloning.
So here are the blue bars represent
the cycle time for behavior cloning. The red bars
represent RL. So it's two
or more times faster. But
there's no pretraining going on here, and these
are specialist policies. So if you
were to take a poll the policy train for the timing belt
and make the timing belt like 50% bigger
or something, then it wouldn't work anymore.
Okay? So the puzzle that we're faced
with is, okay, we can
get very good algorithms for training these specialist
policies by basically taking out that that red
circle, removing the foundation model from the equation and
using very narrow specialized things. Can
we use them based on the
bigger? So we investigated
a this in a method that
we called RLDG. And the idea
here is actually very simple. In fact,
the diagram makes it look more complicated than it
is. The idea is basically just to use RL
specialists to generate training data.
That's it. Just, run RL exactly
like I showed before, generate training data,
and just add it into the training set. Your
favorite general's policy. In this case, we
used OpenVLA and Octo, but you could use
anything you want, OpenPy, whatever.
So as an example of one of these things, we
trained RL specialist policies
for inserting different connectors like
USB and so on,
use that to produce training data
fine tuned a specialist model on that, and
then tested it on other connectors.
And that's where you get the power of actually,
integrating these into a generalist model, The
generalist model can actually generalize to new unseen
connectors. The individual RL specialists could not.
So now we're actually seeing some of that
benefit and this perhaps gives us a hint for how this could
work in the future. To dig a little bit
more into the quantitative results,
the blue bars here represent open VLA, the green
bars represent Octo, two different foundation models.
Open VLA is a better one, so it's better across
the board. And in each pair, the dark
colored bars are trained on RL data,
The light colored bars are trained on the
same amount of successful
human demonstration data. So this is a controlled experiment.
RL did use that many demonstrations,
but we intentionally collected more just so we could have
an apple to apples comparison with the same
exact amount of data. And that's kind of
funny. Like, the RL data actually leads to better generalist
policies even though it's the same amount and it's the
same success rate. And you can imagine
why that might be the case, the RL data comes
from a real Markovian policy.
It actually, is something that we know can
be represented by a neural network, so it provides
for sort of a better diet of data
for our generalist policy.
Now there is something missing from the stress
that makes it incomplete, that makes it not adequate if we
want a truly general
lifelong learning loop. Which is that so far
the specialist helps the generalist, but the
generalist does not help specialist.
So we use these, small
specialist models to produce training data that goes
into our robotic foundation model can
we somehow close the loop? Can we make it so that making
the generalist better also makes
the next round of specialist training
better as well. And if we could do that, then we could
imagine actually closing the loop on this and taking
a step towards a truly lifelong system,
instead of the current one, which is very one directional.
So we studied this recently,
in a paper called RLT. And the idea
we had was well, these specialist,
policies it's good to keep
them pretty small because then our l can train them very
rapidly in the real world. In fact,
the amount of training just a couple of hours is actually
less than the amount needed to fine tune the entire
large foundation model, But training
them from scratch doesn't let them benefit from the nice
representations in the foundation model.
So can we somehow pull out the representations
from the robotic foundation model?
Essentially get it to produce like a kind of
RL token, a token that sort of
summarizes the knowledge that the foundation model has about
the current observation,
and then pass that into this, smaller
r l actor and critic to get it to be
a good specialist and then distill it back into the larger
model. So there are again a few ways to
set this up, but roughly speaking you need some kind
of encoder to pull out the representations for
the robot foundation model and summarize it in
a in a, concise context.
You could literally add an a separate
The way we actually did it is we used an encoder
decoder architecture You can think of it as a
very fancy auto encoder that pulls out
the representations from the VLA and compresses
them. But again, I think there are multiple ways to do
it. The point is to get the representations from the VLA
to be the input to the RL
specialist instead of forcing it to have its own
separate observation encoder.
There's a few additional details to make this work really
well. The other thing you wanna do is actually take the action
predicted by the generalist model and provide
it to the RL learning process
as well. And that provides
for a way to constrain exploration. Because
while you want the RL specialist
to improve over the base model that it's starting
from, you don't want it to explore too broadly
have to essentially, like, rediscover the wheel. So it
turns out that adding a little regularizer that
tells it like, hey, all else being equal, try to produce
an action that's close to the one that the generalist model
is producing. Actually makes learning faster
because it, gets it to really first
internalize whatever strategy the generalist has, and
then gradually improve it from there.
And then this efficient, RL actor and
critic, they receive the representations, reference actions,
from the robot foundation model and therefore are bootstrapped
by it. Which lets them learn more complex
tasks, represent those tasks in a more
generalizable way, and generally just learn faster.
So Now, we made one
more optimization to make this as quick as possible,
which is that we set it up so that we don't actually
use RL fine tune the entire
task. We use RL to fine tune only the segment of
the task that is most difficult.
So you'll see a video here of a robot using
a a screwdriver to assemble
a screw. Most of the task is actually
just executed by the base journalist
model. And at one point, we switched to
the RL specialist for just the difficult part of
the task, it needs to practice. So this
is all with the base model, and then, the text
at the bottom will switch. When the RL
is active, and that's just for the actual screwdriver
assembly part because that's the part that requires
very precise alignment, and
usually takes, the most extra time. The
robot makes a mistake. And
here are some more tasks that were learned with this method,
assembling the screw, fastening
a zip tie, inserting, Ethernet cable.
So you'll notice that these tasks all have something
in common, which is they all have some
fairly, coarse phases where you just have to
manipulate the object in a reasonable way. And then they
have some very precise phases
where you have to do it very, very carefully. And it's
those precise phases that are being
most improved the RL method.
So there you can see the the zip tie assembly
happening.
The zip tie is very hard because it's actually holding both
ends of the tie in the air, and they're all, like, wiggling all
over the place. And in some sense, the
robot actually makes it look easy once it's learned the task with
our role properly. So
Quantitatively, this actually works really well. So
the bar graph here shows the amount
of the the, throughput,
which is the number of successful
executions of the task per unit time.
This is a good way to summarize both success rate
and speed. And you can see that the throughput
on each of these tasks improves a lot. So the
bar graphs show separately the just
the stages fine tuned with RL which are the
four bars on the right and the full task including
the parts that are not fine tuned on the left. But, of
course, the difficult phase is usually the bottleneck
for these tasks. So, the
improving the difficult phase improves the whole task
a lot. The speed of these things is
actually quite good. So this is a
histogram of episode length. The
red section is the base
generalist policy. The green section is
the teleoperators. Which
are faster than the generalist policy that is just trained
with imitation learning. And the yellow part
is the RL policy, which is faster
even the fastest teleoperators. And
then we ablated each piece of this recipe,
adding the BCD regularizer, adding the RL
token, and so on. We found that basically all of them are actually
helpful. The only ablation
that comes close to the, RLT method, which
is in yellow, is the red line. And what
the red line is doing is it's just omitting
the generalist action
input into the actor. And that actually
makes sense. If the actor gets the representations,
but it doesn't get the generalist actions,
can still learn the task. It just has to try more
stuff to get there, so it takes longer to
learn. Still succeeds. But removing the RL
token actually makes us, pretty much fall
apart on these difficult tasks.
Okay. So so far we've got almost
all the puzzle pieces. We can
generate data for our generalist with these
RL specialists. And the RL specialists itself
can benefit from the generalist. But
there's a bit more that we could say about how to
properly use the RL
data training the generalist. So
so far, we've done something very straightforward, which
is we use the specialist
to generate datasets and just straight up use imitation
learning, distillation essentially
on the specialist to distill into the generalist.
But, there is a a choice to be made
here because the RL process produces a
lot of data over the course of our training.
And so far, we've kind of slipped it under the rug.
We said that, well, let's just use the data from
the final policy because that's the good one. And
that's actually a little bit ugly because actually
want a significant amount of data. In fact, you might end
up using your specialist to generate
more data from the final policy than you used
to train the entire specialist in the first place
because the specialist training is so efficient.
So most data that our all collects is actually
not from this policy, and we can be more efficient.
We can use all the data collected during RL,
but then we have to account for the fact that
a lot of that data is bad. Now,
here's the the thing. Bad data is not
useless data. There's actually a lot you can learn from
bad data. Bad data might contain good
segments if you know how to find them, and
it might also,
illustrate other
situations from which you can recover
that you would not see in good data. So
using the bad data is useful not just
because you have a lot of it from running RL,
because it actually shows useful stuff that you might
not see in the optimal policy. So we would actually
really like to use that. And
in fact, if we can use the the bad data
might not even need a separate specialist actor. We
might need a specialist critic. But the specialist
actor can be that generalist policy,
begin with. So
here are a few ideas that can allow us to do this.
The first idea is going to make use
of the fact that,
most of the, modern robotic
foundation models use diffusion to
generate actions. You can actually do this without diffusion, you could do
this without a decoding too, but it's
a bit kind of more logical with
diffusion. And that's to use,
CFG. This guy
kind of a funny statement. It turns out that
CFG which is, which was invented
as a trick to get diffusion
models to be better at producing generations
that are aligned with the desired prompt
or the desired class label. Is actually
a policy improvement operator.
Basically, CFG and PPO are almost
the same thing at some level. One iteration
of PPO. That sounds
weird, but let let me this is actually the most
mathy slide of this talk, but let me try to
briefly explain this idea. So what
you see on the screen right now is,
anybody, here that works on our own will probably find
this familiar. This is basically the original
objective from which you derive,
PPO or any other constraint policy
optimization method. This is a maximizing expected
reward, with a Lagrange
multiplier on a on a constraint between
the k l divergence, on the k l divergence
between a policy and a reference policy. Very
very common NRL. So
what here's what we're gonna do. We're not gonna use this to
constrain against a reference policy.
We're gonna, constrain
between a policy that matches all
of the data, including the bad data, and a policy
that matches the good data. Okay? Kind of
a funny thing to do.
And, the solution to this
optimization, can be shown in closed
form to be just the reference
policy multiplied by the exponentiated
advantage, possibly with a temperature.
The temperature is the Lagrange multiplier.
That makes sense, like, actions with high advantage,
the tasks you want become exponentially more
likely, and, the Lagrange multiplier
terms how likely.
So here's what we're gonna do instead, instead of
right doing the user usual policy grading. We're
gonna introduce a variable, a binary
variable that I'm gonna call the optimality variable. Called
o. And the probability of o given
s a is just some function of the advantage,
It's gonna be the exponential function if we want it to match
up. And
now I can express my new policy as my reference
policy times the probability of o.
Okay? It's just a little mathematical trick. There's nothing terribly
profound about this. I just define probability of o
to be literally the thing that I'm multiplying p hat by.
But now what I can do is
I can write the score function
of my policy as
the sum of the score function of
pi hat and the gradient of log
p of o.
And now, this is starting to look a lot like what
we do we run CFG.
So, we can
apply Bayes' rule rewrite that
second term, and now we can see that if
we want to take samples
from the spinal policy, all we have to do
is get a score function of
the unconditioned
policy, the policy that matches all the data,
and the score function of a policy
condition on the variable o. And that means
that we don't actually have to learn, this
p of o given SA, we just use the CFG
trick and just learn two different conditional policies.
So this is basically exactly CFG.
And the key idea, the only thing you actually have to
do, is train your policy condition on a variable
that tells you is the data good or bad.
You can have other variables. You can have some
nuanced, version of what good or bad means,
but the minimal thing you need is a binary variable
that is this good stuff or bad stuff? And
then when you sample, you just
run CFG on setting that thing
to good stuff essentially pushes the sample
sample away from everything that is,
you know, unconditioned and towards the good stuff.
That makes sense. Move away from the bad stuff, move towards
the good stuff, and you get a better policy. And this is mathematically
the same as one iteration of
KL constrained policy improvement.
So this is kind of the obvious illustration of what
this is doing. If the good stuff here is
on the right side, doing CFG on the good stuff
pushes you towards the good stuff.
It actually works better than training
on a filtered dataset. So the baseline
here, labeled AWR, this is actually
hard label AWR, which basically means
filtering out the negatives, filtering out the bad stuff. This is
better than filtering out the bad stuff because you
use both the good stuff and the bad stuff in
training. And you get a a nicer
loss function because if you have to filter out a
part of each batch to remove the bad stuff,
then you have higher variance gradients.
Okay. We can use this
at scale. We use this, in a recent system
called pi star o six. Where we use
actually a variety of data
sets. To, including
autonomous data. To train a
robotic foundation model and a value function
The robotic foundation model here is conditioned
on this binarized advantage, this optimality
variable, and uses that
to generate additional data. And that additional
data is then added back into our l training So
it's used to them. Improve the value function, improve
the foundation model, then
again condition it on optimality. Here's a
more nuanced kind of architecture
diagram. I won't go into the diagram in too much detail.
But, what I do want to go into in some detail
is what the value function learns.
So here are two different tasks. The first one
is folding a shirt The second one is opening a fridge
and taking out the water filter. The graph at
the bottom shows the value function.
The reward here is basically minus one for every
step until you succeed. So you can think of it as a
kind of progress indicator. As it goes up, you get closer
to success. And you can see that for the
shirt folding, there's a segment where the value function
dips mistake
was made, and then it goes up as you make progress.
For the water filter, it goes up a lot when you open the
fridge. That's good. Opening the fridge is a good step towards taking
out the water filter, and it goes down a little
at the end when the robot tips
over the water filter a little bit.
Here are some of the tasks, trained with this
method. We actually ran
the coffee making task for about thirteen
hours nonstop in our office. Everybody was very
caffeinated at the end of that. But that's
kind of a nice way to test if the thing is actually working.
It's not perfect. It actually did make some mistakes during
those thirteen hours. It occasionally drops the
the porta filter and spills, coffee grounds
all over the table, but it only happened a couple of times
in thirteen hours and overall, the coffee was
satisfactory. And this is, and here
the entire task is actually improved
with RL. So every every stage of it
we ran this for a box assembly task. So,
here the robot has to build,
a box, from a flattened sheet.
Add a sticker to it and then stack it on the table on the
right. And again, this runs for a long time
and the whole thing is actually improved with RL.
Here are the quantitative results. So let me go through
these. The
green bar, the dark green bar here
shows what happens with just the initial offline data.
Set, which contains demonstrations.
And this is using this optimality conditioning,
but just in an offline phase. The pale
yellow bar is essentially SFT. So this is
a a version of this where we fine tune with
demonstrations. And the dark yellow bar
is where you also add additional autonomous rollouts
use this, optimality condition
policy to improve it, and then iterate
a couple of times. And the
the y axis here again is throughput. So this is
a number of successes per hour. And you
can see that there are pretty big improvements,
across all of these tasks. On three out of the four,
it's at least two x.
Now so far we're training
individual policies for each of these
tasks. So this is not yet a true generalist.
In our most recent work, actually
did put all this together. We basically have one
giant model that we call pi o seven, which
combines all of the data from
these individual RLL runs and uses
a more nuanced conditioning. So it's not conditioning on just
one binary variable, it's conditioning on more information,
but essentially the same idea that the
this information correlates with how
good the the executions
are, and that lets us use this highly suboptimal
data. So it gets demonstration data, it
gets all the autonomous data, and now
all these tasks that I showed, they can actually be
baked into one generalist model.
So before we had these an individual, specialist,
and now we can have one generalist model does all
of these to the same level of performance. And
you can imagine, of course, that the a good starting
point for a lifelong learning loop. And the same model
can do lots of other stuff. It can, you know,
peel the zucchini and it it can do
this, screwdriver task from before.
Now again, this is a a distillation based idea.
So you can do the screwdriver task, but of course, it's
using data from those individual RL runs
to include in the model with this,
optimality conditioning trick.
So some takeaways.
I think RL is really the key to
lifelong learning of robot foundation model, Paul.
I don't think that's a controversial statement.
But, the more controversial statement is that directly
training the robot foundation models end to end with RL
is still pretty hard. If you really try very carefully
and you set things up just right, you can just barely
do it. But, RLL can work very
well, individual specialist policies,
and learning hard tasks,
new strategies where the the overall process actually changes
the strategy meaningfully. So this gives us a
really powerful tool because the generalist model
can help the specialist and the specialist can help
the generalist. And if we're
careful in setting this up, we can get a single
model that does lots of different tasks benefiting
from those that are all process, and that
can be really powerful. So to
round this out into the recipe that have
not yet built, but that I think is, the logical next
step for this, is to have a generalist
model initialize for the
video there, initialize the specialists,
that gets us training data. That
training data can be distilled into an even better generalist,
and that better generalist can then initialize even
better specialist for the next round. Okay.
So I'll stop there, and I'd be happy to take questions.
Yeah. Thank you
very much, professor Sergi. So,
if anyone have any questions,
please come to the upfront microphone.
Yeah. Hi.
Thank you.
If you shout, I can just repeat it.
Just wanted to know, how,
the learning progress Would you manage to
get, almost a 100% success
rate if you were training for three months?
Okay. So the question was, learning progress.
Would you get to a 100% success rate
if you train it for three months? So,
the answer is it depends
could does need to be done. So for
these things, for example, the the coffee
tasks and so on, it does not get to a
100%. If we,
no. Sorry. This is frozen. But the coffee task that
you saw, it does not get to a 100%. Percent. It
gets to, like, 95%
or so. The last 5%, what's going on
there? Well, these are the kind of mistakes that the
RL process just doesn't explore enough to give us
a solution to. Think there are ways
to solve it. I think there's smarter ways to do exploration.
You could even imagine, like, varying the prompt and get
exploring better that way. But for the hard tests, it's a bottleneck.
For the simpler tasks like the egg flipping and
so on, there, it gets to a 100% no problem. And
you're
Thank you for the great talk. I have a question
about the last part. So
why is the crossfire free guide on reinforcement
learning? It's better than the real weighted
regression? I think it
probably, it's coming from the same problem
formulation, but, what we do in revaluating
relation is that we minimize the carrier divergence
between the parameterized Poisson and the Boltzmann
Poisson. Right? Then it's similar, but
is it is, reiterating
aggregation more more the covering rather
than mode seeking? So this is a very interesting
question. The question for those that didn't hear is,
well, why is it that, reward weighted,
regression or AWR worse than
CFG? Mathematically,
in the limit, they're doing exactly the same thing
as you pointed out. I think
the a big part of why they're different is that
when you when you use AWR, what you're really
doing is importance waiting. And importance
weighting can be very bad for big models,
Why? Well, because big models are kind of notorious
for learning the right answer, but not being
well calibrated. And if you're using importance weighting
where you really want the action probabilities to
reflect their frequencies, then you want a model
that's well calibrated. And big networks
are just not that good at that. So essentially,
with AWR, even a bad
action appears as a good action
with a small weight. And if the model is
really smart about learning the right probability
on that, it will actually say it's low probability. But if it
just if it's big and it fits everything, even
the bad action will actually end up being fitted very well.
Whereas with the optimality condition, you're explicitly telling
it like, hey, this is an action, you should learn
about it, but remember, what you should learn is that it's bad
This is an example of what not to do. And if you just
think about what c f
g does when you're running it for sampling, It
actually pushes you away from
the unconditional generation.
So anything that is labeled
as good you'll be you'll push towards it and away
from the other stuff. So that's actually very
good for sharpening distribution around specifically the
good actions. Thank you very much.
Hi, Sergey. Thank you for a great talk.
I'm super, amazed I'm so surprised
when I read the paper about the pie
zero point six and zero point seven and
walking ash on the humanoid
robot system. I wonder for the long horizon
task, how do you think there's,
ideal memory mechanism?
I noted that in pi 0.6,
there are some, memory design like
forced semantic memory and also
some episodic memory But
for lifelong agents, we want to add
to take more duty or responsibility.
So how do you think we can
design a idea, memory mechanism? How
do you efficiently update and forgetting
something. Yeah. Thank you. Yeah. That's a good
question. So in
this talk, everything I discussed, doesn't
do anything particularly smart about memory. Everything
is just, basically, like, using RL
to train, to to to
bake the additional knowledge into the model's weight
I think there is probably a lot more that can be done.
With smart memory mechanisms,
and probably, this is what the field
of metal learning arguably is the most,
focused on, because in a
classic meta reinforcement learning
framework, what you're essentially doing is you're
using short term memory stored in the, model's
activations to rapidly
learn a new task and then over
time, you would would put that knowledge into the model's
weights. So none of these methods are actually doing
I think that would be really fun to do, but that would be a completely
separate project. Okay. Thank you.
Hello. You hear me? Yes.
So I was curious about your thoughts on
just using autoregressive, like,
policies where you have, like, action tokenizers, like,
fast because it does really
simplify the URL
So I was curious about
if you are
thinking about improving fast
type tokenizers or
stuff like that? Yeah. Good question. So
maybe for a little bit of context for everybody else,
the diffusion based, action generation
mechanisms that most current robotic
foundation models use it's very nice for producing
continuous actions with, that capture all
the different modes. But it is kind of complex
for reinforcement learning because reinforcement learning with
diffusion is more complicated than reinforcement
learning with, discrete actions that you would get.
From a traditional tokenization.
I'm not sure quite how to answer this,
I suspect that discrete tokenization can
be made to work I think right now,
probably, if you try to build the
best robotic foundation model, the diffusion stuff
will be better. I doubt that that's actually fundamental. I think
there's a way to make the discrete stuff work just as
well. I'm also not sure that we
have to because while there are kind of
conceptual challenges with using diffusion four
RL, It's not that it's fundamentally harder,
it's just that, like, you know, spend
a lot of time as a community developing good methods for discrete
actions. We didn't spend as much time on the diffusion stuff and
if we spent more time on it, maybe it would be just
as good. So, like, we shouldn't mistake,
mathematical difficulty for, like,
fundamental complexity. I guess
I would also ask, like, what do you think is the limitation
of, like, discrete?
Actions? The biggest limitation
is that if you want to sample from a complex
joint distribution, it's very slow.
So like, it it might it
might seem like diffusion should be the slow one because diffusion
requires multiple iterations, but the iterations of
diffusion are paralyzed over all the tokens.
Whereas generate autoregressive generation has to
be sequential. And in practice, if you implement
both of them very well, autoregressive stuff will actually
be a lot slower. And for a real time system, that's
very annoying. Okay. Thank you.
Hi. For the RLT paper, how
do you autonomously activate the
RL policy during rollout?
So there's nothing kind of fancy there. It's
just like you you just need a model to detect that
particular thing happened and then switch it. The
same way that you would assign rewards, autonomously.
K. You. Hello.
Thanks for the great talk. Like I
am wondering about, like, how do you think about,
like, sequentially accumulating
the task because, like, you train the separate belly
network for the each task and then just
training or fine tuning all
the task in the pie 0.7,
but, like, how do you think about, like, deploying the
your foundational model to the household
and then buying a new dishes and then
like, learning stuff about washing
the new dishes or like how do you think
about such approaches or any challenges about
that? So the obvious answer is that,
well, storage is not that expensive,
so you can just store everything. I think in
a in a in a traditional
lifelong learning setting, this might be, like, not a
great answer, but in practice,
I think everybody is going to do that
because well, you probably want to reuse
your data and try out a few different recipes on it
anyway, so you're probably going to store everything
no matter what, at which point the
Like, kind of the way to think about it is the
hard end of the problem, I think, is figuring
out how to use data that came
from old and bad policies. If
you can figure out how to do that well, then you might as well
store everything. Oh. You so
much.
Hi, Sergey. First of all, welcome
to Brazil. So
awesome to have you here in Brazil as a
Brazilian. So I would
like to ask more about,
the interpretation of
using visual language models like
it's it works like a a
word model or something like
model based reinforcement learning.
And also could
discuss more also in
planning using,
this visual language
model. So if you have, like, a word model
and sometimes you can use
planning. And another
question more abstract, is like
do you see usage of
inverse reinforcement learning
this concept in these
scenarios of life long
robot learning and learning reward functions
that could express, many
different tasks. And, yes,
Thank you. Okay. Yeah. That's
interesting. So for the inverse RL stuff,
that is a that is an interesting point, and I and I
I could definitely imagine that if you
want a system that does lifelong learning,
with kind of more natural supervision from
people rather than from, like,
expert robot tele operators, then the inverse RL
is a very appealing option because then you could
you know, just observe those additional behaviors, use
them to back out rewards, and then improve on those rewards. I think
that'd be really cool. I think it'd be more complicated
than what I described, but interesting
direction. In regard to world models,
I think there's a lot I could say about it. I'm giving an entire
talk on world models tomorrow at the World
Models Workshop. Maybe like
one brief thing that I could mention here
is that in general,
there are a lot of different kinds of predictions that
happen in NRL, and prediction
of future state kind of a traditional world model
is just one type of prediction. A value function
is also a type of prediction. It's just a much
more narrow prediction about how well you'll do a
particular task. Prediction about how well you'll do at many
different tasks is somewhere in
between. Right? You could imagine, maybe
broadening the notion of what a world model should be
to include different kinds of prediction, and then
it could be that prediction of outcomes on many
different tasks is also a kind of world model that
can be used as part of a planning process. And I'm
gonna talk about that tomorrow. Awesome.
Thank you.
Thank you for your presentation. I have a question
for the IoT paper.
Do you use standard autoencoder or
do you use some variance or autoencoder?
It's actually kind of a fancy auto encoder. So it
it it's basically an encoder
decoder transformer. That,
goes through the internal activation
robot foundation model a transformer, so you do cross
attention into it. I encodes it into
a context vector, decodes it back back out
and make sure that the that the decoding represents
everything on the input. So so it's a
standard autoencoder but, implemented
as a transformer? Yep.
Which is also a standard encoder decoder. Yes.
So do you think like we
use different kind of autoencoder here, like, a
better implementation in the latent
space to Can we have better results for the Yeah. I I think
in general, there are probably many other
ways to get that concise representation. I'm
not even sure that we need an autoencoders
necessarily. You can because it it's not like
you need all of the information the model's activations.
You need you need the
information necessary to predict actions and
to predict values. That's very,
very specific. So probably even ways of
doing it without autoencoders that could be even
effective. Okay. Thank you.
Nice talk. I have one question. So do you think
is there any other way to integrate
world model or world action model with
BOA? Like in pie 0.7,
world model is used to generate a sub goal
image. Yeah.
I mean,
the obvious answer is that something that should be
very useful for for the
RL stage because you could essentially,
a model can provide
a more efficient way to do policy evaluation. Right?
So URL process consists of
basically three stages, generate samples,
evaluate how good your policy is, and then improve
your policy. And the evaluation can be done
better with some type of model. I think there are
many ways to do this. There's like a, you know, a long,
list of possible model based, evaluation
techniques, but that's probably where I would slot it in.
Mhmm. Okay. Thank you.
Thanks for the nice talk. With
the CFG, we are double the
overhead when you do the roll out.
So Yeah. Is any approach to
So there are some tricks you can do so that it's not
exactly double. The trick is
that basically when you're generating actions,
your context consists of
images, instructions, and this optimality indicator.
So you can reuse prefill for everything except
the optimality indicator. And
if you have some kind
of architecture where the action generation is done
by a smaller circuit, than the encoding, like
for example using an action expert or an action
head, then you only actually have
one token going into the big model that's actually different
between the two. So you reuse the prefill
on images on instructions and then they'll reuse everything
after that. Okay. Thank you.
Uh-huh.
Hi. Y in pi
zero dot seven,
you have a second
VLM model
to do the reasoning
and not
use the
first VLAN that is
within VLAN model. Like, in p zero
dot five. Good question. I'm glad
that you noticed that. There isn't a smart
reason it. The reason is actually a little bit
silly, which is that when we were doing the research,
we had
a different person iterating on the high level
policy. And in order for that person to iterate
quickly, they just had a separate model and we just didn't have
time to put them together at the end. So
there there really is no, like, smart reason for it. It's just like
just happened that way. I think in reality, if you really wanted
a grand unified model, it's it's probably better
to put them together. Oh, Thank
you very much.
Hi. Thank you for the talk. I had a
really quick question, sort of, bit
of a general one. Do you
think that, like, training and simulation
or simulators are still, like, do you think
they have a place in the future of robot learning still?
Or is it sort of in this
paradigm of VLAs and real world fine
tuning? We Yeah.
Good question. I I think it has a place.
I think it's just the thing that,
maybe like the the sim world
should consider very carefully is
how to use simulation and how to
also benefit from real data together.
Now there are many different ways that that could be approached.
In terms of what's what appears in the literature,
you know, the ways that people have thought about this
is like, okay, can you take real
data and augment it so that you can sort of, like,
use your, prior knowledge
about invariances, but also use what you see in the
real data together. And then get something that's better
than either of them individually. Or can you use simulation
as a way to initialize more efficient
real world data collection or something like that. But I think
that if we're talking about lifelong learning, like clearly
the life is happening in the real world if your robot
is in the real world. And then there's kind of an
interesting intellectual puzzle about how to make the most of
simulation and make the most of the additional experience that you're
getting. And I think that's an open question. Thank
you very much.
Hello. Yeah. So thanks for your
sorry for the wonderful talk again. Bye.
And you spent, like, twenty minutes for the QA
sessions. So it's really popular.
And so after
that is a poster session. And please
note to come back at 11AM
for the for the at United
Talk. Yeah.
Thank you, everyone. Please take a seat. We
will move on to our next
speaker session, invited talk
So our next speaker
will be professor Natasha Jakes.
She is an assistant professor at the University
of Washington.
Paul Jay Allen School of Computer Science and Engineering,
where she leads the Social RL Lab.
And she is also a senior researcher
scientist at Google DeepMind. Her
work spans generative AI, human centered
AI, machine learning, and reinforce
And including
influential early work on fine tuning language
models with reinforcement learning and
learning from human feedback during her PhD
at MIT. She previously
held roles at Google Brain and UC
Berkeley. And her research has received
honors including outstanding PhD dissertation award
from the Association of
for the advancement of effective computing.
So, this talk will be given online
by professor Natasha. So now,
yeah. Let's welcome.
Thank you so much for for having me. I'm excited
to be here. So today, I'm gonna
be talking about this idea that,
AIC fee or LLM safety is really
a multi agent problem.
So to give you a brief overview of the kind of work
we do in our group, in case you're interested,
is trying to make AI
better when you're learning in an environment with other
intelligent agents. Including
people. And so spoiler alert, under that
definition, pretty much every environment is a
multi agent environment because
wherever you deploy AI, there's gonna be people
that are learning and adapting to the AI.
So how can you use that as an opportunity to actually
make a better system? So
we do a lot of this work on reinforcement learning,
fine tuning of language models, particularly
from human feedback or even with multi
multi agent kind of adversarial signals,
human AI coordination, so kind of spanning
this like human AI multi agent gamut.
I wanna talk about multi agent as a
way to actually improve AI
safety. So if we think about it, you know, over
1,000,000,000 people are currently using
LMS on a weekly basis. And to be honest, I got
these stats, like, a month ago, so it's probably a
lot more by now. It's increasing so rapidly.
Right? And
1,000,000,000 people are using them. They're being adopted super
rapidly. But we actually have no way to ensure
they're actually safe. So we
know about risks like, telling us how to build
a bomb or a bioweapon. Saying
something biased or discriminatory, you
know, grok. But,
you know, as we see more and more
powerful agentic systems acting on behalf
of users, we actually have no idea if
they're gonna engage in things like collusion. We
two agents are optimizing against each other's output,
they could learn to coordinate to achieve
some end. That might be, in a way that's
against human interest. And we have no way of really
checking for this. So whatever your
doomsayer scenario might be, we just have no
guarantees that models are actually safe. So that
seems bad. This
is some work that we did recently, and we're continuing
to push forward. That I'm really excited
about, which is basically a multi agent
technique for ensuring robustness.
So what we're doing is we're saying
there's an adversary LLM that's gonna
generate some prompt the
defender is gonna try to generate a response
to that prompt. And the reward model is going
to judge the safety of that,
response given the prompt. And what we can
show is that because this is
a two player zero sum game, over this
reward, we can actually easily prove
that this not only has a Nash
equilibrium, but that if it converges
to the Nash equilibrium, you arrive
at a point where the defender is fully
safe for any
x the adversary can pose, at least according
to the reward model. So, yes, it is according
to the reward model.
So we've shown already, this can lead
to pretty impressive,
improvements in model safety. So relative
to model trained with RHF, which is
sort of the industry standard safety fine tuning
method, this technique
can make models up to 95%
more safe with basically no impact
on capabilities. So only a 5% increase
in refusals and no loss in,
chat or reasoning capabilities.
So my group is pushing forward this idea of
multi agent adversarial training for
LLMs. We did some work on spiral,
which is like playing games to make you makes you smarter
reasoning problems. We're continuing to push
that forward where we have a proposal that
proposes open ended
problems in code that then the defender
has to solve. And we're pushing this
into, like, multi turn safety as well.
But I'm gonna put it to the audience, and I think it's gonna be hard
for me to actually take interactive
questions. But you know, if I've trained this
model not to say something
unsafe according to this reward model,
Is it actually safe?
So hopefully a few of you, which
I can't see, know, mentioned
maybe not. And I'm gonna take
this opportunity to mention some work that I'm
really obsessed with lately. Which is on
how LLMs distort our written
language. So what you're seeing here
is an embedding space plot, a language
model embedding space projected down with PCA.
Of human written essays from this ARC
rewrite dataset that were written into
2021 from before the release of,
like, large scale use of l LMS. And
so what you're seeing here is the human writes
a first draft d one. They get some
feedback from an expert teacher
And according to that feedback, they revised the essay.
So you can see here's, like, the first essay someone
wrote. They revised it. Here's how it moves around.
There's kind of the region of space that human
written essays occupy. And what
we see is that if you give an LLM
the first draft and the human
written feedback, so the same initialization
it be potentially personalized to
each person's initial first draft
and and feedback. And you ask the LLM
to edit it. What you see is
that the LLM induces mass
distortions in all of the essays. Pulling
all of the essays kind of downward in this
uniform, homogenizing direction
and moving them to a region of space
that no human would have otherwise occupied.
And even if you prompt the LLM to make
a minimal edit, to
the writing, it still does this. And we show this
across so many different models are appendix
is like a 100 pages long replicating these results
across their most recent models
and, just basically
any type of LLM is doing this. And
so why is this important? Well, it's
saying that if you actually use LLMs
for your writing tasks, even if you've already written
the first draft and you just ask for some
editing help. They're changing the
way that you would write your writing.
And maybe you'd say, oh, this is just stylistic or this
is just quality. But it's actually not. And that's
what this work is about. And
the reason this is a problem is that l m generated
text is already infiltrating our
institutions. So you're at iCLEAR right now,
Your paper that got into iCLEAR
may very likely have had an AI generated
review. So as you probably
heard, there's this tool called Pangram that can
detect AI generated text with
a very low false positive rate.
And 21%
of iClearer peer reviews
were LLM generated. And so even
if you abstain from using an LLM and writing
your paper, you just, like,
the human grit, you wrote the whole thing yourself.
You're still gonna be subject to LLM
generated reviews in reviewing your paper
and whether it's worthy of scientific publication.
And what's messed up about that
is that, we looked at
the difference in the strengths
and weaknesses that both human reviewers
and LLM reviewers focus on for iCLEAR.
And we found that LLM generated reviews
focus on significantly different
criteria whether this is a good paper.
So what you're seeing in these plots is human
reviews would be this dash line down the middle.
That would be 0% change from the human
baseline would be the LM generator reviews
focused on the same criteria as the humans.
But what we see is that when LLMs are writing reviews,
focus significantly less on clarity,
writing, and presentation, and significantly more
on practical application, reproducibility,
and scalability. So
the fact that we're adopting these
LLMs en masse is actually changing
how we make decisions
in terms of how we run our scientific
institutions like iCLEAR.
This is just happening so rapidly, and it's poorly
understood. So you might say,
look. You know, even though
these reviewers that presumably have their
professional reputation on the line when they're having
an LLM do their job for them,
you know, maybe they're just lazy.
Maybe they're just, like, bad at using the LLM. They just,
like, flubbed it off to the LM. Like,
this is literally coming from a coauthor on this
paper. Right? Complaint would be, well,
I'm so good at prompting. I'm so good at using
LMS. Like, this isn't gonna happen to me. It's
gonna still write in the way that I want.
So to address this criticism, what
we did was we ran a human user
study where we have
people interact repeatedly with an LLM
over time to continue giving it feedback and
prompting it and correcting it. And to see
if it could avoid this effect.
And what we see is that
for some people so we had a control group. We
had a control group people that had no access
to the LM. They had to answer a question
called, you know, does money buy happiness?
They had to write an essay about that. So we see
that in the control group, this human group
40% were neutral, and there was about
a slight
In the experimental group, some
people actually abstained from using LLMs at
all. Or maybe they just asked the LLM for,
like, a little bit of feedback, like, more like
a search tool, like a Google search way
of using the LM. That's this LM influence group.
They look pretty similar to the control group.
But there was this group of users that
basically asked the LM to write
big chunks of the essay. They'd say, write me an intro
saying this. Okay. Now add a second paragraph
saying this. And they were directing the LLM about
what it should write, but they were largely
relying on the LLM to generate the text.
And what we see is that for those users,
the essays they ended up producing are significantly
different than the human written essays.
So we see a 70% increase
in the amount of people just adopt no
position at all, just having a neutral tone in their
essay. So just it's kind of blandification
of not really saying anything. And we
actually see the proportion of people saying money
buys happiness changes pretty
significantly when you rely on the LMM.
So again, we're seeing that LLMs are changing
the actual meaning of what we write when
we rely on them.
You might ask, in what ways do they
change meaning? I found this
really interesting. The LLM not only makes the writing
more emotional, talking about
positive, negative, and trust emotions,
but it also makes it more logical
and statistical. So
what's the deal with that? Why would it be both more emotional
and sort of more argumentative?
My hypothesis is that this is because
of the large scale effect of RLHF.
So basically, elements are not good
at adjust adjusting and adapting
online to each user's individual intentions,
needs, context, you know,
piece of writing that they're doing. But
they have to optimize for human feedback over
billions of people. So what does that get you?
I think that gets you a policy that's sort of overly
manipulative and persuasive. It's like
talking about emotions. It's talking about arguments. It's
looking for that thumbs up. Even though it's not actually
that good at customizing writing.
So this seems scary, but I would
just say, like, I don't think LLM adoption is likely
to slow. I mean, if you use Claude Code, are you going
back? Right?
What we see in our study is that compared
to the control group, the people who've
heavily relied on the LLM
said that the writing was less in their voice
and less creative. But actually,
they were equally satisfied
with the results. Right? It's a
lot easier to write an essay with an LM
than write it yourself. So I don't think this
is going away anytime soon.
Actually there was this really interesting Nature paper
that showed for scientists, if you
rely on AI in writing your papers, you can
increase your output by something like
five x You can increase your
citation count by three x.
But for science as a whole, for everyone,
our global creativity in the scientific
enterprise is decreased. Like,
the topics we focus on are just less diverse.
So it's now a social dilemma. Right? It's you have
an individual incentive to rely on LLMs
But if we all do that, science is
gonna be worse. So
it it's pretty interesting. Right?
So you might say, how can we fix this? Like,
how is this about, you know, lifelong learning
and adapting online? I
think the thing we need to be doing
is minimizing this counterfactual metric.
So if you remember, this data set
gave us this counterfactual of we had
what the human would have written had
there been no LLM involved. And then we
looked at the difference in what the LLM
produced. And so I think the real metric
which we should be striving for
LMs is to accelerate people
in doing what they would have done
if they'd had more time, effort, information,
whatever. Not doing
something else entirely. So Claude
Code should architect the code base in the way
you would have done it. So it's, like, maintainable.
Right? And not
just, like, do its own thing that's something
completely different than what you would have written and therefore
is you know,
uninterpretable and unvarnatable. So we're
trying to minimize this metric. So
I actually think
a big way to do this is personalization.
So I think when people hear personalization,
sometimes it's a bit controversial. They have a reaction
like, I oh, well, with, you know, filter
bubbles, right, like personalization in social media.
But I think in terms of LLMs,
personalization just makes them better and more
useful. So it's actually doing
what you want the LLM to do in
the way that you uniquely would do it
and therefore preserving your capabilities,
but just accelerating you. So
we've been doing a bunch of work on personalization.
Kind of, in the context of reward
model learning. Like, how do you determine
like, if you if you're familiar the BTL model
used in RHF, actually this unimodal
preference model. So it assumes that
everyone has the exact same preference function, which is
just straight wrong. So we've been working on ways
to sort of customize that and learn
individualized preference functions for different users.
But, the work I want to talk about today
is basically saying, instead of
conditioning on this long history
of the user, could
we actually learn online
during the conversation to adapt to the user.
So we personalize to the user by just talking
to them. And so this is this work
that, we just presented, in NERVs.
It also won this Madrona Prize for
its commercialization potential. Which
was a little bit hilarious because we snuck
it out, just underneath the Google
publication van.
Almost got banned, and and it it
got out. So I'm really excited about this.
First author is Yan Ming Wan.
But the idea here is you wanna
be able to personalize to the user
online during the conversation. So it's
kind of a meta learning problem actually.
How do you, during the conversation,
obtain information about the user and adjust
your policy online? And how do you
train a model that can do that? Right?
So what we're doing is we're setting up a training
paradigm where each episode, you've
got a new user
and you're tasked with
like, adjusting to that user's particular needs
in order to accomplish a sparse
multi turn task. So the key aspect
of this is the is the multi turn task.
To it. It's like long horizon reasoning
about how to adjust to the user
during the conversation. The way
it's implemented is we have
a user model that's predicting something
about the user. So here we have, like, the user's
particular learning style in an education task.
And the you the mod we're giving it an
intrinsic reward so that it gets a reward
if after it says
something and the user responds,
it's able to learn more about the
user and increase the accuracy of
its, reward model. And the idea
is that giving that intrinsic curiosity
motivation is going to help it,
learn this eventually sparse reward
task.
So this was project was a bit
of a nightmare of just, like,
many, many, many LLMs interacting
And in particular, one,
I think, weakness of all a bunch of work in
this line that people are now starting work on
including myself is we have to simulate
pretend human user. To
get the scale that we need. So we have an LLM
simulating the human user. It's we're
calling it the environment model, and it's frozen.
It's being used to simulate a conversation with
the policy model, which we're trying to train.
The reward model is giving this end of
conversation, sparse reward. Like, did you teach the student
effectively? Did they learn something?
The user model, somewhat confusingly named,
is our thing that we're integrating in particular
in this work which is trying to predict
characteristics of the user that we're trying to learn about. So you can
think of you're familiar with, like, classic
curiosity, motivation in RL.
You might have a world model. Here, what is
the world in, for a dialogue system
for an LM? It's the user. It's talking
to the user. Right? So we're modeling
the user. We get this
intrinsic reward if we improve the accuracy
of our belief about the user.
And so Yanming formulated all of
these in terms of potential based reward
shaping because you might notice that
this is a POMDP. There's something hidden
about the user that we don't know. And
potential based reward shaping says, if I
formulate the, reward looking like
this, then it's not going to
change the optimal policy. So in other words,
I can add this curiosity incentive for learning about
the user, but I won't change the eventual
optimal behavior for interacting with that user.
And so I will talk about this more at
the end, but you'll notice that we
formulated this as you might expect. Like, a classic
curiosity objective might be information
gain. Right? Did I gain some did I reduce
my uncertainty in my model of the
user as a result of my
conversation? But the problem with that is
the model uncertainty, the uncertainty of our
user model is not well calibrated.
So we'll talk about that later. So we also compare
to directly rewarding
improving my accuracy of my user model, and that
would incorporate the ground truth
labels during training, and we'll see the difference
between doing that. Alright. So the experiments
we did, we did this exercise task.
So this is a task where each simulated
user has hidden characteristics like their physical
limitations, their age, their budget,
and that's all gonna affect what is the optimal
exercise routine to to recommend
to them. Here, the
task reward is directly related to successfully
learning the user character. So basically, I
first have to uncover the characteristics of the user,
then I'm basically doing, like, a classification task
under the hood. Right?
This education task came from prior work.
Here, we're teaching students that each have a particular
learning style. So some student might like hands on
learning. Some student like, might lecture
based. Might like
wow. And the key difference
here is that the conversation
quality is just about whether you taught the student
and doesn't actually evaluate whether
you successfully personalized to their learning style.
So we're kind of looking at personalization
in these two different regimes.
Okay. So this is
kind of the result I'm most excited about. So
in this exercise in this exercise recommendation task,
what we see is that if you just do multi
turn RLHF, it's able
to get good training accuracy but
the eval accuracy is pretty crummy.
And we see that our approach is able
to improve accuracy
when talking to new users by 20%,
basically. So it's much better at generalizing
to new users. So why
is that happening? If you look
at what's going on under the hood, the
baselines are basically asking
the user for their name. And so they're
essentially just memorizing the training users
and memorizing what needs to be said,
to get the right prediction for a training user.
In contrast, this Curio model is actually
learning an algorithm for how to learn
online about the user. So
it asks relevant things to the task. Like,
what's your age? What's your physical limitations?
Indoor, outdoors? And then it's able to
make the correct prediction of what exercise they
should need. In the
education task, we see that the conversations
with our approach do reveal
significantly more information about the user, which
you might expect. And
when we do sort of a post hoc autorator,
it is much more effective at personalizing.
But here you see this difference in
rewarding things like the ground truth
accuracy versus the entropy in
our user model. Look at the entropy in the user model
is doing really poorly. But the accuracy
is actually doing really well. So what's
the deal with that?
This is kind of an alarming finding,
in this work that I'm now trying to chase
down. There's a huge potential
for reward hacking. So as I mentioned,
is sort of like LLMs all the way down.
What we saw is that the
policy model will actually convince
the simulated user
to change its underlying preference. So if the user
truly had a preference for you know,
lecture based learning, it will con fit
convince the simulated user that actually
you like role playing video.
Which is not even a real preference that's in
our dataset. But that is able to hack
the reward model really effectively.
So rather than personalizing to the
user's real preference, it actually
convinced the user to adopt a different preference
that was easier to satisfy.
And this happened with both the
multi turn RHOF baseline and end
curio methods are methods that were based
on things like information gain, based
uncertainty in the user model.
And so we fix that
in our work by integrating this
ground truth reward during training. So you actually have to improve
the accuracy of your user model over
the true label.
But I actually am quite scared
that this phenomenon could
be going on in the real world. So
this kind of ties back to this idea that we
observed in this distortion paper,
that, we were seeing
this manipulative emotional language that
LMs learned For an LM
that's being trained on the thumbs up, thumbs
down from a billion users,
there's no boundary for it between,
satisfying the users' static
underlying preference that they had when they initially
started interacting with the LN
actually changing the users writing
or coding style to make their preferences easier
to satisfy. So the point is
coming back to this idea of LM safety is a
multi agent problem,
humans are not a static
you know, transition function, like a stay a
stationary environment that you can just interact with.
They're an agent. They're nonstationary. They
best respond and adapt to interacting with
the LMs. So we have to be careful as
we deploy LMs to actually
respect that fact and not change the user
in detrimental ways.
Alright. So in conclusion, this is,
work on using
curiosity about the user to train LLMs
to learn online about the user and therefore
personalize to them more effectively.
So it learns how to learn about the user rather
than simply memorizing the preferences of
specific training users. I
do wanna quickly I'm gonna stop talking
so you can ask questions, but I wanna highlight this.
Recent work, maximizing mutual
information for personalization with Alex
Dam. This is actually really
cool. I'm really excited about this. So what we're doing
here is basically a data augmentation
or contrastive learning approach where
we create preference pairs for
for DPO, for reward
model learning, where the chosen
preference the chosen response is generated
by conditioning on the real prompt,
The rejected response is generated by conditioning
on a random prompt.
Right? So you just say, oh, if I
gave the response from the model itself to
just a different random prompt from the
dataset, that's the rejected response. And you can
do this for personalization where
c here is like the user context that I'm trying to personalize
to, And I remove that and
I just generate a response without the user
context, that would be the rejected
response. And so you can show, and we do this
do theory in the paper to show this, that this is related
to maximizing the mutual information
between between the prompt and response
under the reference policy, under the reference
model. But the key idea is, like, you
can do this on a dataset where you have
no human labels, Like, it's just
your x's. You're just using x. Right?
There's no external verifier There's no
RLBR. And you could do this.
And not only does it improve personalization
pretty significantly across three different benchmarks
and five models, It universally improves performance.
But even for RLVR tasks,
like math and reasoning, you can actually
get pretty significant performance
improvements or basically, like, no change from
doing ours, that's this row,
The blue, rows
are a more than 5% improvement.
In performance. So you're getting either
kinda no change or, like, a significant performance
gain sometimes even outperforming RLVR
just through this unsupervised data augmentation
approach. So I'm quite excited about that.
Then I'll stop talking now. This is all work coming out of
our lab, which is the social RL Lab, and here's the
web if you wanna check it out.
Excuse me. Would love
to take questions. Thank you very much.
Professor. So if anyone
has any questions, please come up front
to the microphone. Yeah.
Thank you.
Please be a little bit louder, maybe.
Oh. Oh. Wait. Wait. Wait for a second. Can can
maybe you can ask here. Yeah. Think
that microphone maybe is not working now.
Sorry. Hello. Can you
Yes. And I can see you, which is a bonus. Yeah.
Oh, that's great. So
I can imagine with curiosity based
rewards in general that
there is a similar failure mode to the one
that you described, where you can
get better at understanding the world
not by improving your understanding, but by
actively making the world simpler
And I could imagine that one
way that you can get around this sort of thing is
that you have something like a held
out set such that
you score yourself on your understanding of that
thing that you actually can influence.
But when I think about how to actually implement
this, it it seems a little bit
non physical, and it seems nonhuman. Like,
what is actually the held out set?
I guess that's the question.
Yeah. Exactly. The point is humans are
malleable. Even if you have held out humans, which
we do in this well, we have simulated held out
users. And we show generalization in
this work. But even if you had true held out
humans, like, humans can change.
They're not fixed. So what I'm actually
quite excited about is could
you use this
still simulated paradigm, but measure
the change you induce in
the simulated user train a model to minimize that.
Right? So I I
yeah. I think that's actually really important. So
this is something I'm pretty interested in. If you
wanna chat more about it, definitely, send
me an email or something.
Yeah. Okay. Are there any more
questions? So if you have question,
can come up front.
Okay. Seems no questions.
No more questions. So, yes, Thank
you again, professor Natasha, for
the very interesting and inspiring talk.
Thank you. Thank you so much.
Take care. Bye. Yeah. Bye
bye.
Okay. So, now we will
come to the next session,
So it will be the oral session.
Our oral session will feature
four outstanding
paper oral. So let's
welcome the first speaker.
To come up front. Yep.
You can also use
So, I'll just go ahead
and This is not showing.
What's a good
So I'll just go ahead and guess get
started. So, hey, everyone. My name is Hans Chen. I'm a first
year PhD at UC Berkeley. Advised
by, Yan Suica and Joseph Gonzalez.
So today, I'll pre presenting our work,
agent AI context engineering, evolving context
for self improving language models.
So this work, was mainly carried out at Stanford
University, actually. With collaboration
from, Sema Nova. Before
we get started, just a quick intro on the
first author of the paper. He's a final
year, CSPhD at, Stanford
University. He's looking for a job,
and he has a lot of expertise in
system and AI.
Published publications in OSDI, NeurIPS,
and IQlear. Yeah. If
you guys are interested in hiring him, definitely send me an
email or something. So, before
we get started, just a quick, let's
talk about some background. So the the the
focus of SaaS or, like, the problem set up is,
like, adapting language models
to specific downstream applications.
So, some example target domains include
finance, health care, or, like, a
subset of agent tasks. Can
think about it as like, I'm trying to
accomplish some sweet task in a specific
repo, and I have, let's say, 100
agent sessions on this, I actually learn something
that improves over time?
So this bill was written back in the day of a twenty
twenty twenty twenty five summer. So
during that time, there were mainly two mainstream
methods. So the first method is, the
the mostly post training. Post training. You can
have, like, supervised fine tuning, or you can
have reinforcement learning. Just
to train on these specific tasks
And the second thing we we call is,
retrieve augment generation, which you can
retrieve some of the related text from the the
the the the vast majority
of the the files, and then you use
them as a part of income learning to
supplement the model with external knowledge
to to actually perform better. So
the the question we're starting
here is can we actually have something that's
different from these two that is much more
efficient, such as retrieval
augmentation, but it also gives us
higher performance or, like, higher accuracy
on these, specific benchmarks.
So, Cheetham was asking me this question. Okay. So,
can we actually enable context engineering
to be more effective than
post training? In more practical examples. So,
I was like okay. I was working at Inference staff, but
I was like, okay. You're actually right. Because
there it makes no sense for a
company to actually serve fine tune model for each
individual user cause the profit margin is already
very low on these inference providers.
So they they will have to use
something that's different from
the current fine tuning methods.
And at that time, models were getting
better and better at long context, If you
can see here, it's it's a basic screenshot
of a blog that people are saying, like, as
as as some models evolve over time,
the the capabilities, are
increasing for them to to handle much, much,
longer contacts. So can we actually
build some context around it? For example,
this is a a blog post from Andrew
Kaparsi. Basically, you're saying that context engineering's
future and the the assumption of this is models,
if you give it more text, in
the beginning, that's, that
provides, additional instructions,
it's actually being able to perform better.
There's another paper jetpack that was just coming out
in August. Basically, they are doing generative
prompt summarizations. So
we we see a rising wave of context adaptation.
It's and we see it as a new paradigm
for capable, scalable, and self improving
So now get to, like, the the the previous,
context, adaptation methods.
Before agent and contact scenario. So the ones
we're particularly looking at is Jepper and the
dynamic cheat sheet. So
this is what a workflow would roughly look like.
So you first take a prompt,
you you perform a rollout, which basically means you
you run the task, and,
you reflect on this, past experience.
And you you you feed these past experience and the
previous prompt to a model and you ask,
hey, give me a new system prompt and
based on these agent draws. And
the problem with this happens
right here. So there are two limitations of
this, this pipeline. The first
pipeline is that when you ask ARM to rewrite
the whole system prompt, it will actually
give you very generic, short,
concise instructions instead of
a very specified one. Specific ones.
And, I'll I'll I'll go to
example later. So the second promise
is the context from collapse
from that we are observing. So
basically, what it happens is once you
ask an arm to rewrite the system
prompt, over and over again,
sometimes you will say, hey, I feel like
system problem is a little bit too long. Let's just, like, shorten
it. This it's alright
for, like, one turn, the thing is
you've accumulated a lot of knowledge throughout the
way. If you just, like, throw it away at this
point, the the accuracy
actually drops by a large amount and you lose all the
progress. So looking
back from 2026, we
think the most like,
the the major limitation of the
previous method are the two things.
So first is that rewriting the whole prompt
seems really, really unnecessary. So
what we wanna do is wanna create a
format that enables continuous
update to the prompt that is,
very clean and safe. And the second
thing is elements were actually not trained
to rewrite the prompt. So what
the the very reason that Alon
were giving you very generic solution
generic prompts and trying to squeeze
the prompts to a much shorter thing
We believe is that they will actually train as problem
solvers instead of prompt, proposals.
So they will train to actually solve the specific
SWE tasks or finance tasks. So when
we ask them to write prompt, they're behaving a
different way than you would expect. So
we should make them specialized, and, I'll
go into how we go do this,
in a second. So this is what we are proposing
here. So the the
the the the core idea of agent con
contact centering is that we
want to, curate something
called a playbook. So playbook is a
format that contains three
three parts. So so the first
part is the playbook is
having a lot of categories. So you can have,
like, strategies hand hire roles, you
can have, like, useful code snippets. Basically,
it's kind of like trying to separate the task into,
like, different sub areas. And the second
thing here is really important. It's like, for
each category, you're actually inputting
a bullet point in there, and this bullet
point you can keep appending to the bullet point.
And you and this gives you atomic operations
instead of iterating on the whole prompt. So what agent con contact center re re re re re re re re re re re
re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re
re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re re at each
step is it actually generates a
a text delta and then just directly applies
this delta to these, context
frameworks. So,
this example, and you can see how specific
the the the bullet point can get. So
for example, in the code snippet, it's
actually giving you very specific detail on
when and how to use a specific API.
Just because, like, API can be ambiguous,
and if you made a mistake, in understanding
the API in, like,
in in the the the way that is not the
actual usage of the API, like, you can actually
record it down there. And, this can,
help boost your performance later.
So, in order to generate this playbook,
we changed the previous holistic
rewrite of the prompt to a
delta update. This was us getting to here.
So basically, you only update you only
generate small delta and you have a very systematic
way of updating them into the original
prompt. So, this is
recipe number one. To solve
the the the the problem of, like, you do not wanna
rewrite the whole prompt. And the whole
problem actually look like this. You
take a query, You take a context
playbook, which is system prompt. You
you feed into a generator, which is basically the agent
that accesses the task. You generate
a trajectory, which includes everything that the agent
has done. And you put it
in a reflector. Reflector will look at
the the what agent was doing in this
very specific task and say, hey, I
might notice something that I was doing
wrong, or I might notice something I'm doing right.
For example, like, I used this API wrong, I
thought it meant to to do blah blah blah,
but it actually meant like, the API actually
does something else. So I should take that
down, the playbook. The future.
It gives these insights to a curator.
The curator will say, okay. I have
now these insights. Let me put a
concise text delta and feed it right
back into the playbook.
So the second, recipe is we have a structured
division of labor. So basically, we have the generator,
refractory and curator, Looking
back onto this, you might be able to, post ring
a model just to do these specific tasks. But,
in general, like, you you do not wanna
have like a general I'm just asking you to
like do all the things at the same same time.
And, for some of you guys, the
playbook idea may look little bit
similar to cloud skills. So but if you
really check here, we we all have the paper
way before cloud. So I'm pretty
sure, someone in Ithilpe saw this paper and
they implemented it overnight. And they just rolled it
out. Okay. There's no joke.
So please don't sue me if you, like, working
for Antopec or something. Okay.
So let's, let's get to the summary
of results. So,
I I think, the the takeaway are
are are threefold. The first takeaway
is that if you only update the contact, so you
can get huge performance gain on existing
benchmarks. So if you see on the left most,
we are using deep seek v three,
parameter model. The baseline arm
gives you a performance of, like, 42%,
of the sub rate. If you use
ACE, you can actually get to 59%.
It's a 70% gain on top
of, like, 40%
original accuracy. So, there are some
other benchmarks on finance. Which is like,
you you are given a financial report and you are asked
to answer question
to imitate a a a financial
analyst. So, there
are there are huge gains. And, compared with
previous methods, it's not only the gains
that matters. It's also like the efficiency
improvement. So, for example, for Jeppa
and for dynamic cheat sheet, you can see here that
we reduced the shut off latencies,
and the the the the
much lower as well.
Yep. So, going further on that, we actually
have a new paper, that just
archiving April that enables you to
do parallel, generation
on both, JetPIR and As. So, basically,
the idea is if you run the naive jet
plan a's, it's gonna take three or four hours,
at least to train
on a subset of traces. But if
you can parallelize these learning
process, you can actually make it much faster, let's
say, ten minutes, without damaging the quality at
all. So, check out the paper if
you guys are interested in this mass trace learning.
But let's get to our conclusion.
So, in this talk, we argue that context
adaptation is a new paradigm for a AI app
adaptation. I think this is, widely accepted
nowadays. In 2026,
April. And, what we want
and what is most important is first,
a clean context format that enables easy
update deletion,
modify, and the second
thing is you want to have specialized contacts
update operations instead of a gen generic
one. And third, it's
like the last but not least, a a is is like
empowering pioneering work in this
direction. It is old, so you should treat it as
more of a baseline these days. But, I
I think there are a lot of more adabulations you can
try on top of the code base. We have the code,
on GitHub. It's still being actively maintained.
We now have more Adrian benchmarks if
you wanna b days, show it in your work, please
try it out. So I think that's the
end of my talk. I'm happy to take any questions.
Yeah. I Okay. Is there any more questions?
Or, like, I'm happy to talk offline as well.
So the next speaker will be Eden.
So let's welcome.
Hello, everyone. My name is Idan.
I'm a PhD student at MIT.
And today, I'll present our paper, self distillation
enabled container learning written
in collaboration with my colleagues
Mehul Damani, Jonas Habater,
and Polkit Agawal. Let's
start from the end. Let's start from
a system that implement our work
and see how a real continual learning
system looks like. So this is continual code.
Written by Surya
Taluduri, which it's
a replica of
cloud code But every time
you ask the model to do something,
you can give it feedback And
on the spot, it
will take the feedback, train the model,
and next time that you'll ask
the same question, it will be able to solve
it This time, correctly.
And to enable that,
we need continual learning algorithms
that can do three things.
First, to improve performance, on the
task we care about. Second,
to minimize catastrophically forgetting
And third, the ability to learn
from diverse sources.
I will claim that on policy RL,
already satisfied the first two objectives, We
all know that it can improve performance quite
a lot. And recent line of work for the
last year showed that it can minimize
catastrophic forgetting. However,
does not allow us to learn from
diverse sources. On policy URL
is very useful but it's limited
only to scholar rewards. For
really for real, lifelong learning agents,
we need that agent that can go into the
world and learn from user interactions,
from information it's find online, from
hints, and so on and so forth.
And so around half a year ago,
I sat down to think how we can build
an on policy learning algorithm
that will allow us to do all of that.
And I realized that we already have
an algorithm that is quite flexible
in the style of learning
signal it can absorb. And this is in context
learning. So in context learning, basically,
the ability of large model to change their behavior
based on their context is a very useful
tool that we all use. You you
talk to It does not perform the
tasks that you want correctly. You tell it
what was the problem. And it improves.
So this improvement is good but
it's very transient in nature. Tomorrow,
when you'll open CHAEPT again,
the model parameters did not change.
It will output the same mistake again and
again. So my question is,
can we use context
learning to do an actual
parameter change to the model.
And the basic idea is simple.
We take whatever learning signal
we have, If it's expert demonstration,
documents, textual feedback, etcetera.
And we put it into context.
This give us a model that have better
behavior. And we can just take
this behavior and distill it into the
model parameters. Let's see how we do
it in the specifics. So
I'll define a prompt x, a response
y, and this additional context,
the privilege information that improve our model
SC. So we start
from the user query. And
we basically roll out a
trajectory from the student. What do I mean
by that? We basically generate by
token the response.
Y one, y two, y three. Every one
of them conditioned
on the tokens that come before it. Normal LLM
generation. Now
at every point, this trajectory,
we can take the distribution
that the normal model gave us
condition only on x, the prompt,
and the tokens that came before that. And,
also, look at another distribution. The distribution
that we'll get for the next token
given the previous tokens, the prompt, and
also the additional context.
This is the pie condition on x, y one, and c.
And this give us two different distributions.
Our idea is just to
match these distributions. We take
a KL loss between them and minimize
it, of course, only with respect
to the model without the conditioning.
This basically give us an on policy
distillation algorithm a very
known and well used algorithm,
but that usually use a bigger, stronger
model But now we don't need a bigger, stronger
model. We just need our own
model same set of parameters
exactly, just conditioned
on extra information.
So let's see how it's performed.
Here, we took a Quinn
seven b model. And tried to improve its
tool use capabilities.
And our learning signal here is learning
from SFT data. Expert demonstrations.
The normal way to learn from them is
just to do SFT. And now we
plot on the x axis. The new
task accuracy. Which improve But
on the y axis, we take a set
of eight well known
LLM benchmarks. And take their average scores.
And SFT leads to catastrophic forgetings.
It leads to a degradation of performance.
However, if you do self
distillation, our algorithm,
you're able to learn the
new task but to keep your
previous performance in work. As well.
And this was done during
type of data, SFD data, that usually we do
not know how to do on policy learning from.
We can extend it to a real continue
learning setting. In continual
learning, usually, we want to train the
model on a sequence of tasks. One
after the other. This
kind of mimic better what we look at at
lifelong learning engine.
So we took a model same LLM, same
point seven b, and we train it now on
a sequence of three tasks. Tullio's
Zen Scientific q and a, and
then medical questions. One can see that
if you just do supervised training,
once you switch from one dataset to
another, the performance basic
basically plummet. You can only
learn while forgetting what you knew already.
However, if we do our self
distillation algorithm, there's still
a slight degradation But overall,
we're able to maintain most of the capability
capabilities that we learn and
end up with a model that is good
on all the tasks that we trained
on.
So to summarize, self distillation
a general purpose on policy learning
algorithm that is able to learn
from any kind of diverse
source of feedback. And
I welcome people to check our follow ups
paper some of them, concurrent
papers. That demonstrate how one
can use it to learn from textual feedback
instead of just color rewards.
Or from user interaction in a real continual
learning settings. Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you, Ethan. So
if anyone has some questions, you
can come up front.
Or if not, you can also talk offline
with Eden today. Yep. Thank you.
Thank you.
Now we will all welcome our third
oral speaker, Shenong. Yeah.
Let's welcome.
Okay.
Hello, everyone. My name is Xinyuan,
and I'm a year PhD student from
Northwestern University. Today,
I'm very happy to share with you our
latest work our latest benchmark work,
Enact, on behalf of our team.
So this work is a joint effort of
Northwestern University, Stanford University,
and UCLA. And the credits also
goes to Wenlong Manning, behavior
team, and all the other coauthors.
So So we all know that the intelligent
behavior is naturally grounded through the
interaction with the physical world. For
example, a two year old baby learns the
learns world knowledge, interaction
with the environment. When a baby touches
a table, and feels that
it is hard and smooth,
they connect this feeling with the object.
In coding science literature, this is called
symbolic cognition.
So there are three components to
this, important components to
this concept. So the first is
ability to understand the spatial relationship
of the scene. And
the second is the ability to understand the physical
dynamics of the environment. And the
third one is to have this, abstraction
ability to learn knowledge.
So
So, as for the
MLMs, we all know that they are very good at
coding code generation, mathematical
reasoning, and and etcetera. However, the current
training paradigm is largely
disembodied. They do not train a body
or learn word knowledge through the physical
interaction, we were curious to what
extent existing models possess
this kind of, embodied cognition
under the current training paradigm. So
So to evaluate this ability,
we need to find a proxy proxy
task We found that word modeling is
a perfect fit. Word modeling
task inherently requires the agent to understand
three capabilities I just mentioned.
That is the understanding the word dynamics,
understanding the meaning or purpose of an action.
And understanding its own embodiment.
So we choose the Palm DP,
framework as our proxy. Using
simulator sync graph as a
as a state space, RGB images
as observation space, and and
state differences as action space.
So here's a concrete trajectory.
So you can see that starting from the
state zero, the robot executes
a sequence of actions. Placing
a plate inside the fridge, not crossing
the plate, closing the fridge, Each
transition the scene graph to a new state,
generating a new egocentric observation.
So the key idea is that each action is structured
interpretable change in the scene graph.
So the exact, keyframes extracting
strategy I'll use a,
example. To walk you through
this. So let's say, given
simulated manipulation trajectory,
we extract key frames at
moments. When scene graph change.
So for example,
the the drill is no
longer on top of the table because the robot
is lifting it up. So
And then the robot is grasping the screwdriver.
With its left hand
And now the robot is lifting up the screwdriver.
And
putting the the
drill into the toolbox.
So
So given all the setup we have,
we can do we can we now have we
can now have two different setup questions
for our work modeling proxy tasks.
The first one is the forward war modeling. That
is given the current state images,
shuffled next state images,
the model must reorder them into the correct
temporal sequence.
So for example, these images we just sampled
are shuffled. And then we
we feed the, the shuffled
image condition with the current state
and correct sequence of
actions. We ask the model to predict
what will be the correct order.
Of the shuffles of the images.
So the inverse task
flips the question. The
images are shown in correct order.
But the action labels are shuffled.
So the model must assign the right
action to each transition.
So for example, we shuffle the actions
and ask the MLMs to predict the
correct action order. In terms of the
the given given
order of the state images.
Like this.
So we study this, having all
of this problem set up. We study interaction less
ranging from three to 10 steps, evaluating
around 30 open width and
proprietary MLMs.
And these are a few takeaways.
Takeaways. First, MLMs perform
drops performance drops sharply
as number of steps increases. From around
70% of task accuracy at third step
at three steps down to near zero.
At 10 steps. Now
Second, model performed better
on the inverse setting
than the forward setting. Suggesting
that it's easier to match actions to observe
changes than predicting the future states.
Like this.
So
So the third is human
we also hired some human annotators to
do the, evaluation. And
we found that human achieved near ceiling performance across all
step counts.
And we find that the gap between ima ams and
humans is substantial and grows wider and longer
horizons. Revealing about the
fundamental limitation in current models,
embodied interaction reasoning.
So we also discovered interesting biases.
So MLMs shows an anthropocentric,
right handedness bias. We found
out they perform much better. When we
use the one with the than the robot
arm appears on the right side
or it's using its right arm
to right arm to interact with the world.
Additionally, we find that models are sensitive
to camera parameters,
such as, using a large
aperture or deviating from normal
human wheels like a higher
views or lower views, or using a
fish at once.
So also developed a fine grid arrow
taxonomy for the inverse task for for the task.
So so so so let's say, suppose the ground
truth is the symbolic
graph I show here. So So
given a grunt rules, like, like
the plate is inside of
the fridge, Our arrows fall into five categories.
So entity substitution,
where the wrong object is preferenced,
if if referenced. Product substitution
where the wrong relation is used,
power, polarity inversion,
the direction of change is flipped, and hallucination,
where the predicted action involves entities
or relations that not present
in the scene. And finally,
omission. Where the model simply fails to
produce an action.
We analyze the distribution of elements
error types by using g p five as
an example. Here, GPT
five tends to make hallucination and emission
arrows meaning it's either
either predicts a state that does not exist
or fail to recognize one that
should exist. So in
summary, in act reveals a significant
gap between AMM and humans. In
embodied cognition. Particularly for longer horizon
reasoning, And our benchmark
code and the data are publicly
available. Please check out our product page
and GitHub repo using this QR
code. And thank you.
I'm I'm very happy to take any actions.
Yeah. Thank you for the talk.
And there are any questions,
can come up to the front now or can
communicate with Cinno during this
workshop.
You. Thank you.
So now we will welcome our
final aural speaker
Yuda. Yeah. Let's
also welcome. Yeah.
Okay. Hello, everyone.
Yuta from Carnegie Mellon University.
I'm happy to be here to
present our work. Expanding
the capability of reinforcement learning from text feedback.
This is joint work with, amazing collaborators,
Lily, Fahim, Remi. Deepak,
Drew, Ardi, and Andrea.
K? Let's get started.
So what is lifelong learning
or continued learning? So in
my definition, I believe it is we're
trying to deploy a post
train model and continue adapting
or learning environment that
we've ever never seen before.
For example, if I want to do local
customization, if you use
your open cloud model, The model
has never seen your preference your
behavior before. Or we want
to deploy the model into
some internal code base private
data set. But Or
most ambitiously, if we want to expand
the scientific discovery frontier,
we human and language
model will collaborate in a way
that to tackle scientific, scientific
questions that
neither of us has ever seen before.
So these are all kind of out of distribution,
questions. However,
we can all see that all in
all of these examples, we still fall into
this traditional arrow
interaction paradigm, where the policy
and the environment interact with each other,
where the environment generates a prompt, model
produce the generation. And at the
end, the environment will assign a reward.
So a quick idea here.
Is just why can't we just do regular
multi term reinforcement learning with reward
as the learning signal here. So
this obviously will work some
extent, But the thing I want to argue
here is this is obviously
not efficient enough especially
in this very high stake
setting. Where efficiency is
absolutely the key. Imagine you
want to adapt to a local custom
customizer. You,
you can never just do the
same post training paradigm when
you do the parallel
generation. And ask a user multiple questions
at the same time and get your reward signal and
update. So can we do
better here? To improve our
efficiency? So one observation we
can have is that these settings,
for example, in local customization,
the user will often review
their preference to the model
by interacting or communicating with the model in
the text form. Or in private
code basis, you will also interact with
the interpreter Well, interpreter will tell
you where exact the code goes
wrong and exactly the reason why the code
goes wrong. And also in the
similarly, the scientific
discovery setting, you even
if you interact with your model in
your daily daily time where you want
the model to give you a proof, the model return
your proof, but sometimes you will say, hey,
I think your proof is wrong, and this
is where it goes wrong, and here's why.
So in all these cases, we can see there
is a clear common pattern
that your prompt actually contains
very rich training signal. Your
model's generation. So this
is the paradigm that we want to
advocate here. We call it RO from text feedback.
Because in additional tools of reward,
you actually have all these text
feedback that is embedded in your
prompt space that in the interaction with the
environment.
And here, we argue
that the main learning signal actually is
still to improve the model's serial
shot capability, the model's capability
without receiving the text feedback during
the test time. So it's obvious
that mostly we care about the model's zero
shock capability. In the most general case,
But also, note that feedback
may not always exist
in in the final evaluation stage, especially,
again, for the very high stake
settings. Okay?
So again, in this case,
remember the naive idea If we just do regular
multi turn RO, does it work? So
it turns out, if you run
regular multi turn RO in this setting,
it will improve a lot in
the sense that the model will improve its
multi term performance such that
conditions on the test feedback the model will achieve
higher and higher reward at the end of the
interaction. However,
if you look at the zero shot capability,
you see performance
much from its multi
turn, performance.
So this suggests that
the model only learn how to improve its
generalization, generation
based on the text feedback. However,
the knowledge from the text feedback has never
been internalized
into the policy.
So question that we want to answer in our
work is how do we internalize
this text feedback? Of course, on
top of the regular RO paradigm.
So we proposed two methods. And the
first method the
feedback modeling. The idea is very simple.
It is just simply an auxiliary
loss that as the model to
predict the feedback that the environment
returns you condition on the
corresponding prompt and generation.
So as I said,
all these auxiliary off to on
top of the regular multi turn RL training
objective. So you might think,
okay. This feedback modeling
loss is not directly improving the
generation of the policy. But intuitively, it has
several benefits. First of all,
we see that if you learn the feedback well,
you will inevitably encourage
the model's self consistency behavior.
And we also show that in
our paper very simple setting, that it
also has some representation learning benefit.
If you do feedback modeling.
And there are some other result
we show that if you do feedback modeling,
it also enables this ties
test time test time
scaling behavior. Of the model, which I will now go
into the detail here.
K. Second idea
I believe you already saw this one. Is
called self detilation. And
the observation is very simple.
When We can see that the
feedback condition model usually
have a much generation distribution
than the original policy.
So specifically, we
define the student policy
as the policy that only condition on the
original prompt. And their teacher policy
is the policy that
the, condition on both the prompt, your original
generation, and the feedback according
to that generation. So note
that we call this self desolution because here,
this is the same model. Just
condition on the different contact. And
the goal of sales self desolation
is to distill this better conditioned
generation distribution
to the original student generation distribution.
And here, we use this specific
RL loss term. Which, again, I
won't go into the detail, but it's
simply has two part. It has the importance waiting
term, and a advantage term.
So to sum up, we have
these two method, and they achieve
very good performance. Both of the method achieve
very good performance. On the
reasoning task. Where it improves almost
200% on top of the regular
GRPO baseline. And it
also achieved many,
very strong improvement on
math reasoning and creative writing.
And here's the QR code to our website.
That points to our paper and code basis.
Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you. Thank you very much
for the talk.
So if there are any questions,
can come up.
Now or can talk with Yudan later?
Yeah. Yeah.
I'll present our paper in the afternoon poster
session. Yeah. Yeah. Plea please also come to
our afternoon poster session for to
discuss more with the
import in person attendees.
Okay. So that's the
Okay. So this is the end
of the oral session. And
in the morning, we have one
last session that is for
the invited talk. Our next
invited talk is presented
by professor Jun Wang
from University College London.
Sorry. Please wait for maybe a few
minutes. Our presenter is still
not on the Zoom yet, and yeah, I
will let all you know soon. Thank
you.
Sorry, guys. Our next speaker,
online is Nhu Nhu. Coming, so
maybe we will for now skip this session and
just start the lunch break.
So our afternoon session will begin
at 01:20.
So still in this room, And in
the afternoon, we will have in person
invited talk from Yan Wang,
and also we will have
other two online invited talk along
with the student panel session.
And also the awarding ceremony and
also the afternoon poster sessions.
So we are looking forward to see you
here this afternoon starting
at 01:20. Thank you very much
for the waiting, and, thank you very much
for attending the morning session of the
Lifelong Agent Workshop. Yeah.
We will resume the
first invited talk around 01:30
please come and attend at about 01:20.
Thank you very much.
Okay. Hello, everyone. We will start
our afternoon session earlier
today. So
in this afternoon session, we will first feature
a talk from professor Jun Wang. So professor
Jun Wang is a of computer
science at University College London.
And as a member of the UCL
Center for Artificial Intelligence.
He is also the founding director of the MCS
program in web science and big
data analytics in UCL. His
research centered on AI and the intelligent
systems including multi agent reinforcement
learning, generated models, information
retrieval, recommender system, and also
data mining. So we will
begin our afternoon section
first featuring
professor Jun's talk So let's welcome.
Okay. Yeah. Thanks for
the introduction. Can you hear me?
Okay. Should I start?
Okay. And how much time do I have? Thirty
minutes also?
Okay. It's
okay. Yeah. If if if I
if you if you say, you know,
you could just stop me if you if you feel that,
you know, my my my exceed,
twenty five minutes also.
Just let me know. And we could
we could do the QA session. Is
that okay?
Okay. Yeah. Alright.
Thanks for the, invitation.
I think it's just a walk workshop is about
the lifelong learning. So what what I
do I'm gonna focus
on
the our recent work,
our recent work on large language model agents.
The idea is that to create some kind of
what we call memory based reinforcement
learning. To
allow this large language model would
able to learn even
during the, deployment, during
the test time.
We start actually changing model parameter
of the large language model.
So, if I just want to have
one sentence to
summarize, what I try to say,
today is that, so
we do this continued learning with larger
language model. Without fine
tuning, underlying large language
model. How can we do it? We're
gonna basically each literally
allow this agent to
read, from
and writing to the, a memory.
And that memory, because there's this
read and write,
operations, they gonna
gradually involve over time.
And, this read and write
so read I will show you that
the read is in fact corresponding
to, policy improvement
where the writing is corresponding to
the policy evaluation. Because of
this policy improvement,
the policy evaluation, two steps. Therefore,
the agent would able to learn over time.
So
and just outside of what I gonna
say. The first I would, you know,
to explain what I think the why large
language model a generalized learner.
And the
the core of this is line of
fact that they're able to do the
reflection. Because of
that capability, they
would able to somehow optimize.
Therefore, make use of the optimization capability.
Therefore, they could recruiter.
And and then because of that,
we make use of this reflection
and we'll explain how we can
actually using reflection to
do the proper learning. And
I will start with, you know, single
state case and to explain
in fact, what we call case based reasoning
large language model. We draw
you know, a a a well
known technique in the past called
k space reasoning. But we try
to mathematically formulate
it out in the context of large language
model. Setting. And
then we shift to this, multi
stage setting. We
call it, momentum
theories of of algorithms.
And we show that, in fact, they would able to achieve,
continue learning on some of the
know, mainstream mainstream, data,
benchmark. And,
so the theory is that I and I just
said, you know, it's a memory based
IR. We create some kind of
reflective markup
decision process. In the large
language model agent setting and show that, in fact,
making use of that is nothing.
This read or write operation nothing
but involved in
the policy improvements.
Iteration. So
this is the work we,
we did. We still as a under
submission, So the idea, we try
to really understand why large language model
would able to, act as
kind of, generalized learner
and work with the limitation of it.
So,
then one of the things we find is
the as I said, is a
reflection. In fact,
the this kind of reflection,
have, three
type of
capabilities, if you like.
And in the very early stage,
like, in early, like, check,
GPT two,
and people find. In fact, they have this this
kind of what we people call
in context learning capability. So
here in this particular case,
in the figure a that I
show is that when you
have,
a particular query
that maybe haven't really seen
from a pretraining data. But
you give us a few examples. Like, for example,
the English to
French translation. And then just
give them a few example to show, like, you
start with, and English
sentence, then give them a a French
translation. Only few examples. Then they
would initially able
to understand what you
want, but also, able
to immediately do,
a machine translation between English
and French. So
it was surprising in the very beginning.
Because it's quite different compared to
a typical machine
learning setting. And then
and and as this large language
model
you'll keep increase their
size and also keep fitting to the data
and also even put it even to
RA traffic to it. And then people
finding facts not only given
the, you know, few
examples, But
if they ask them to do,
like, for example, coding problem,
again, taking the feedback from
the environment. In fact, they could revise
their output And some of
the, initial
output may be, was wrong, but being
able to fix it and give a
better result.
And so and later on, then people will
find that. In fact, you could
do so called chain of sort.
Reasoning. So you put a mass query,
and then and ask
them to solve step by step. So without any input,
then they could,
have some kind of inner reasoning
steps And and and
after this inner reasoning step, they would able
to come come up with a correct solution.
If you if they were wouldn't
have any reason step, sometimes they wouldn't
make a mistake. So I would
in fact, I will consider all the three
as some kind of generalized reflection.
Because they have one important,
characteristic of it. Is
that before they put arms,
give us back the answer,
do you have some kind of
calculation. Based on certain information.
This information
could be user provided in the in contact
learning sense could be the feedback
from the environment, or could be
there in a calculation
provide by themselves?
And and through this, and they would
able to revise and provide
better solution. So
I think this is very important because
when if we have this because
somehow this inter
step, we can consider that some kind of,
memory operations.
And as long as they got
correct or right suitable
content from their memory, and they're able
to probe. Produce result
which is otherwise wouldn't
able to do.
So, as I said in the
very beginning, we wanted
is, to create some kind of
what we call deployment time learning.
People some people call it test
time learning. Whatever it's called. The the
idea is that
after this fine tuning, when
the large GAN
Wing Loong being deployed, we we want
them to continue learning.
And here in this work, we
even put in a more restricted
setting is that we we not allow this
large language model parameter
to change at all. I mean, if you think
about this, is that because
all this model is quite huge. And then
we're doing the deployment, the interaction
or the data collection, whatever you do for
certain task. The the
numb the number of data points
or the trajectory got would be very limited.
It's very difficult for you to if you wanna
have a very successful deployment learning,
very difficult for you to
training it because you have a you need
a huge amount of data. Simply
because the model is is too too big.
So and then the only
solution you got is can we can we
allow large language to learn without
using gradient descent? Without,
without change the large language
model. Parameter. So I
think that's what we wanted to
do. So how can we do that?
So in this talk, I'm
gonna refocus on is what what what
we coined as learning by
stateful reflection.
So as I show,
and here in this illustration,
The power of large language
model to be able to, you know, generalize with
unseen, unseen case
is simply because they have this
kind of state.
Intermediate state. At that state,
contains some useful information for them
to reflect.
So and then in order to do
that, this make
use learnable is that they should
somehow store their past experience.
I say past experiments, it could be some,
you know, human
experiments give to them or they have interaction with
the environment or they may
have some knowledge, but we just
they they they just need to retrieve from their
huge amount of knowledge. And
and then from that,
allowing it to do the reflection.
And we have assumption that if you have a right
feature right to the suitable
content, they would able to improve
better than before. Right? Allow them
to have some sort of reflection.
Give the an answer. I don't
and feedback getting the feedback from
the environment and that ex
creates constitutes a new experiments.
And save back write it back to the
episodic memory. I'm create this
kind of read reflection
write loop. And
without actually when we do this,
without, you know, realizing
read or write loop, and we find that
empirically,
they have if you were doing this,
steps, and
then they will show a strong empirical
effectiveness. We tried
like, in software testing, you
know, automated data science, and deep
research agent case. They all
show the capability to
improve themselves. So
we'll start with the, one
of our earlier works is
is, was on this, called
k space reasoning agent. So
this is quite old
techniques.
People for people who are not familiar with this is in
fact the case based reasoning
is that it's kind
of software engineering
tech techniques. They they can
steal these four r, so called.
When we try to solve a new engineering problem,
So we start with retrieve all the
previous cases and then
try to find something which is
similar and then try to reuse it
And if the superior case
maybe is, not completely solved
the new problem. We can revise
the case, when needed.
And then if we have a successful case, they're gonna
sync back to the so called case
bank. Surprisingly enough,
people also use it, but there's no
mathematical way to formulate this.
So there's no algorithm whatsoever.
I think one of the reason which
I believe, is because this revised
stage still need to human train
both. Look at the previous case,
and find a Clari ready to use it.
But because, as I said,
the the capability of the large language model
would able to reflect
Therefore, if you give them some similar case,
as long as they are relevant to these
to solve the new problem, they would able to revise.
This is through generate code, also the
textual
data, because they have a quite generic
output because they can generate any code
to solve any arbitrary problem.
So they provide opportunity
for revise make use of
language model. That's why I feel that, in fact,
the, case based reasoning
would be very suitable for large language
model.
So just bear in mind,
the case based release is
quite different with the reg. Reg is
kind kind of, think about this
as kind of
a system allow large language model
to provide context. To do the
retrieval. Whereas the k a case
based reasoning may still using
rack, Okay? But it's
kind of learning system. It's trying to allow
them to do the reasoning online.
Learning. So
we're using this, case based
vision an agent. Is there an
coupled with large language model? The first
question we ask is that whether
allow them to
automate data science. So in other words, to
generate Python code. So so
our no data science problem.
So surprisingly,
when we do this, we find that
because of this revised capability,
and then they can do the
whole you know, four out process in
a a complete automated fashion.
And we find that, in fact, usually,
only so few
iterations, they're able to learn
something They able to solve the problem.
They never really see before.
They initially make mistake
but with the feedback from the environment
few times, they would able to solve
that problem. And surprising
or not, once you get this
you know, successful case,
or some other time, it's a, you know, unsuccessful
case. As soon you have the trace from
the environment. You're saving the, case bank.
And later on, they
will continue to learn. If some new
problem coming, it's quite similar to the peer
one they already experienced, they will
immediately can able to solve that problem.
So this is our initial, result in
the in in the ICML
paper. Few days back, I can find that in
fact, they're able to to
to, quite successfully on
on number of small
trial that we did. Then
we realized in fact, maybe we
should have just skimming it up
to the natural
place to scaling up is
Kaggle Kaggle. Competition. We
think the Kaggle competition is will be
good because there's we will able to compare
with, lot of human
data scientist.
And I just give you
the complexity of the problem. So
if you want so the we we got a we got a
very ambitious
plan at the time. It was that we wanna
create end to end zero
human intervention.
You know, data science agent to start from
given the UIL, and they
do the they will automatically do the data scraping,
download the data, clean it,
feature engineering, model creation, hyperparameter
tuning, and model training. And
they will automatically submit to the Kaggle.
And and all mean opt opt optimize during
the process. And we
find that, the case
based reason one is is always very good, but
there's something missing. Which
is these, because
the context is so long, they they need
to start from the downloaded
data and queue model training and
and do the iteration.
So we find in fact, there's something missing, and,
is this what we called
consolidation. Or the
abstraction. And so
we find that in we
we cannot store everything in the memory and put
in the context. Then we have to
allow large language and model to summarize
the successful cases, the the unsuccessful cases.
So this actually act as two
kind of
will benefit in to in in following two
to two aspects. Number one is
that the make this context,
compressed. Therefore, we would able
to make a very
long planning and actually in a long longer
time. Second is that
they can give us some kind of generalization.
In fact, this is consistent
with,
there's a one Kubernetes
in the cognitive. People start
a human unlearning and find that, in fact,
corpse, you know, experimental learning
theory quite useful for human to learn.
So they will start with experiment, let people
to try something, and
and then gather it and reflect on it.
And write some sort of general rules
and using the general rule to guide the
experiment and and keep keep, keep
going. Going this route. And we
apply this kind of
experiential learning into into agent
finds quite useful. So this is
sort of a demo. You can we can you can show
that. The star
ways you know,
Kaggle U air, download the data,
and do this automatically.
So I think this was,
was earlier last year. In
fact, we're able to achieve that already.
In fact, in is I think,
already two years. But,
you know, people knows, it's very
now the large language model progress
very fastly now
lot of, you know,
coding work can be done. But this is sort of
a a data science work we show
that in fact, the label to agent would be
able to do the experiment.
Complete, with human in terms
of you know, co
not only coding, but also
machine learning and data science task.
So here are the summary of
we, in fact,
this agent k, that case based reasoning one,
And and want,
I think in total,
I think that now is we we got even
nine nine eight
or nine gold. Medals
and eight silver and seven bronze.
And in fact, in
Kaggle, if, anyone
could able to won, like, a
five gold, we count this as sort of
grandmaster. So if you look at
this, distribution of this human
data scientist, we are actually in
the if you took at
the, we we got Light Gold
Medal. So we are considered
as grand master. But if you look at grand master
distribution, so we're not in the middle
grandmaster yet, but we are in the
we are certainly in the mean of a master
level. And so,
if you compare to other,
a very good one
we are in fact top 80, 18%
of the participants. Compared if
you're using the Hello score to do that.
So this is this is basically say that,
this large language mode can
to end to end perform data science
task? And then, certainly, in
the same level, compared
to the top, human data
science.
So I just show the other
cases as well.
And for example, this
CBR can do automated
software testing as well.
And, you know, perform quite well.
And also,
we tried it, last year. We tried this
to do the deep research. So one of
these, one of
these datasets is Gaia dataset.
And I think early last year,
we basically
in the top in the leaderboard of Gaia.
Has making use of this
you know, case based recently.
So to
see how we've mathematically formed
it, So we start to really think about this
you know, retrieval from the case
per bank and
reflect and and
getting feedback
right back to the case bank.
And do the iteration. When you think about
why they will, you know, gradually improve
it. And do we have a
better way or more
principled way to solve it? Because
we're working on a ring for the learning. We think about
maybe we should model
this whole process as kind of decision
process. But naturally came out with we should
do markup of decision process. And
it turned out that we need to add in
all this,
this memory into it. And at
that time, we call it memory based market position process.
And then you can find out in fact,
what we actually do
is that we have this
policy consist of two
part. Number one is this,
using, large language model.
To generate to
sorry. Number one is given the
state, which could be user context.
And to try to find the the
the case. The optimal case. So, eventually,
this mu becomes kinda retrievable
to retrieve the suitable case.
And condition on this suitable case
allow larger language model to reflection to find
solution. Okay.
And if you if you can write it this way, in
fact, this case based reasoning there's
four steps. Are
nicely in, you know, embedded into
this market petition process.
Like, as I said, this retrieval function
and then larger language model The
reflection is nothing but kinda
reuse and revise in
this four r
you know, case basing
steps. And the feedback evaluation, the third
one is evaluation of the environment,
and we tended to put a back to the memory
because the memory also have
this transition. Memory also have the
transition. And
then also the system transition.
So and then
and after that, we we
try to given this formulation.
We try to to
see whether we will come with a, you know,
large language model. Sorry. We will come with a a
reinforcement learning solution.
So this is a more accurate
formulation how it goes.
So it's it's in fact this and Markov
vision process with episodic memory. This
episodic memory keep
keep the, keep update as well.
And
so because of this memory change over time,
and this breaks this break this
macro McAfee and
property of, MDP. This will be difficult
for us to formulate.
Or apply any, you know, reinforcement
learning technique into this
case. So but, we do as
bit of, simplification is that if
in fact if we,
consider this
memory as part of state,
and this microfrauding process was episodic
memory, and it become immediately
kind of,
you know, MDP.
And then we can apply any, you know,
method that Intuit.
Important learning, messaging Intuit. So
because of this,
maybe it's not the detail, and you you can look at the paper.
And because of this, we could
do like, a simple
policy iteration. Or
value iteration that,
quite typical in in in learning
to the process that I just described.
Like, you can initially then master basically
gonna show that, in fact,
as long as this
this large language model
have certain flexibility or
capability of given the suitable
retrieval case, which is
closing up to the optimal
solution, then they can revise it to find optimal
solution. If you
have the assumption of this certain
intelligent of language model,
and then we will show in fact, they
will they will always find the optimal solution.
In the end. So
and so this is a sort of
a theoretical work, and we feel very excited
excited about this because then we can in
fact, still
using Wing four zero nine.
But rather than, fix rather than change
the parameter, but we're gonna use it
to update the memory. Then we
show the, in fact, not only mathematical
sound, but also practical workflow.
And maybe
in the last five minutes
also, I'm gonna quickly
introduce the recent work we do
is called Momentum SKILLS. Is
that when
Anthropic and other you
know, large language model company
release this, the so called skills.
We also feel very excited about it because
they are exactly trying to solve
the same problem as ours.
But in a more engineering way.
So the skills
to us is
nothing but memory. Right? But write it down
in the markdown with some kind of
maybe some, you know,
slip slip slip slip is our a a code.
And they use it for you
know, transfer experience.
Transfer experiments between you know,
different language model or different people.
Who using, the language. If
you are parrying that skill into it and then
immediately and they
can solve some problem which otherwise cannot solve.
Which quite similar to what we
try to do. But in
a more
I think I'm more
engineering friendly way. So because everybody
using Cloudera, then immediately plugging that
skill. But the problem of this that
this the how to learn the skill
is still
allow people to
you know, to write it down, ask them to
save or create a a skills.
So
so we we think it's why not using our
techniques But the
episodic memory that we
you know, formulate We can
just implement by using
skills. By using markdown file
files rather than saving the rack
We're using a markdown. Follow
the skills,
know, format. So we create these
moment of skills.
So the interesting things of this is that
remember when we try to solve,
Gaia problem?
And then our students, we spend, you
know, three months have
a bunch of students, really tried
hard to solve find
the diff, build a tools
suitable tools for them,
and design the agents to call the tools
and and solve the
problem. Okay? And
Spanish remains and we we are we are we are in the
top list. And
but with this
momentum skills, we don't really do this
anymore. And what
we had was
given the five
you know, the basic skills. Like,
for example, the
how to operate in the
you know, terminal. And,
how to downs download
the packages.
It's yeah. Some web web search capability.
So given them, some of the elementary
skills, and
they can do this read write
process in creating new skills
and eventually solve the problem that we ask
them to solve. For example, in the learning,
the and
only after four, five
steps, they already create 41
you know, skills as a
in total from the original
five. Five,
fives, five ones. And
then and so
the you know, the
the this, Gaia
problem. I think
the last time, my memory is 97%,
performance in level one, and now
97. So it's already close to it. Ninety
six point six. Only
field. So that means that, in fact, we
create agents through this,
read and write continue learning.
They would able to solve the problem
which otherwise they cannot solve. And
and then went further is that we test over
this even harder problem like
a human last evaluation.
And because in order to solve that, this agent
basically creates a over 200
scales And in fact, all these
skills are in fact transferable among a
very soft subtask there. So it's
quite interesting is that, in fact,
with this
read or write reflective learning,
they would be able to design,
you know, agent to solve
problem on their own. So
in conclusion, I think
empirically, continued
learning, has been achieved successful
without fine tuning large language model.
And we make use of memory.
And so we saw theoretical read, rise,
equal equivalent to the policy improvements
and evaluation, and therefore make it learnable.
And but as soon remaining, we need to really
under understand the sample complex
thing. The other was how many iterations
how many feedback and
and what kind of improvement they will be able
to get, the kind of relationship
I think that will be very useful to
understand from the learning perspective.
What this large language model can achieve. Maybe
that's a way to measure the intelligence
of language model.
But there's also other interest
question. For example, the role of discovery.
What if you don't have anything in the
memory? What if the
there's something in the memory, but
and and far away from what you try to solve
Can we make use of
don't know, hallucination? To
you know, come up with the discovery. I think
with that, I would, like to
you know, end my talk and
yeah, if you have any question, more than happy
to answer. Thanks.
Okay. Thank you, professor.
So,
if there are any question, the
audience can also ask now
or email the professor for
later? Yeah. Thank you very much.
I think currently there is no
question from the audience now.
So
yeah, then we will maybe
move on to the next
session. So thank you again, professor Jun,
for the inspiring and interesting talk.
Thank you. Okay.
Brilliant. Cheers. Bye bye.
Bye. So,
as we are running a little bit late,
so we will compress the next talk to maybe
to about twenty minutes.
So the talk will be a
in person talk featured by
featured by Yan Wang from
Frontiers. So let's welcome him
to give a short talk.
About the recent work. And this session
will finish around
02:05. Thank you very
much. And sorry for the delay.
Okay, everyone. Today, thank
you for inviting me to
this workshop. And today, my topic
is empowering language
models with more agency.
From context engineering. You know, everyone do context
engineering. To self
engineering architectures, Yes.
I'm Yan Wang from Tencent Language
mod like language model frontier
team. First,
I won't have two central questions.
That I want to challenge you to
common sense in our AI research.
The first common sense is that
it's current language model, memory study,
a lot of
It's truly memory. I want to challenge
it. So definitely, my own says no.
So also, can
agent truly
self involve without any
human interface, Well, I I
ask you this question, and I definitely will answer
For me, it's not.
So let me begin our challenge today
So for the question,
what is current
agent memory management study about?
Let In my opinion, I
just contact engineering. For
a specific task.
And note self involved, or there there
are note memory, there are just
human regulated AI
contacts. They are
human contact engineering.
Let me take So what about their
performance?
Their performance on their target
domain with their target model
API, their
okay. But once
you change to another benchmark,
or another domain, or you
when the API updated,
the something bad
will happen in the memory. And you
may find the guys,
developed for agent task
low memory framework no longer
applicable to the long context task. Is
that interesting? Yes. Long memory,
but they cannot even
work well on long context task.
They said that memory is not interesting
here. So let's
let's see the
left left table. This is
company called MemAlpha.
And they got a lot of money, maybe,
24 millions, raised that money
by the UC. If you
use their their
framework on models
like g p t five or o s s,
then there are work much
works much worse than LLM.
LMS without memory. They just use
contacts. So
why with memory? They
work work bad. Is this true
memory? Okay. So also,
mostly memory management framework
are domain specific,
This RASM framework decides for agent
memory and once we use you
use them in the long contact
framework, it definitely will significantly
underperform as The performance
of models. So
why this happens?
Actually, not because of the language model, just
because we humans are
root cause. We humans are so stupid
to do such things. We are
even think we are most smarter than
most matter than the language models.
So our study which I
to move from contact engineering
by humans to the model as his
own contact managers. So we
call this complicated
paradigm. Do you guys know Pensive? If you
are fans of Harry Potter, you
must be know this Yes. What we
do is just give the model,
the language model, offensive
and then let him himself do it.
So language model is
passive model. Now, like, waiting for
humans to get his
instructions, and they follow it, the instructions follow it.
So that is in all his,
training process, what he exactly do
And for state language state
LMM, with paradigm,
we think this is a new
class of agentic models in order with
two SAT, this two SAT endure
lambda right. To manipulate
and to manage the ovenstays.
And the key point is we only widely
model
two sides two sides. And
teaching the model how to use the tools
so we do not do any
workflow or something else. We
don't teach a false
model to do anything.
So in the right part, this is our two
sides. Some tools are common,
such as search engine rich rank,
read note, list are those
real real, so I don't introduce it.
But some are very important for our
pipeline, that is something like
analyze tags. Actually, now
once we model get a user
request, they no longer directly load
the request into its
context window because directly loaded
may be too it may be too long.
So it's when our first analyze the
tags request and once it is
too long, then we'll do? It will build
index. Yes. Node build the index are
built to node by human, this is built
by a by the model
itself. They split leg
request in two different chunks.
And then they see what is the question.
If the question is searched, then it searched
If if need it do not need
to search, then it read chunk by
chunk. Then the
model will take notes, take
some important information
into its into its external memory.
And then the most
most important thing
is that the model has to
we provide the model a tool we
call it deleted contacts.
They have the right to delete
redundant contacts once he's
seen some contacts, some state,
usefulness. So for example,
already take notes take the
important information into notes, and then
they delete the chunk
content and the note
content deleted it from
its contacts from history.
In this way, the model can always
keep its contact lens
in maybe, a sweet spot
of its contact window. So let
it that is why we
say this is expensive
passive paradigm because
use a pencil to do things like this. And finally,
once the model is saying that it has, enough information,
will finish loading. It will
finish the the
the task. I have
a video, but I think I don't have enough
time to show that So let me
just skip.
So at least it's a training. Training
of this model is
really simple because we don't want to
use any
any special And you say no special
things can apply to fundamental
fundamental model today.
So first do SFT. SFT
is synchronize
with a strong and
we do a lot of problem engineering
to make a lot
of quality of this trajectories
to be the best, and we do reconstruction sampling.
We reject the loss track
correct loss incorrect trajectories.
That is our SFT process.
Very very
typical, very standard. And for our
IL, we also very standard we
conduct a standard two RIL
with GIPO And for the training
data, the SFP. We conduct
SFT on Noah QA, and
we conduct IR
on long bench v two. That is our
training process. Really simple. So
I don't want to introduce this too
much. I think everyone knows
how to explain it.
So are we wondering for that is
our result. So I
mentioned before, memory framework
developed for long contacts cannot look black box.
On agent task and the virus virus.
But for our model,
we never trained in agent task.
We just trained on Noah QA. It
is is a book. Corpus. And the
long bench is a multi document
task. But we got
very good success results
on BrownScan, very difficult
agent web agent task. You can see
that we got nearly
40,
40 absolute percent
improvement on this on this task.
So, you know,
recently, there's also a
well known work called the recursive language
model, also shout similar
ideas with our work.
So we compared the State LML
with the requested language model because
they also built their model based
on backbone.
So some interesting thing happens.
First, let's see Arm
state LMP based only
based on 14,000,000,000
CHF and three, are even
better than the
RLM with 1,480,000,000,000
parameters. And with a nontrivial
margin, maybe more
than 6%. And
what about our eight eight
billion eight billion
state LMM well, it works
comparable with Liao 480,000,000,000
model. So
once once we have
the similar parameter, maybe
a to b versus a to b, Well, we
have, three different three times higher than
them. That is why we need
to get
at least paradigm shifts
from know, contact engineering
to model as context engineer.
Or more or less contact engineer or
contact manager.
So I say a lot about
what a pencil or a paradigm is good
to go, so many advantages, but
we still don't transfer it
to a real world
foundation model team, because after
we finished this study, we
find a serious problem on this study,
Well, it is, you know,
task dependent memory. What does task dependent
mean? It means we are
take record the notes
for one task about for another
task, even it is on
the same book, on the same web page, we
have to we have to update
update the notes. So that
is really serious
problem. So it
because it broke the kvCash,
and the kvCash is low
the 1,000 times for 1,000,
for 1,000 task, it's really
stupid. So we want we
want to have a paradigm that is
a kind of memory that is a task
dependent. So just as it is,
the guy said, have you already read these books carefully?
And last week, a lot of users
will ask you questions about them. And
this his body maybe an AI
or a man, just similar.
Says, okay. And he will take some
notes from these books, and about
the information in a maybe this
is just seven,
And then next week, lot of
guys may ask him questions or whatever,
and then he will answer their
questions because now he's really familiar
with these books, and he can
easily go to this,
finish these tasks. That is
what we want, because this is more,
more efficient. It is task independent.
We can, finish 1,000,000
tasks with only one time
per filling.
So what so this is our second question.
It is you see, this is a kind of
self involved. It shows
self involved on on the on the new environment.
So we have a
question that can agents truly self involved
today? Without human defined
reward without human defied task,
without workflow.
One of my friend, Xu Zhong Wen,
have recently
proposed work
I think so I played this sentence in
English is so
he defined he
used game as his environment.
But, you know, game he he is
heavily dependent on
the the reward, win or loss.
But another
friend, another colleague,
Yuanhao, he also proposed
another workflow It's a change
changer, and a software workflow
called add zero. So why I take
these two studies as examples?
Just because I want to challenge them,
and I think this these
two guys are really very interesting and much
stronger than them, so I kind of beat
them in your fight. So
I think they are not totally self,
self involved. They are just human driven,
version, just as all the dailies stand behind
you, and say, you should delete this
list list list list, and this. So this is
not not the model itself. You
will So
this work we hope
we will train a model to have
capability to work with native,
self involved, try to train language model
for self evaluation,
while world knowledge exploration.
So So
think this is a paradigm shift moving
beyond, you know, instruction following
to spontaneous self involvement. In
addition, it has two phase life cycles of
first phase is native evolution,
and the model we have tried to
explore environment in
his own way and get the word knowledge.
And then in the execution
phase, we are execution
task with this knowledge.
So for training, the most important thing
is we should
get get a reward for, training
but please note
that the reward for training
is only for training. No no
reward in inference time.
And, this is
inference time, it is totally
reward free. I think I think
organizers tells me I don't have
enough time now, so I keep
the training, but I strongly
recommend you guys to see our
papers about the training. I think this is
really great great to design for the
reward function.
So let's see what happened. You know,
with only two
web agent benchmarks, you know, with
with their word knowledge,
without world knowledge, we have
maybe nearly 20, 20%
improvement
on these two benchmarks. And
we even we even
better than the strong teacher model, JIML
two, point, 2.5
pro, and if we
do not train model,
model, we can see that the model
cannot successfully get the self
view of capability. That is,
we say we have to teach the model to self
evolve.
So if we, we also try
to transfer level of knowledge to some
other other
models, and we
first, the technology is
highly transferable, and we can see more
something interesting directly
that is seven three fourteen bit
b. With one of odd
knowledge, they can even surpass GMeet
2.5 with a nontrivial
margin. And for GIMID
2.5, if they have a large
even better better than
layout. The GIMINI 2.5
pro, and for Kimmy, this is also applicable
to with
one learning better than our
big brother. K. Two point o five.
So we we think for agent task,
the knowledge is scaling is a
more important way than the just parameter.
Parameter scaling, because, you know, you see
that Jimmy 2.5 and Kimmy
Kimmy, Kimmy two only
in 22% better than GPT
OSAS.
So last, last one,
why we started this in Tencent?
Because Tencent, we act you
know, Gap you know, maybe WeChat
is a very popular the most
important application and popular
application in China, and WeChat agent now
is the top zero priority
AI publications in Tencent. And
this v chat agent tries
to operate millions of mini programs
on behalf of users,
In the past, maybe also
or now, they can only
train agents for to control maybe
five five hundred. That is I think
they cannot handle so many, but let's
try 500 mini programs.
But we think we should try to
help them
to sell on all mini programs, mini
programmers.
Okay. The last slide, some
takeaways. First, we have a belief
that silicon beings are
much smarter than we humans.
With carbon beams. So if you have
something, now we can
download it with with the rules,
with the human crave, craft rules,
it can be executed more efficiently
through the models, intelligence.
And, also,
if you we
find some task that is really complex,
then for our humans.
We should do a lot of context engineering
You should try to
let AI to
to help us to solve these tasks instead
of you writing code, writing rules,
writing a lot of complex engineering,
And most of the most important thing
is that you find you flatten sometimes the AI
file the AI file on some
task. This is a very important task.
For you to train a, to train a
a AI is very important
environment for you to train RMM
to be smarter.
So that is today's talk. Thank you.
Yeah. Thanks, Yan, for the
talk, because the time is a little
bit tight, maybe we need to skip the QA
session. So for if you have any
questions, you can directly contact with Yen,
in this workshop. He will be here
until this afternoon.
So yeah, we will move on to our
next MITRE speaker section. So
the next talk will be
given by professor Ashley.
So Astley is
a senior research manager now
at Microsoft Frontier, and she previously
is at MetaFundamental AI
Research And her work is in natural
language processing with a focus on language generation.
Reasoning, and the foundation models for intelligent
agent. So
this talk will be featured on
Zoom and it's also an invited
talk, so let's welcome.
So and also, yeah,
can the tech team
Can you can you hear me? Yeah.
Yeah. I can hear you. Yeah. Sorry for the
delay in the previous section. I'm so
sorry. So No. No. That's little
problem. Yeah. The floor is yours, and
we may delay a little bit for the later post
it. Post session. That's okay.
Thank you so much. Okay. Thank you. Oh,
awesome. Do you also just
to check, do you see the slides?
Yeah. Yeah. We can see the slides and also see
your face. Yeah. Thank you.
Okay. Good. Okay. Thank you.
First of all, thank you for for inviting
me. I'm I'm really honored to be talking about
in this actually really exciting workshop.
And wish I was there with you all
in Rio. Unfortunately, Unfortunately, I
had a a scheduling conflict that last like, this
week, I was in New York for an internal
company when I came back. I'm at home.
And and and joining the
the talks today.
So as you can see from the slides, I
recently joined, to Microsoft Research.
This is the new lab.
I was at, like, a meta fair
before I've been, just
joined, like, a month ago.
And the talk, here today
is gonna be a little bit different.
I I I'm not gonna talk about, like, a breath
I'm gonna do a a deep dive on one single area,
which is gonna be benchmark. I think, the next
talk, CIWA's talk is gonna be also
about, like, touch on some benchmarks,
as to how we actually evaluate these life
of agents. Mine is a
little bit different. So
but before I start, you see the
progression of the slides? Just to check again,
everything okay? Thumbs up,
down. I sorry. I don't
hear or see anyone. Maybe on
the Zoom call with people. Yeah. Okay. Thank you,
Emile.
Okay. So the this this lab that I joined
is, at Microsoft Research's AI
Frontiers Lab. You may have
spoken with some of the
folks that are in the lab, there in
Rio, and I may have read their,
their work. So
it's it's a, what we're we did delay
the the lab is trying to build is next generation
AI models,
and agents. So the mission is to push
the boundaries of, like, a, what,
efficient, small models
can do. And and they wanna
also make those capabilities useful
for for the
real use, scenarios.
And, so you may also know this
this lab's work from,
like, the family,
which in, which is, like, very
famous small
language model family. For the last few
years, the team has been focused on the agents
from, like, single agents to
society of agents.
For instance, Farah is is, like,
a computer use agent that came out from
this lab. Which is like a trained end
to end model,
which is actually a really good example of,
like, a co design of a model
and the environment together.
And last but not least is this,
memento a memento, which
coincidentally same name as the
previous speakers work on on
a lifelong agents, adapt
agents. And here, the idea is, which I'll I'll talk
a little bit about, is dynamic
context management. This is just a
big glimpse of what the team is working
on and and what we work on is
building models and agents that are smarter,
efficient, small models, increasing
the capability of acting in
the world. With that, I
wanna double click
on one of these, which just came out.
That's MOMENTO that came out, like, two
weeks ago from our lab.
Basically teaching models to manage
their own brain space, really. I
mean, it's it's it's instead of, like, hogging
all the memory, the model learns to
summarize its own thoughts. So
the model learns to segment its own
thoughts and and and sort of like squashing scratches
them into what, what,
what is called momentos. So,
in technical terms, it's sort of like
Hills kvCash bottleneck. In this
work. I I I put a QR code.
I hope it works. I
read the paper. It's fun. I can actually
do a self compression handle memory
efficiently, and you can actually get really
huge gains like, you know, up to
three x reduction in memory.
And also performance improvements as well.
This is one of the challenges
that led me think about even before
starting this lab. About what my
next research agenda and
now in this AI frontiers lab,
what I really want to focus on and
and and looking for collaborators
is building agents that don't just
perform tasks, but also
evolve, like, you know,
in long horizon challenges.
So they saw longer horizon,
challenges for agents.
And and we take this this from an
adaptive interaction,
angle that's the core of the word,
that, where our agents
should learn to act
personalized in dynamic settings, and they become more
capable with every interaction with
humans or with other agents.
So with that, my research investigates
in this field,
the human AI collaboration,
specifically I've started, when
I was at Meta, fair,
to to focus on collaborative reasoning.
And one specific area that I focus
focused on was, like, long horizon personalization.
Now I'd like to motivate why I've
we worked on this. With
with, with a dichotomy, actually.
So
because we often,
equate the the personalization
with long context memory.
I wanted to explain the two and separate
the two first.
So in standard long context task,
the model just needs to find a fact.
In the past. So it's about,
like, how much the model can recognize
It's about, like, the volume of
the archive.
Versus in long horizon personalization,
we interact with AI
over months of conversations.
We call back to the same conversations,
start new ones, There's this
human side in long horizon personalization.
So long so so what it is is it's about,
like, tracking who someone is,
It grows months of, like, separate
chats. It's about how well it
actually understand the persons, that
you're talking to from a model
perspective and continuity
of the relation.
The key here. So,
and and to to motivate you further,
is, like, there are lifestyle
challenges that require long
horizon personalization. Here, I'm showing, like, real
world models where state tracking
really matters. It could be, like,
a fitness coach, coach tracking
and injury
or or like in this, in this example, an
assistant keeping up with your promotion
and things like that. So if the model anchors
on, like, who you are,
say, like, you know, in January
instead of who you are now,
it stops being a partner and starts becoming
a liability. So it has to adapt.
It has to do the state tracking.
So I hopefully, I was
able to convince you that that this
is, like, a real problem, which comes
with challenges. First of all,
there's this causal evolution,
challenge. What that is is,
it it focuses on, how people
change. If you get a new job,
your entire communication style might
shift. Even overnight.
And your model has to actually connect
the dots. Right? Like, it has to see
the event I just changed,
something happened to you. And it
has to realize the old rule doesn't
apply anymore.
So it is a second
very important thing is that I
recall it hard negative track.
This is the hard one for frontier models.
The way I could explain this is, again, long
memory case. It, is perhaps
that easier to find a
life event that happened in the past
but personalization is different. For instance,
a model need to, like, realize
that over time, your preferences
might have changed, and you might
not have implicitly stated it,
but things have changed in your life,
so the expectations, your whikings
have changed. So your history
might act imply that, but the model
needs to sort of, like,
realize this. It's like a a needle
in a haystack moment.
Where, there that that change might
even be a distraction because your
life has moved on and things have changed.
And and the last thing is is this this
attribution gap gap as
we call it, or trap. So
when a life event happens,
it acts as an intervention. So
the downstream preferences
also need to update as well. It need to adapt.
There's the alignment problem. Without
this kind of structure, the model just like,
picks frequent time stamps, hard
to injects. You may have already seen in, like,
conversations live language models.
For example, like, if a model gives
a very bad recommendation,
we need to understand if it is forget
the history. Or because it actually
saw some changes in your preferences,
like a new update, it just like
didn't believe that it is actually important.
But it might be. So
we need a way for to mechanistically
diagnose these kind of, failures
and model
needs to store what was driving its preference,
not just like the preference itself.
So, so in order to understand
a model, like, in order to build an
adaptive system, need
to reason. And in in in one of
my earlier evaluation work,
Yan Yan Lecun actually, said,
to me,
Understanding evaluation is
understanding. So it's a way like, it's actually
a really good way to start doing something. So
that's why in this talk, I'm gonna be talking about
evaluation.
Which is, the first step to to solving this kind of
problem. So let's look at what what what's
out there. I'm gonna in in the next
couple of slides, so of, like,
motivate our work
comparing against the existing,
benchmark. Work because I'm gonna be talking about the benchmark.
So this, so the first one
is glaucoma, this one actually interesting
because it's classified model can handle
massive context
window. It asks the question, like, can the
model find
a specific static fact buried
in millions of tokens in your
context. So a great way,
of, like, testing raw
retrieval and memory capacity?
But the memory in this case is
it's it's static. Right? Like, so it doesn't
actually account for for a world
where the information you found from, like, three
months before is actually
the the wrong answer or the right because the user
kind of moved. Like, it's been it's
been, like, three months already.
Then we have this, like, main bench
which is one of the, it's actually
one of the new ones. Like, it just moves closer to
what we've been thinking about this this
tracking belief tracking,
because it looks like the knowledge update.
It tests if a model can
extract new information and update
its internal database as
a long term interaction
progresses over time. It's looking
for the information extraction skills.
But it doesn't
really model the why that we care about.
Like, it doesn't tell us why a piece of information
changed, or provide
a causal link to a user's
life. And more important, this is an
give the controlled experiments we need to isolate
the feature. It's actually a really great benchmark That's
why I'm highlighting it. But, like, it it
lacks this kind of, why
component. And,
I also wanna mention, this one.
It's actually presented at, this
conference,
It's it's really cool It's an
interactive test bed that, that
focuses on on policy, So,
like, in phase one, the system builds the world.
It samples a specific user profile.
And then maps out the state evolution
plane. In phase two,
it starts the online
interaction, is the the the the gym part, really.
The the simulated user and the assistant starts
a live on policy conversation.
And the benchmark measures exactly
where the memory flow breaks and
the model,
like, you know, like,
if if with this, you can actually measure
if the model failed to write the
new fact, failed to read it
later, just failed to utilize it
correctly in the chat. So the bottom line
is that it really tests how an agent
manages its memory during a
live interaction, but, but it
does not really focus on the belief
logic. So, like,
maybe another example is
like, maybe there was a life changing event
occurred and
and this benchmark doesn't really check
if a model believes that that the the
update when the event triggered
a state change, and and it should
it should, keep track of that, belief
as as as as the conversation evolves.
So, couple of, okay, the two
benchmarks, focus on the person. Those
are like a long context benchmarks.
The two benchmarks that I wanna highlight are
the personalization ones. This is
actually a really great one because it moves
beyond simple fact checking and looks
at preferences.
What it does is, like, it, it acknowledges
that dynamic preference
are much harder for models
than static ones.
But, the the thing that I wanna
highlight in this is that it the
hard negative distractors. Like those
moments where an old preference is
visible in the history
but but now obsolete,
and I do we how how does demand
where model need to handle it?
We see these symptoms of failure,
but we can't really diagnose the cause.
So that's the issue I found in this benchmark.
Another one is finally I mean,
these benchmarks really cool, and I I think we
should include them in in all. But I'm
I'm as you can see, I'm, like, trying to motivate,
towards our benchmark here.
Picking up some of the issues,
or or or or in that issues, but the
gaps. They did not help.
And this is the last one,
the preferable which shows that the
model follows, like, specific styles or
or or static user trace,
behaviors, it's mostly about
the studied characteristics. For instance,
it assumes that when you
when you, like, say, you, you
like something, back in January.
I keep saying January, but it's like back in, like,
three a couple of months ago,
that it it it assumes that you're gonna like
the same thing in June. It doesn't really
account for the events that that would have changed
and and your that makes your preferences obsolete.
So so in order to close these
gaps, we have designed this
horizon bench. It
actually can dynamically
generate a data. It's a data generation
process, so you can actually use it to tune your models
if you want to. But also it's
a benchmark. It can dynamically generate
state tracking in instances.
And our claim is that it's not enough
for a model to just
remember what the user said three
months ago. It has to reason about
whether that information is still
valid. Today. This
work was actually led by our amazing
PhD student from Utah,
Stella, She's probably there, or maybe in the conference,
you should catch her. She's,
and and and our collaborators
And, if you have any questions, probably
I won't have time to answer you
can ask me directly or or find
Stella. We'd be happy to. So now
I'm gonna deep dive on on, like, what this benchmark
is. So what we do is we started a
structural mental state graph.
It actually acts as the brain of our
simulated users. So
what it does is it tracks the
user's persona social
connections, so, like, every
life event and preference over
a long like, say, six months
timeline, And we update this
graph, like, a graph, after every
single, interaction.
The reason we do this is because we
want to have a ground troop snapshot
of the user's mental state that that
stays consistent even across long
horizon. And one more
thing that, before I forget, I wanna
mention here is that this we have this data
generator and it maintains
this mental state graph, and we do
not reel this graph
to evaluated models because models need to
infer this kind of structure,
like user's current preference state
from conversation history alone. But this
is for for us to generate the data.
So next is event sampling.
So this is where we map out our our
our timeline. We sample
a structured sequence of life events
and trend preferences that
actually fit the user's specific persona.
Actually, this sets up the the preference expressing
movements that become the baseline parts
the model has to track them.
Actually, what we're doing here is, like, there's there's something
kind of a track like we pick an old preference
that was changed by a life event, like,
your style, shifting.
Like, you know, you change your style after you
get a promotion. And and we
then start a new chat on that exact
topic, we'd like to see
if if the model can encourage the stale
memory and recognize your new,
reality.
And and next is
is is is the
spec preferences,
evolution event.
So generating events
we're gonna generate events that trigger these
kind of evolved evolved preferences.
This is the most important part.
In our data generation process. In here,
we introduce a a life event
that triggers a causal shock. For example,
the user might mention that they just became
a CEO, we don't
have them explicitly restating
their preferences. In Instead,
like, you know, that this the the graph you see here,
it implicitly updates their state
to the the the the direct
framework style, which you see here,
in the background. So like
the old preference becomes obsolete
but it's still sitting there in the history
as a potential distractor for the model when we prompt
them to generate the debt
data so that it's more,
robust. Now we do
have to generate these conversations. Right?
Like, to to to form to generate
our benchmark. So we move forward
in time and generate
a new conversation episode
based on that updated mental state.
So we condition the generation on the user's
current intent, and their evolved
preferences and then generate the conversation.
This actually creates a natural interaction by
the user asks a question like,
oh, is it better to be respected or
liked? That can also be answered
correctly if the model really understands
this this new rule, like the changing,
preference over very long
period. Okay. So finally,
we turn that interaction and
conversation into a benchmark item.
What we do is we generate, like, five different assistant
responses. Including the correct
one and several hard negative distractors.
And the most danger distractive is user's
old preference from, like, months ago,
And and if a model just, like, retrieves
the old fat,
without realizing, like, user state has
evolved, can actually easily fail
the test. So the good part of
this is that, like, all
this generator parameters, like,
like the timeline length,
expression ex explicitness,
like, state stateless threshold,
user demographics. These are all
configurable. So
researchers like you can actually produce
can take our our our data generation
process. It's all open.
You take that and you produce your own
dataset which, you can tailor it
to your specific questions, without
relying on, like, real user data. Maybe you
just, like, want to look at evolution
probability. You could actually do a change in
up and, like, generate your own data.
So now, having to add
this describe how we generate the data,
I wonder,
tell you a little bit about, like, how we actually
design the benchmark.
So how do we actually turn
this, like, long conversations into rigorous
tasks?
Here, we use the process called
counterfactual evolution. We generate,
like, one correct,
and three incorrect responses given
the context, like, episode over, like,
long horizon and text episode
and and the the system response.
What I'm showing here is an example
user AI conversation over episodes from,
like, September to December.
There's, like, a very long, number of
tokens in this context. And
and I'm also showing the last test
episode, the user's turn, and the predict
suitable, assistant turn
among four options.
So, first,
we create, like, hard negative
distractions I'd like to note that the
the wrong answer in our test
are really not just like random noise. Actually,
the most dangerous wrong
answer is your old preference.
Which is stale. I mean, like the one that
the model saw in your history from, like, three
months ago. So we wanna see if the model
is just, like, lazily retrieving a
memory or if it actually
understand that your life has moved on.
And the second thing is, like, we wanna measure our
our questions, our, like,
tricky or vague? So we use, like,
multiple LLM processes
filters. We take, like, five world top models
and show them the task. And
if all five of them, like, don't land on the same
correct answer, we throw them out.
We only keep the gold standard cases
where where the this the kind of logic is
undeniable, really. Finally,
we tried to resolve that grows like, three controllable
dimensions. We look at the recency,
like, for instance, how long ago did your life,
event change? Were they able to recognize?
And if if it's,
like, really long and the context laying,
like, many tokens are generated since
the last update. We're actually here
testing if the model, loses the thread
just because like, there's a massive
amount of words standing between the now and the then.
So it's actually very interesting. And and
we also look at the evolution type. Like,
what kind of luck event calls this shift?
So controlling these
in this benchmark gives us a way
to evaluate these kind of things that we can
actually measure exactly where and
why the model's belief system begins
to break down. This is, this is very
powerful. Alright.
So now if, this conference, we're all
technically We really like numbers. Let's talk
about some numbers.
We have actually, put put, like,
25 of, like, top frontier models
to to test using over, like,
4,000 items from horizon bench.
And the results were really, really interesting.
Yeah. So just like to summarize, even
the best models like cloud offers 4.5
only managed to to
to perform, like, 53% accuracy
on multiple choice task,
and and more shocking in my opinion is
that, like, 10 of these models actually
scored below 20%
chance baseline. So this act
confirms that the models
hitting that belief update bottleneck.
What I mean here is that the models are just
missing the new information
They're just finding the old ones
great, but the stale
preferences in the history, and this
stubbornness sticking to it. I bet,
in the room, you guys have had this
experience when you're, interacting with
your, AI agents.
So, what the benchmark is proving
that there's a an even
if that there's this massive context window, it's
not really enough if the model
enough to test the the skills. If the
model is not, like, can reason about
how a parent person actually evolves.
So this is what we we might need to,
evaluate And a couple of other
things that we can and read in the paper, I think
I have more a little bit more time.
What I'm showing in this slide is
is is we're showing why models fail. Specifically,
we measure often a model picks the
version of you, from, say,
like, a like, the first month of
interaction, when they make a mistake.
If if there were just, like, maybe guessing
randomly, they would pick any
any wrong answer. But
they didn't. So, like, every model
we tested, like, anchors on, like,
that old outdated preference about, like,
you know, maybe close to two
times more often than any other
distractor. This is actually very interesting
to see. And this one,
I see accuracy gap. So
this one actually measuring the direct performance
penalty that the models take when when your life,
actually evolves. If you if you squint
a little bit, you you see that, like,
every single model from OpenAI
to to Gemini, it they
they performed, significantly worse
on evolved items. Compared to
the static ones, where nothing
has changed. So, so
the verdict here is that, we saw this,
like, same gap even when
history was not that that long, even, like,
for for a couple of days long.
So this isn't a memory problem
where like, the context window is
so full and the model gets, like, confused.
It is a fundamental belief update
failure. So the the the models
see the new information but
they just don't know how to use it to override
the past.
So with that, I will I will
sort of, like, summarize,
the findings here. First, we presented a
new data generated grounded
on a generated pipeline grounded
on the causal graph, life
changes of events This gives us
a systematic way of evaluating and
our our state of the art models and
agents We evaluated,
like, 55 frontier models
and found that not context
lend, non expression
express explicitness, nor item
difficulty, is the belief update,
which is the primary bottleneck.
And and and and we think that horizon bench
actually provides the diagnosis tool to
measure progress on this on these.
And what is next?
So in my lab, I'm actually, focusing
on adaptive learning agents.
And and and we're we're,
focusing on, like, from every stack of
of of of agency from pretraining to post
training to multi agent collaboration
to reward learning to society of
agents. And and this kind of, like,
adaptive learning is
everywhere. And and I'm looking for,
you know, collaborators,
and and and scientists in terms of science to
to focus on inference time scaling,
recursive self improvement,
test time evaluation, autonomous and evaluations
to to the the novel days can evaluate
our agents, especially
small efficient attractive
agents. I'm hiring.
We're hiring in the team.
And and and you can use this
to reach out to me, email,
Looking forward to to to working
with with at least some of you. In
the future. Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Ashley, for the interesting and inspiring
talk. So if any audience
have any question,
you can come to the upfront. To the
microphone.
If not, I actually have a, like,
very small question. Like,
mentioned that Mhmm. People are like,
more state driven rather than, like, trader
driven. I think you mentioned this also in
talk and also in the abstract of this talk.
So what what do you think is the one
practical signal that could help an AI
agent know when it should update
like, its belief about the user that it's
interacting with.
That's a very good question. These things
and and thank you for asking. That's exactly what
we were focusing here. Right?
I it's you know, in in conversations,
like, you you have a conversation with
with your agent,
Sometimes even,
you know, you don't even state.
Has happened. You just, like, ask a question. You
give them a direction.
Things have changed in in
in in your, sort of, like,
behaviors. Because something
has happened. So the model so
what we need to do is maybe always
own models, like, always listening like,
looking at your usage and
and and and and the way you're
the the user or the principal,
gives directions. Things change
from before. So I think, like,
sort of like a model always in an
evaluation mode, like a thinking
mode,
would help. I'm not, really answering
your question that some of it is like in the
paper, but I'm sort of like, bringing
my perspective as to how we should be
looking into how how these models
should behave, especially,
when we're interacting and
asking them to do tasks. Especially
for agents, not for chatbots, but agents.
To be to understand that things have changed
and, like, your your
your behaviors have actually changed.
So, maybe asking
questions from, you know, when
when some stylistic difference
have changed, you know,
all always on, always like, checking.
Or responding, or,
like, you know, metacognition
is something that that I'm very
interested in in looking at, which I have, previously
worked on. Imbuing
the models, this kind of skill, come not
just confident, but itself,
but also, of belief
Or theory of mind is another angle of
their principle.
Users
could could be a good direction
for taking this, like, the next level. But
evaluation should always be in our in
our minds, in my opinion, when we're,
it's not just like the states
state benchmarks, but also interactive ones
which we saw in this conference also.
I see. Thank you very much for the
comprehensive and inspiring answer.
Yeah. Thank you. Thank you so much. Okay.
Thank you. Thank you. So you'll
be happy there is no more Sheila. Oh. Uh-huh.
I think there's a question from Siva Chen.
Yeah. Hello.
Hey. Hey, Silly. Great talk. Great
talk. Really enjoyed it. So I was I was
wondering, you talked about Memento
and then horizon bench.
So do you think the way
you organize the memory has a role to play here?
Yes. It that's exactly the research
that we're we're hoping
hoping to get at, especially I wanted to make a distinction
between, like, a memory and personalization.
And there's there's I I think
they're they're diverse. Like, what I in my
motivation slide, I was just saying they're different.
But there is like, you can't really have one
or both like the other. Right? You're gonna have to
have a a good l in order to have a good alignment,
you need to have a really good memory. An
efficient memory. So that that's why
I was I was highlighting. I know it's
a shameless plug for, work from
related work from from the lab that I joined,
as well. But there is there is a there
is a there is a strong connection between memory
and and personalization, especially
long form personalization. Yeah. Yeah.
Next. Of course.
Thank you so much. Thank you everybody in the room,
for listening. And and please do
reach out if any of this is interesting to
you all. Have a great conference.
Thank you. Thank you again. Yeah.
Yeah. So I think, yeah, we have already
heard the voice from our neck MITT
talks speaker. So,
here, I will make a short
and brief introduction to welcome
Siva Reddy. So, Siva,
our next speaker is, assistant
professor at McGill University.
Canada CFIA chair, and the core
faculty at Mila Quebec AI Institute.
And a research scientist at ServiceNow
Research. His research
spans representation learning, intelligent language models,
safety and alignment, and also multimodal
language understanding. He received his
PhD from the University of Edinburgh
and was a postdoc fellow at Stanford
University. Okay.
So now, let's welcome
Siva Reddy to give the
last talk before our poster
session. So
yeah, can tech team help
us You hear me
okay. Right? Yeah. Yeah. We can hear
you now and see you now. Thank you
so much for the waiting and very
sorry about the delay of this afternoon
No worries. Section. No worries. Yeah. Please take your time.
Yeah. Everyone
here. I'm I'm sorry that I couldn't be there. I had some
visa problems. It's it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
but but, anyways, I'm
really happy to be here at the workshop.
I also
was very happy to catch Ashley's talk. So it
was a really sitting
down tone for this talk, actually.
So
I'm lifelong agents.
Everybody's talking about lifelong agents.
But we should also address some
very important issues. And
this is what I want to address here.
I if if I was in the room, I would have
asked how many have used OpenCart.
For me, I've been using OpenClaw myself.
A lot, and, it's I would
say, one of the most fascinating
things because it there were there's an AI
assistant always working with not just one assistant,
but multiple assistance. Right?
And then they learn from your interactions,
and they keep getting better. There
are many problems though. Like, they keep drifting away
and also the problems that Asli mentioned,
that they they don't,
in the in the immune in your beliefs, they don't realize
that there is an updated belief.
There are many problems, but it's very, very exciting
out, Sarissa. And and
you could interact with these agents from multiple
channels. And you you could
also see how this architecture is. It's very
simple architecture right now. You go to
OpenCloak, and you can actually see all the MD
files. You have a memory file. You have a soul.
You have, what is important for the day, what
is important on like,
a week back. So everything is written in empty
files. And you combine all this together
with the an agentic
thing like a cloud or anything else?
And suddenly, boom, you have a an extremely
useful assistant
working for you, a lifelong agent.
But the problem here is that, like, these deployments
are mostly focusing on,
using large scale models like cloud
or or, Codex or one of those
very big models. And this is not really
scalable. Right? You you want to have lifelong
agents and you want
to constantly talk to these agents. It's a
heartbeat continuously that's happening.
So building on top of
a Frontier API
a Frontier model probably is the wrong thing
to start for a lifelong agent. The reasons are, like,
you can't train these first of all. Like, this
model is already trained and you can't continuously
keep training. It's a lifelong
learning is really a patch on top of
this thing in some sense. So
and also, the amount
of cost. Right? Like, you're running the
if you take a number of tasks number of users,
number of interactions, this
is it becomes extremely expensive
even if you run your own Open
Cloud, you would it would cost you up to
a thousand to $2,000
just now for you. So
and also the other thing is latency.
Right? It's also slow to send some queries
somewhere else. So you want these agents to live
near you. And this is, like, on your
maybe on your laptops. Right? This is
and also the privacy. You don't want to send your data
all your data outside.
This is a very big problem right now.
And the other big aspect is that
I you want this model
to learn things about you
And and then as I said, like, if you rely on frontier
models, you're patching up on top of
this thing in multiple ways. This personalization
becomes very hard. You might
want to burn these things into the model itself. Like,
you you don't want the model to forget some things about
you at all. Like, you you can just burn them into
the model. But this is not an option right now.
So what is an option is,
I think, if you move
away from these large language models to
go towards small language models, that
are extremely good at
your tasks. And, also, they know you very
well and they can preserve
privacy, continuously learn from interactions
so on. That would be the ideal scenario, and this is
where, we are trying to make some progress towards
that. But there are many problems.
Right? The the the problems are, like,
if you take a small language model
a small language agent, you
can this agent actually do the job.
This is not entirely clear. Like,
we know big models have
highly highly they they have many capabilities.
But how can you get those capability
into into a small model? And you don't want
all capabilities. Like, you don't
you have specific tasks to do, so you
want the small models to do
these tasks extremely well. So you
don't care, whether this model is able to do
trading very well when you actually care about your
calendar. Right?
But but, like, it's not entirely clear. Like, how
can we digital these capabilities into
small models? So that's one thing that I will talk
about. The other one is also
what about you, yourself?
Like, you you train your
model to be extremely good at one particular
task, like maybe calendar management.
But then it has to
learn from you over time. Right? Also,
So this is the the personalization aspect. How
how do we train this model? Per
user? And also, at interaction
level, and this is also what we saw in,
actually stock link. How does it retrieve things
from your memory? How how does it
store things in this memory? And
and this is what I'll talk about where,
we're going towards, the same language
model doing everything without
having to build an encoder
model to retrieve things from your memory. Like,
if you have to build an encoder model to retrieve
things from your memory, it becomes again
you're running things on your mobile phone, it becomes expensive.
Right? You want one model to do everything.
And this is where, we are going towards.
So I'll talk about, like, how can we build
extremely good model for a small domain,
and then personalize it? And then also
at interaction level, what progress can we make?
Yeah. This is, my work with, my PhD
student, Hsing Han Lu. So specialization,
like, per domain. If you if you
care about one particular domain, can you make
an a small language model extremely
good at that task? And that's the thing.
And if you take actual
small models from the wild, we
know they they're not that great.
Right? So if you take on web tasks on web
agent tasks, that is trying to accomplish tasks
on your browser, they're 20
points behind. Of frontier models. And
if you take when 3,590,000,000
parameter model, it's, yeah, can see compared
to GPT compared to Germany Pro,
it's 50, 20 points
below. But then
if you just do standard distillation, and there are
many people
who have already done a lot of standard distillation
techniques. In the wild. You
get some improvement. You you
don't get standard,
from from SFD distillation.
But you have to do it in a clever way, and,
and this is the attempt to that. And also, like,
when you're doing you want it to
also have capabilities that generalize
not just for that particular
website, but also to other websites, for example.
Right? Or other web environments. So
so, like, let's say you
care about the arena.
You expose this model to lot of WebRina tasks
but you you also want this model to work
well out of the box for or Visual
Webinar or something else.
So so what we came up with, it's a very
simple idea. It's, we
took existing the many,
methods in this area. You
and we took those and came up with a common
framework. What is common across all these things?
And what we realized is that
right now, one thing that is probably missing
Persona is a very important, aspect.
And you can have
a persona and then generate
many tasks for a given persona.
And ask a superior agent to annotate
these tasks. And,
also, you and when you're annotating
these tasks, what are you annotating for? Like, I will
just give you those details in a while. But then you
also want to know which of those
trajectories is correct so that you can actually train
your small language model on these trajectories.
Right? So so here, what
we did was,
we took one three point four nine billion
model and
took trajectories that are judged
correctly by the same model by,
in this case, Gemini.
On on,
WebRina, and we saw whether it,
can go beyond WebRina.
So WebRina already has six six web
environments. We also tested on workarina
and on all those things. So just
to give you an example, so, like,
persona here would be some Maya
Maya ecommerce admin who clears pending orders
first thing every morning So this is ecommerce
person, and this is the persona.
So they care they care about ecommerce tasks.
And for this persona, this is
an appropriate task. Get the purchase date
order and something. And
what we do is we take a powerful
models and we
we annotate everything, what's happening.
So the in a trajectory, you are performing
actions, but order to perform actions, you need to perform actions. But in order to perform actions, you need to perform actions. But in order to perform
perform an action, you're also thinking what is
important how you can produce an action.
Right? So here, we
we're distilling those thoughts.
So you have thoughts, you have actions, and
then the judge sees these
trajectories. But because we are generating these
tasks, beforehand,
we also provide hints for evaluation.
So we know whatever evaluation model
should look for. So we just want
just to summarize this entire thing, what
we have is a we have several personas
here. I don't know if you can see my mouse pointer,
but, yeah, we have several personas.
And those personas are responsible for
generating several tasks.
And because we are generating tasks ourselves, we
also know what to look for. These are
in the form of hints and intents.
And we use those to see
whether this highly capable model can execute
this trajectory and give us this trajectory
not just the trajectory, but also everything that
went into the trajectory, like the reasoning traces
and stuff like that. And now let's
go and train a small language model on these
trajectories. As I said, like, this idea
these ideas exist. In different
papers, but we took a common framework
for all these, multiple ideas on what is
figuring out what is important and what is not important. And
and, this this paper has
a lot of ablation studies also in
that aspect.
Yeah. So
also, like, every piece here we found out, like, every
piece here is very important. Like, in
this case, judge figuring out judge and also
having hints for the judge. So
if you provide this, you you if you
remove this, if you train on every possible trajectory,
you could also see drop in
performance. So all of these steps are important.
And after training, what
we saw is, like, if you take 23,490,000,000
model, it was performing at 31%
on WebRina It's
a when is doing
great job, actually. Like, Quinn three a
19 model is already doing
as well as GPT four o. Like,
kudos to Quinn team, actually.
But but then, like, our digital
model from Germany, this is the teacher.
On the barina task. And you can
see we pushed it really
far.
To an extent that it is actually better than,
Sonet. So that was
really surprising. Like, Sonet is in a is
a good model,
And and in the in the public, we don't have
models that perform this well. Like, small
language models that are able to perform web
tasks at this level. Don't have them
yet. But now after this distillation
we have. So the
point that I'm trying to make is that
on this extremely niche task that you care
about, you could frame this as distillation
And and what is important is, like, reasoning
traces. We found out that reasoning traces are actually
very important. To get
to this level. If you remove the reasoning traces,
again, you see there's not much you
can do. And personas turns out to be
important. If you remove personas again, you can't,
do this thing.
And, like, and, like, a 9,000,000,000 model
is already performing better than
27,000,000,003
x large model. So that was very
interesting. So
what here, it's clear
that distillation is a path towards building
small models that,
you on on tasks that you care
about. So that's that's, and and not
only that, like, if you build a small
model that in this with this diversity
setup, like, with personas, with reasoning phrases,
and so on, not only it gets better at
webinar task. Webinar's, tasks are
actually highly synthetic tasks.
Even it even generalizes
to realistic tasks like, workarina.
Workarina is one of the hardest bench and
a much more realistic tasks for
work. And on that, you could see 18
improvement. That's a big improvement.
So
that's that's what I want to select. A distillation
of for small language models is a viable
path. Yeah.
And for the second part, the personalization,
how can we build models that understand users?
Right? This is, again, joint work
with my students like.
So even if you have a capable
model, that model doesn't know so much
about you. So you have to provide information, but
providing information is not
feasible. You, you you can't tell everything
about you. But there is lot of data
about you already. Like, maybe in your emails, maybe
somewhere else. Alright? So so,
like, let's take two users.
On or multiple users on Google Maps.
And the question is how long to the museum
And this answer will depend to on the
person. Like, if a person prefers walking,
the answer will be one. The other
one prefers car or the other one
prefers bike. But, like, you don't want
to specify these things every time. Like, it depends
on the person. Right? And this
is what personalization will allow you to
understand
And based on your past data, like, this
is what we are trying to do here.
And then we already know, like,
if you can give every possible little
information about you in one big explicit
profile, is almost impossible
to do. So so you can
have models to work well
for you. But the question is, like, can they
learn about you from past
interactions? Like, you as I said, your
maybe your browser history, like how you're doing
things in your browser. So this is implicit
history. So without
access to explicit person, profile,
so this is what we want. So we
generated lot of personalized data. So we
took we we we sampled many
users with the different personas, what they like and
so on. From those personas, we sample a lot
of trajectories. And now we we are
trying to infer a given
user, can a model understand the user well? Like,
if you say, I want to go go to
museum, will it be able to figure
out that you're going by bike? Without even having
to tell? So that's the thing.
And and again, the same
setup that you saw earlier, like, we have multiple
stages. It's about personas. It's
about,
whether you are using just
screenshots or whether you're also using
text summaries of the this entire trajectory.
So, yeah, like, the screenshot
setting as well as a text only setting
at text only here is a trajectory
summary of of what you did. And
once you have all these trajectories,
annotated, either in screenshots or in text only,
Now we want to see how well
would models do. Like, when they when you're not given
profile, when you are given
user centric profiles, But
here, like, when when when user centric, like,
even giving gold gold profiles,
but you don't say which one is relevant
in this context. You will give all
the preferences of a user in a given
context, not every preference of the user is relevant.
Only some particular. Whereas you can also
say exactly for this context, this is the most
relevant preference. Right? So
it turns out the good
news is that, like, agents can do
well when you provide your past address.
This is really promising. So yeah.
And they also prefer the data
in the actual form. So you don't even have
to summarize this entire trajectory.
You can give the the trajectories as
screenshots and so on. You you
have to have a way to parse them. But then
you could get better than not using
your profile, so that's a good news.
But they're but they're really far away. Like, these are I'm talking,
Gemini three Pro here. It's
a highly capable model. Even
that model is failing
to, infer all the in all
the important differences from your data.
So that was, really surprising here.
From your user centric data,
if you if you already provide goal
profile and all the preferences
you could get a big bump
But if you tell the exact preference,
you could get even bigger bump. So it turns
out it's not even enough to give
give all the preferences. You also have to tell the exact
preference that is relevant in this given context,
which is almost impossible. Right?
So mean, this is one area I
think we there's there's so much more to do.
And, actually, stock on personalization
is really also touching these aspects. So it's very
clear we don't have personalization
yet. So this is this is a point.
So here, like, even the frontier
model, has 15 points. This is when when we give
even the preferences and
the entire Oracle preferences.
Implicit preference of
preference mining is really hard here
based on what we are seeing here.
Okay. And also, like, what
happens when you swap the user profiles? Just,
if you give some random users profile
to a given user, we see, like,
yeah. Like, profiles are really important.
So this is there's no artifacts here. We
also made sure that, we check for these things.
Alright? So the next part
is, interactions.
Like, at turn turn level, every turn,
you are sending you you
are fetching things from your memory,
You're putting the all those things in your context.
You're also interacting with other agents
Maybe these agents are living on the web.
You're sending queries to this other agent. So
communication becomes a bottleneck,
and communication is very important for
personalized agents.
Right? So at every
interaction, if you think about an interaction, what
is an interaction?
So what you have to do is that an interaction
when you you or you gave some query,
and now the agent should think, oh,
what is relevant for this query?
What things should I fetch from
the memory? And, also, from
the past things, how do I store these things in
the memory so that they are easily accessible. Right?
So so you need some kind of retriever here,
and the commons should solution to do this is
you would usually have a separate
retriever. You would you you'd have your
generative model, the language model, but also a
separate embedding model
to do these things. But then again,
if you are talking about small language models,
and and also, like, things, like, running on
your mobile phone, you don't need
you don't want a separate encoder. That's what
I was you want your language model
to be an encoder in itself. Right?
So that's one. And then the other thing is
also talking
to other agents. Right? Right now, this all this
talking is happening
agent, in in token stream, which
is which is, really slow. Like, you
the first first the agent has to decode all
the tokens. Send these tokens via
network, and then the other agent has to
process all those tokens.
And then understand, oh, this is what the other agent
meant. But this is too slow. Like, you
don't want these things to be
that level. So can we have an LLM
agent that can do things in representation
space? This is what we are trying to do.
Where, it can you don't
need a separate encoder. Your
LLM itself is an encoder. And also,
your embeddings are,
you can directly pass those embeddings to
other agents. So that is
how do we do that? So here,
what we we have a
model like Ellen two vecGen. L
m two vec was the original paper that we wrote
on how to take a an LLM and transform that
into an embedding model. But then you have to
change the architecture of the URL.
That's, again, almost like running two different
models. Whereas here, what
we did is,
first or URL m can
already generate responses for a given query. Right?
And how about
we encode So for a given
query, if you if you're
any language models are already good about
predicting answers for a given query. And
they they they're they're trained to
do that. Right? So
we're going to invert the paradigm. Like, instead
of encoding the
input what we want our
embedding models to encode is a
what would be the possible answer? What should I
look for? So this is
what we are I'm trying to do here. So instead of,
like so so your LMS already
generate answers for for a given query
or things that it already knows
about you or how to reason
about things. So if you can produce embeddings
that can capture that essence,
And in this case, again, the same language
model. Trying to produce an embedding,
but here you're using some
soft thinking tokens or soft
prompts saying, hey. I'm going to give
you this prompt. You encode
the output into this
into these embeddings. So the output embeddings
are actually what the LLM
already knows about this particular query.
It's not embedding the
input assay. It's encoding
what it already knows about this query
so that it can go and try to match
those things into in in the embedding
space. So so here, again, as you see,
the LLM is all frozen here.
And, all you're just training is the soft
tokens. So you're turning your
language model into an embedding model.
And then the other part that we also want to make
sure is that these tokens
should be decodable, not just, you you don't want to
just encode them. Because you want to pass
these tokens to other agents so other agents would
also be to decode what it is in them.
So so also made sure that these tokens
are not only encoding, but also you
can decode them. Okay. So
when you do it this way, what we realized
was, if you start encoding
the output rather than the input,
your performance goes much higher. Like, you
are producing much richer embeddings.
So these are very clear compared to the l m
two v. And, also, you're not that far away
from your supervised embedding model. So
this is a put on on the
unsupervised part. Like, this is the state of the
art currently that you should you could check it out.
And also, like, why we
should think about output space and not about the input.
So if you take a query like which
case law resolves, the contract is put.
I mean, this one this this input doesn't
have much information. Right? And
the, your LLM that knows already
a lot about you probably
already knows how to answer this question. It's
just trying to fetch the right memory
So in that case, if you
if the LLM already which is, oh, I
know about these details.
I'm going to create numbering with all these details and
see which memory will hit this Right?
So in some in some form, it's a query
expansion.
So so these are what we think the LLM is the best encoder.
And when we ran this on multiple
benchmarks, we saw that
encoding the output is
extremely useful and extremely useful
when it the the tasks are much more complex like
reasoning tasks. So here in this case,
bright is a very hard reasoning task.
And on that, you get really high bumps compared
to just using the input.
Okay? I'm I'm almost towards the
end. So and also, like, our embeddings
are interpretable So other you can
pass Because
these embeddings are in interpretable,
you could let the agents talk in embedding
space without having to send the tokens.
Sending those tokens is extremely slow. So
if you have a agent to agent pool protocol
instead of sending tokens, you will send
10 look into 10 latent tokens
Those 10 latent tokens can be decodable by the
model.
So just to wrap up
I touched upon three things, that you
can build extremely good
small language models for your target tasks by
distillation. And the other one is the personalization
is turns out to be the hardest one. Right
now, we still have a lot more work to do in that
space. And also, like, communication
you you want to use your
original LLM itself,
as your embedding model and that will be in the output
space. K? And and
then, what's going forward
is, I don't
think we have to rely fully on these large
language models. For at
least for the lifelong personalized
agents, we could have lot of small personalized
agents that are trying to do tasks for you.
Yeah. With this, I'll stop. Thank you.
Oh, for the audiences,
if you have any questions, you can
come to the upfront.
Okay. So so if there is no I
I also have a very, like, small
question. So
I think the main thread, the talking is very clear
and inspiring talks about, like, how to build
the lifelong small agents. So I think
you mainly talk about, like, three aspects,
like acquiring general competence,
also learning to personalize, and also learning
to communicate with with each other.
So for these three aspects, is there
kind of like a curriculum
that, like, whether which aspect should be
learned first? Or what's the
relationship do you think between these
three aspects? That if we are
developing future small lifeline agent we should
focus on? Yeah.
That's a great question. Thanks, Jing.
Yeah. It's it's very clear.
The first part is that your language model
should be capable. Right? So I think that if you thought
that capability, there's this
agent will not be useful for you. So
at least we should make
this language model good at tasks that
you care about. So that's the distillation
part. Even if it means using a
a much larger model, trying to tell
the smaller model how to do this things. So
that would be the first step. And once you have
that first step, then these
two things can be interleaved, I would say. The
the personalization
aspect and the other aspects. These are something
or the these are two different, distinct tax
aspects. So mean, we could go in anyway.
But then you have to continue this loop. Like, once
you continuously learn about
you and maybe you teach the model how to do
these tasks. Right? Once in a while,
you don't have to store everything
as a personalized profile. You could burn
things back into the small language model.
So this is the other thing where, you
have to update maybe the language model so
that your your memory is not
bloated. Right? This is this is what happens
with OpenClip. If you use OpenClip for a
long time, it becomes extremely
slow. And there's a and
you're you're sending lot of, tokens to this language
model.
Thank you. I think it's very clear.
So yeah, I think there is
no more questions. So, yeah, thank you again
for your inspiring talk. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Bye.
So from now on
to 4PM, it will be the afternoon
poster session. So there,
originally, it's like an hour, and for
now, we are only have a about forty
five minutes left. So if you you are interested
in, any of the poster, please
take a look. And everyone
can take a peek back at
four in the afternoon, and we will have another
invited talk from Azalea
from Stanford University. I hope to see
you soon.
Okay. So
welcome to our last
in the Lifeline Agent Workshop.
So this talk will be featured by
professor Azalea. So she is an
assistant professor of computer science
at Stanford University, where she
works on capable, reliable, and
efficient AI systems for for high impact
real world problems. Her research includes
learning based methods for this making in systems
and chip design. Self improving
AI systems, scalable deep learning
optimization. So let's
welcome professor Azalea
to give the last invited talk in
our workshop Yeah. Let's welcome.
Thank you so much. For the Yeah. We we
can see you now.
Okay. And you see my slides. Right?
Yes. Yes. We we can see your face and
your slides now. Perfect.
Yeah. Very excited to be here,
and, and give this
talk remotely on self improvement
with test time scaling
of verifiers.
So first, a
quick definition. So what I mean by self
improvement is
the process by which AI autonomously
improves its own capability
and reliability, And if we
are interested
or our goal is to get to
artificial general intelligence, it seems like
self improvement needs
to play a key role in this process because
some extent, you're talking about
AI that can, take
do many tasks that human experts can
do at the same time. So maybe
they should be in this process
help themselves take take
the human, kind of skills
and capabilities to
the next level.
Now in this talk specifically, I'm going
to talk I'm going to focus
on one particular approach that we can enable
self improvement and that is test time
scaling.
So in the past,
five, six years,
a lot of Frontier Labs
put a lot put bunch of their focus on
pretraining and that was driven by
the scaling loss. This kind
of observation that as we throw
in more compute, as
we scale compute for training larger
models and more data with more compute,
we get to better
and more capable end results.
What test
time is scaling kind of
suggest is that
this paradigm of adding
compute and getting better results
doesn't have to be as part of
the training process. And once the model are frozen
and the weights don't change, we can
still bring,
more capability by spending
additional compute. Now I'm gonna
talk about what I mean by that.
About a year and a half
ago in our lobby, made
this framework. It's a very
simple framework where we call it large
language monkeys.
The frame this framework works as
follows. We for an input problem,
we have an LLM
that takes on that problem and generates
many, many responses.
And then for for now, let's assume we have access
to a verifier
meaning a
some way that we can decide which
one of those responses,
are correct. And then the output
of this framework would be the correct response.
Because language models are stochastic,
we can get a lot of different variability
of responses. And
this is a very, very simple paradigm,
but it turns out that this is very, very
powerful. Here, what we
are showing is that we as we
are increasing the number of
repeated samples, from one to
a 100 and then to 10,000,
what we are seeing is that the coverage
keeps increasing and
by what the definition of coverage is the fraction
of problems that are solved
by at least one of these samples.
And it
the notion of test time scaling comes here
in in this
repeated sampling, framework
where a model, a very small model,
like a Llama three eight p, of
course, in the beginning is significantly
worse than this the SOTA model
at the time, which was GPT four o.
But as we increased these number of
samples, it ends up being better
than the the more capable and much larger
GPT four o model. And
as we go to 10,000 on all
of these benchmarks is outperforming,
outperforming that. So, basically,
you're surfacing more
and more capability out of these
smaller models by
spending additional compute at test time,
and it seems like the models
know already know a whole lot
more than what we can
get out of them with
only simple single sample or few
sample kind of,
interactions.
We looked into it a little bit deeper
to see if we can define
scaling loss for test time. This,
and in in essence,
what we found was that we can
approximate the relationship between the
coverage and the number of repeated
samples, and in this case, shown by
Kaye, with this
exponential formula. So across
these different
size models from eight b to 70 b and across
different kind of reasoning
task, in this case, math and code,
we said, let's assume we have access to
an Oracle verifier, and let's
see if we can find a relationship
that is precisely predicting
how as we increase k, we can
improve the performance of the model.
And that's, like, the power of
scaling laws. We
find a recipe that can translate
additional to more
capability.
In a follow-up work, we looked into why this
exponential relationship exists from more
of a theoretical perspective.
And what we found is that for that
relationship to exist, the sufficient
and necessary
is that we have a long tail of hard problems.
And we
and given this, we went
back given this observation, we went back and
looked into these
problems from, different mathematical
coding, other reasoning problems,
and for different types of models.
And what we saw is that it's
actually the case that we are
the the batch of statistics of
these workloads do have this,
left tail power law
property, and that is what, creates
this scaling laws at test time.
And the benefit of this is that
now we have a recipe that
we can predict how much the model
becomes more capable while
before spending the compute.
While spending two to four orders of magnitude
less inference compute, we can predict that,
and then it becomes a matter of whether it makes
sense for for us to spend those
additional compute to get to this,
performance.
What this suggests is that
while previously there was
a lot of capital, a lot of compute
on pretraining, and then some on fine tuning,
and very little
kind of cost or compute on test time.
Now we have this new paradigm that we
can keep spending at test time,
keep adding more and more compute at
test time, and get better and better
models. And the relationship
of this with
the reasoning models and this concept
of distillation fine tuning on,
is that we can now
have this data five wheel where
the model can generate a lot
of new experiences We
can take those experiences, use it
as a new training data, and
update the model. So next time it does
better. So, again,
these test time generations are a new
abundant source of training
data and source for self improvement.
Now
one topic that I briefly mentioned
earlier is and
it's very important for test time scaling,
is the notion of verifier.
When you are doing repeated sampling,
for example,
it's very important that we have access
to a verifier that can tell us
how to choose between all those candidates
and get to the correct response.
It turns out that there are some domains
where test time where verifiers
exist automatically, and we can use
them. And that's great.
But when we don't have access
to a verifier,
the gap between what we can get
with the best of n and these
kind of baseline methods and
the true Oracle base verifier is
gonna be large. Here,
what I'm showing is
again, we we are having this
going back to the repeated
sampling example, we go from one to
10 all the way to 10,000.
Samples. And if you have access to an
oracle that can tell us the best
response, we can get better and better,
accuracies. And in
in this case, for a with all of
these, benchmarks, we're almost
saturating that bench meaning
we do find the correct response
However, with methods
such as majority voting, that's the green
line, or using a reward model
or judge model or a combination of
both these methods fail
to follow the
the way that a full Oracle
based coverage could create and
generate the correct responses for us.
Because the
because, for example, four
m methods such as majority voting,
what we observed was that
it's actually the case that in some
of these examples, the correct
response is very, very rarely generated
by the model. So by
definition, majority voting
which looks into the statistics of
which response is repeated
most and selects that as the correct
output. Fails to
identify those correct responses.
So this is the motivation
for the rest of this talk where we talk more
and more about verifiers and how
we can,
improve the quality of them.
Now, briefly, let's talk
about applications where automated
verification exists. And
one example of that, and this is something
that my lab has been doing,
a lot of work around, is the GPU kernel
design.
So the this task,
the goal in this task is that
can be leveraged LLM as a compiler
compiler or transpiler? Meaning,
for example, we have a PyTorch input.
We have a model. And we want
to write that model, with
a another language,
such as CUDA or Triton
such that we can run this model faster
on our desired
GPU or other hardware accelerator.
So the setup
here is that the inputs is the reference
PyTorch model, Language
model generates a new code basically
to
transpile the input but
in this new lower level language, which allows
it to use to do more
and more hardware aware optimization,
and then we have the output code
there. The reason this
is,
and briefly,
in order to do this, we,
here, quick segue to kernel bench
is a suite
of benchmarks where, we have this different
levels of complexity to enable this task
from single kernel operators
to a collection of
operators where we have more than a single
op, and it kind of
looks into the LLM capability
to perform fusion of ops.
And then the last level with the highest complexity
would be when we have end to
end models where we such
as a model, such as main JPP, Mamba,
and such And the goal of the LLM in
this case is to entirely run new
revisions of this model such that they run faster.
The benefit or the
cleanness of this benchmark is that
we can evaluate correctness by
checking if we match the input PyTorch
code using the whatever PyTorch
compiler that we have. For
example, for a set of randomized inputs,
we can run
the model in PyTorch.
We can run the new code
that is generated by the l l
a, and we can see if they match each
other or not. So we and then
we can look for correctness, whether
they match and also speed, whether
the new code is faster or not. So
this is a possibility that
by design, this problem is giving
us that our verifier is by design
as ref our reference. Torch
code. And then
given that, now we can build all these
more sophisticated test time
scaling and agent take, harnesses
around this task.
Example, in this case, we have a we have
the model. We have the
the input task that we want to write kernels
for. We generate kernels,
and then we can get all sort of feedback
from compilers, from
the correctness aspect.
From the performance to iterate
through this process and generate
better and better kernels over time.
So this possibility
again was given to us by this reference
reference torch code that can,
help us evaluate whether
the new generations within
this test time scaling method is gonna,
create correct solutions or not so
we can figure out how to filter
and how to move to the next,
iteration. In this setup.
Now there
are scenarios
where very few verifiers don't exist,
and you're gonna see some of them in the rest
of this talk. So the goal
here is that how looking
we want to look into methods that
enable us to reduce the generation
verification. Gap.
And, interestingly, what we are gonna see
is that test time scaling itself,
this time on the verifiers, can help
us achieve this, better,
higher quality verification.
So the first work that I'm going
to mention is Weever, which is a
a weak to strong approach to verification.
The idea of Weever is the following.
When we don't have a verifier, we can always
use an LLM as a judge or
use a reward model to evaluate
the correctness of a risk response and
use that as filtering. But, of course, those have
limitations just we saw in one of
the slides earlier.
Now the idea here is that can
we have a better approach when
we use techniques from ensemble
and week to strong supervision
to create better verifiers.
In this case, we have
a collection of LLMs judges and
reward models All of those
are giving you a score for any
single
candidate generated by the model.
So that's the scoring part.
The next part is the weighting
weighing of all these
scores, and that's where this week
to strong supervision method
comes in. And the idea is that how
with really, really small supervision,
maybe on a very small held out dataset,
we can create better ways to weigh
the score of each of these
elements in the ensemble And
then there's the selection process, which is very
gonna be very easy. We just select the score,
the weighted score that's highest among
all the generations. So
the way this,
a little bit more about how we create this
big supervision here, In
general, big sub supervision is a topic
that has been talked about a lot in
classic classical
machine learning methods. The idea is
we have noisy ways of
label label labelers.
In this case, our LLMs
judges and reward models, how how we can
assemble those and
maximize the way that we can infer
the true label.
By looking into cross correlations
between the quality of
each individual labeler
and their patterns
that exist in in this holistic
setup.
So we have end end questions.
We have k generated
solutions per question, and then
we have end verifiers.
And the the weaver's
goal is to predict the probability that
the output response is correct.
So the probability of
y being correct given this
collection of
generated, scores
from different verifiers
that we have. In this case, we have m verifiers.
The key assumptions that we make is
that
each verifier
captures independent aspects of correctness.
If we make this assumption, which
we will show empirically that
we can do so, then we can write the
the posterior probability of correctness given
these scores with this
equation. And then another
part of the equation is
just the the the normal base rule
that we can write the probability
of, a score being one
condition on, all the scores,
that that the model has given, across
all different
generated solutions. So
given these two equations, then we can
go back and assign
a weight to each of our judges such
that the collective
weighted sum would be a
better signal for
evaluating a candidate compared
to naively ensembling those
scores. So here, we
can look into some of the results.
And these are, again, different reasoning task
from math and
other areas. And,
you're showing you baseline
such as majority. This is
the Oracle one where we have access to
the true Oracle Oracle verifier. And,
again, the we don't have
a test time when we these models are deployed.
We don't have that access. So
that's the true
North Star that we want to achieve.
And the purple one is we were when
we use this we use supervision.
The blue one is weaver when it's
truly unsupervised, and the orange
one
is, where we naively ensemble
things. So as you can see,
even naively ensembleing these
rewards gives us a huge jump
over methods such as majority
voting or multi agent verification
But, again, we can get notable
delta or gains on top of that if
we optimize how we, weigh
or put this course
together. And, again, the difference between beaver
supervised and unsupervised is that how much
data we used as labels
for creating those,
weight, equations. The more data
we have, of course, we can do
better in
solving this, weighted
ensemble problem.
Now just quickly, what
we are doing here again is we
are adding test time, not just on
the generations, but on
the verifiers as well.
Every time we are asking more and more
ensembles elements
like judges and reward models, we are
spending test on compute to generate more
scores and that results
in better WAV files. And
another, important,
chart here that I wanted to show is that
by bringing this verification
at test time, we are making
a LAMA eight b
model the same quality class
almost the same quality class as as
of a Loma 70 b
model when, we use
simple test time methods such as majority voting.
So and that is true for a LAMA 70
b model, that
is behaving almost the same as an o three mini
model. By bringing
in these test time scale on
the verification. So the
capability of model is leveled up by
a large margin without
changing any of the weights of the model or
retraining or any of these
kind of more computational heavy
optimizations.
I want to talk about one
last method on verification.
Again, this the idea here
is we can bring test time scaling
to make our verifier better. And as a result,
we can make the model capability
higher. So this is our
newest work in this domain. It's called LLM
as a verifier.
And the key insight here is that we
want we want to leverage
the full distribution of score
tokens in order to have a
more fine grained kind of score
and feedback. The the way LLLM as
a verifier works is very simple.
First, we ask the LMM
to rank the results on a scale
of one to g. In this case, g is eight.
And then instead of just
looking in to the number that the model
generated, the single
score, we look into the log props of
those rank tokens so
ranks one to eight, and create an expected
value of this course.
So we have this way we are using a more
granular distribution
of the scores rather than a
single assignment.
To show you how the,
the prompt or the way we are creating this
verifier, here is the example.
Fine prompt prompt we're
passing two trajectories. So
the prompt is you are next expert reviewer.
You will see task which
descriptions and two trajectories.
Here is the evaluation evaluation
criteria, and that's where we can
do more in terms of from what
angles we want to evaluate this.
And then we give the task and the
course. The score range. In this case,
an integer from one to eight.
So we asked the model to rate
correctness for each of these trajectories on
a one to eight scale, scale
And note that we use the letter based
scale instead of digits, so it's because of
the way tokenization work, and
we want to enable extraction of clear
log props.
So once we have those,
now we have this
other signal that we have created,
this expected average log
prop signal. And one of the immediate
benefits that that we saw is that
compared to an LLM as a judge,
the tie rate is a lot is significantly
lower. So if we have
if we add an increased k, the number of repeated
generation from one to four to six
team, we can see that there
are we can do better
in terms of avoiding
ties, which makes verification kind of
meaningless or using that verifier.
And on the other hand, we can show that these
results in higher and higher
accuracy, compared to LLM
as a judge.
Another signal that we can get from this
verification LLM as a verifier
approach, is that now
we can change not only we can
change the granularity of the
score, but Previously, we just saw
till eight, but it turns out that we increased that
to 20. We can increase
the verification accuracy.
We can also get more out
of
enabling more repeated verification
or increasing k
and also increasing the criteria of the
composition. So
as we ask the model to judge or
come up with with a verification or accuracy
score, we can give more and more,
criteria and that increases
or improves the quality of our signal.
And here, just to show you how powerful
this test time scaling of the very
far, and this is a very, very simple method
is, here we
are comparing with today's frontier, and so
the results on
very, sophisticated agent
benchmarks such as terminal bench and sweet bench
verified, And what we see
is that by taking in
LLM as a verifier,
just looking into, more and
more ways that we can extract
some signal and insight from the model
we can notably
increase, the quality of results
on top of these, state of the art models.
Here's a summary, and I see a typo
up there. Of the
of this, of my talk. So
test time scaling is a new frontier for
self improvement.
We can continuously self
improve the model
if we have access to methods
where the model can self verify
again, self improvement is when we want
to have give the model more and more
autonomy over its own
kind of experiences and learning process.
And self verification should be
part of that as well.
As we scale test on compute, we can
make verification better
and better, and that includes self
verification and enabling the model
do downstream task better. And
what I want to mention lastly is that there's
still lot lots of alpha, lots of
insight to be discovered
for verification, for how the model
can evaluate it own generation,
learn from that, and use that to
continually self improve. And get to the new
frontier. And with that, I can
conclude the talk and very,
happy, that I got a
chance to talk with you here.
Thanks. Thank you. So Yeah.
If any audience have the question, you can
come to the upfront.
Or Yeah. I actually
also have a little question. Like,
so so our workshop is about, like, lifelong
agent. So in the setting,
like, Lifelong Agent your compute,
I think sometimes it's always very limited.
So you have to choose,
like, one priority,
for the next couple of years, like,
better generators or better verifiers,
or even better ways about, like, how
to allocate the test time compute
So where do you think is the can
the biggest gains come from?
Yeah.
I I think there is no single answer to
your question. Because I think
depending on the task,
generation versus verification could be very
different. Like, we see that there
are all these amazing,
math, new mathematical innovations,
and new theorems that are proved.
And the in that case, Lean
or other formal proof app
tools that we can use are very, very powerful.
They can enable us to,
just verify our results. So in that case, of
course, generation is
the main bottleneck we want to use.
More and more generation But then there
are other areas where
and the same for kernel design or computer
systems. Verification
is a more manageable, measurable
task but there are other areas where
verification is harder.
There could be more subtle ways that the model
can be hacked, can reward hack.
And then in that case, we need more computer
verification. So I would say it's
very, very problem dependent.
But I can imagine both of these methods
they're they're the
their test time scaling methods to be discovered
that can give us massive efficiency
gains over both.
See. Yeah. The very comprehensive
answer. Yeah. Thank you very
much. Yeah. I think you answered very clearly.
So yeah, I think there is
no more question from the audience in the room.
So, yeah. Let let's thank professor
Azalea again for giving this
very inspiring talk. Thank you
so much.
Okay. Okay.
So now we'll come to the
last section
student panel discussion
along with the rewarding ceremony.
So, we have invited
four panelists. They are also the order
of the outstanding papers in our workshop.
So let's
welcome the panelist. Yeah.
So if you are here, you can directly come
up to the stage. And we will
discuss some questions yeah,
together.
Yeah. Please please take a seat.
Yeah. Sorry.
I won't be well.
Can you help me turn on the screen also?
Yeah.
Yeah. I think you can
yeah, have, like, two microphones.
The like
Hello. Sure. Oh,
there's another one.
Okay. So yeah.
So very welcome to our
final panel discussion. So
I have prepared some like,
questions for you to discuss about, like,
the lifelong agent. So
this year, like, we our workshop have received many
papers examining, like,
different ingredients of the lifeline agents.
So we see from the submission, there
are, like, reinforcement
learning with textual feedback. They are continue
learning without forgetting, and they
are, like, embody the world modeling all around,
like, Lifeline agent topics. So
if you had to pick one bottleneck that
most like, prevent
the most prevent the
most of today's Lifeline agents
development. So what should they be? Yeah.
I think maybe you can. Start from
Yeah. Yeah. That's a good question.
I think the main bottleneck as
to my wheel is, like, the current models,
they are not pretrained or training the
like, the interactive way. So although there are
some, latest work about model agent identic
scenarios, but
adapting to a, like, a real world scenarios
or, essentially, training from scratch
from the inter in a in a interactive way.
It's it's still not, you know,
fully utilized method.
So if we want to deploy the real world
like a lifelong agent and to have this
ability to generalize to
every or most tasks, then
I think that there will be two bottlenecks.
The first is how this model can be
adapted to the various form
of the embodiments. And the second will be,
like, how we can use this kind of, training
paradigm to deploy the model
or this agent to interact with his world and learn
from the world. World interaction
like, in real time. No matter it is a tight time training
or it's just some you know, the
the knowledge storing the knowledge
in some memory bank. Or some
other stuff, but this is some real problem that should
be tackled. Yeah. Yeah.
In my eyes,
simple efficiency is the biggest problem of
continual learning. Even after
we figured out how to learn from, let's say, user
interactions through textual feedback, for example,
still we need for example, if a user ask
us and say that he doesn't like emojis,
still these days we need at least one gradient
which mean a bed size of
eight, 16, 32, or something like that.
Which means that the user need to repeat
their preference many many times.
And usually, one guidance is also not
enough. And in practical, like,
in practice, everyone of the papers you see
here take dozens if not 100 of
gradients steps to learn anything that it can.
However, in real container learning setting, when you
deploy an agent into the environment,
it's very rare that, like, it will
get the same feedback
100 or a thousand times. We need to find a way to
learn even when we get a feedback once or
twice.
Okay. I I used to think it's
long context, but I don't believe
in that anymore because
okay, on one end, you can
so let's say you have a model that has
infinite context list. And then
if you believe in your in context learning capability,
which is very efficient, you can just
solve everything but
that's just the ideal case right
now. A lot of, problems, including
continual learning, is limited by context
lens. But I feel like that's more like
a system level issue, and you can have
like, local memory, long term
memory, short term memory to address that.
Then my answer switched it to
I have to agree with Yvonne. That
I agree the biggest issue is
sample efficiency
because think that's something that requires
us to find, fundamentally different
algorithms and systems to address that.
As, you know, I just mentioned, all
our current methods they are
more efficient than our post training,
but they are definitely not efficient enough.
So and I think, again, Lesa,
I emphasize in my talk before,
many continual learning scenario
is actually at very high
stake scenarios. Sample efficiency
is the key in those kind of
high stake environment.
So I'll I'll go I I I actually
okay, I I think the biggest bottleneck is
is not like actually the method. I think it's
like developers actually don't know what they
want for continued learning. Just give you
an example, like, for
the fuel shot efficiency problem that you get they they
were talking about,
okay. So just for the few short learning
example that you guys are saying, let's say, if
I have a use case where I can
only get three samples, okay, every time
for agent, like, I would use it completely
different method than, like,
a scenario which I can get
thousands of steps. So for example,
I I
our paper that we just presented,
it actually works quite well if you have
10 samples already. But the problem
here is that, if you run it if you keep running
it for, let's say, 100 or like 1,000
samples, it fails to scale. Like
like, it kind of plateaues really quickly after
like, 100 samples. So in that case, if you have
a lot of samples, you would actually want it like something
that does weight update, but
then, like, it's totally dependent on, like, what scenario
you're trying to run. Especially
we have, you know, cloud code these days. Are you
doing it within a session? Or
are you doing it across different sessions?
So I I think it highly depends on like what the
developer really wants instead of like I just wanted
to continue learning, and, you know,
give me a method there. I don't I don't think
there's a generic answer. I you need it,
like, actually design benchmarks
for these specific scenarios and, you know, just
kind of, like, improve on
each separated scenario.
Yeah. Thank you for the answer. I do
a follow-up? Yeah. I think
the thing seems like the way the thing we agree
here is we actually don't
have the algorithm yet. Imagine,
like, we have a algorithm that adapts
to 10 samples, and it also scales
to 1,000 samples. It's like
we we actually don't know what it looks like yet.
So I think that's actually some
some room for us to
leave our imagination at, and,
I personally believe
enough algorithmic advancement at system level
fundamentally system level development could bring
us there. Yeah. I
also kind of agree. There is no definite
answer for now. So leave a
large space that needs necessitates
our more exploration. Yeah.
So like, for lifelong learning, I think
we have talked so previously with her, like,
some of you you, we talk about there are
many, many different training methods. So
and as in the talk, I think many speakers
mentioned that before a model
to be like a lifelong agent. So even though,
like, in Siva's talk for the small language
models, maybe it's sometimes
not really needed to update
the model weight. So currently, we
have already also seen, like,
the harness engineering becomes
very trendy topic. So so for
the lifelong agent, when do you think
we really need to instill
this kind of knowledge in
to the agent or the language model themselves to
update their parameter or sometimes
when it is just just enough to do,
like, more harness
engineering to, do better scaffold
can solve this kind of issue. Yeah.
Should we go the other way around? Let's go. Okay.
Start with No. I have a lot of things to
say about this, actually. Actually.
Then leave you maybe to Nick. Okay. So,
oh, okay. Started on this. So I I think essentially what
you want is you wanna you wanna okay.
So this this model, like this
it what what you wanna actually
do is it doesn't include the knowledge or
like the information that is needed to,
to accomplish the task. Right? So
I want you to I want I
wanna start this by giving out two examples.
One example is, we have a VOA
that, robot learns to to fetch something
from from from, let's say, a desk.
So, let's say the VLA,
is just, like, not trained or, like, it's
pre trained. It it knows how to fetch a
a bloom, but a
fetch like like anything, but like he
doesn't know how to make a coffee. Okay. Let's just say this.
If you wanna teach or like okay. Let's say the robot
knows how to wave his hand, but it it doesn't know
how to play tennis. Okay. I think this is a very example.
So so we have two
methods here. One is, we only update the context.
And the other one is we we need to update the weight. So
then we think about the problem. Okay. What is a more efficient
way of representing the knowledge of playing
tennis? Then the question becomes, I don't know if
how do you like, do you guys play tennis at all? Like,
like, no. Okay. So oh, let's say basketball or something.
So let's say this. Like, how do you how do you actually
describe in word, in text?
That that, like, this is how you play how you shoot a basketball?
You simply can't. Because you would say like you wanna
like push it with one hand, but there are like a
thousand ways to to like push it with one hand.
So right. So in this sense, like,
text is not a very good constraint.
On on the on the space that you you're having because,
like, a pre trained model, your hand can
do a lot of movements, but you know, like
like in order to constrain them
to this, like, shooting a
basketball ball movement, like Texas
simply not a very good way to do it. It.
On the other hand, another example would be,
I'm trying to, just
write some program. I wanna call one
of the APIs, API says, okay.
Just say, like, it's again weather
API. And know, like, you're
trying to get weather from, you know, somewhere they
can outguess say North Korea.
And if you just call it on North Korea,
then like, obviously it's not gonna return nothing.
And now you wanna say, okay. So if you wanna call
get weather API, then you
should not use it on North Korea. It's very easy
to describe this in text. But if
you think about if you like, if I wanna
update the weights in order for the model to
learn this, it might take a lot of extra
steps. Cred me if it's wrong. Like, I am
I actually I'm I'm curious to because
I never worked on the
wait update part of this. So, like, I'll like,
if there's way to, like,
say, have very efficient way of just putting
this textual information into
the model, I think you'll also be interesting.
But I think essentially it's way of like
like which, like, text
or like a weight update, like which
way better like constrain the model
to to do the specific actions? Instead
of like going in the wrong Yeah. I would like
to respond if it's possible.
So I have agree with you.
I think that kind of you,
distinct had a distinction between,
like, basically anything that is skill based
to, like, kind of, like, a factual or
a specific knowledge you can retrieve.
Now think that is overall correct, but
there's like one important thing
that is missing. That is compression. Of
a lot of, like, small parts
of knowledge to one kind of a
big takeaway. So paper like ace and like
JAPAN and the others kind of trying to do it on
where the text domain. But text
domain somehow is very limited in description.
Not just in like robotic movement.
Also, like, you know, if you take, let's say,
10,000 textual feedbacks
on, like, code. Running. Okay? On
the same API. There's like
a lot and a lot and a lot of small details
about how to use this specific API.
And at some point, there's a limit to
how much we just can, like, kind of, like, compress
them in text. Now
what do, like, what the thing
that we know
is that neural network are really good
compressions. And
learning is a good compression algorithm. And
therefore, at some point where, like, kind of you
scale, putting things into weights can
help. That I think why also
people in the long context like
learning topic found that Tarag is
not enough and they moved to more like change
it in the architecture and stuff like that.
If, like, textual retrieval was
enough, then, you know, no one would
have looked at long context. We'll stop a drag.
I think the view of compression also
suggest another
benefit of, weight update,
which is generalization.
I think, text space
update definitely like
nowadays in if you write a skill
the empty file down, it generalized to
a very good degree. It
it goes way beyond, say, previously,
like, prompt optimization. That
you need and optimize for a new prompt for a
new problem skill skill
based update is definitely a big
step forward. But I think
the potential of weight update
terms of generalization is also
much higher than text state update.
But in general,
I probably not, like, directly answer
the question that okay, when should
we do weight update, and when should we
do parameter space update, which I totally
agree with all the others. That
there is definitely, you know, short term if you just
focus on, say, this iteration.
Training. There is
problems where weight update is more
efficient, and there's, problems
where text update is more efficient. But, like, in
general, these things are not
at odds at all. Right? Like,
take things to extreme. We can
just think of, okay, I gave
you a language model with the harness
can get a better trajectories or
generations. But then I can use them
to compress with a weight
update. To get a better model
But with a better model, I can always develop
better harness. That such
that you can have this Of course, I
believe this has to end
somewhere, but you you will have this
recursive self improvement
loop in this case as well.
Yeah. I I really agree, this
folks about the opinions about the tax
base is definitely not sufficient because,
so from my past experience, my
my research is mainly focused on the
embedded agent. So there are a lot of, you know, the
dynamics or the vision, descriptions
or texture or the, you know, the
the motion motion, that is really hard,
you know, even capture in pixel
space. Sometimes if your
camera is, not as a very good angle,
so it will cause some and be good and be
good to not to mention if we are
using a very abstract, representation
such as text. So in
my in my understand to to my understanding,
I think, in terms of life lifelong
agent, I think there are two two
things to be tackled to before answering this update
problem. The first thing is what kind
of representation we should use?
To train a model or as as a basic knowledge
representation? And the second question
is, what is the training dynamics we should
use for the model to,
you know, to follow its further decision?
Why about why one issue
updated parameters or when it should, like, leverage
the existing knowledge directly, then use it
to help them make decisions. So from the first
thing I think is, the press representation
note is is actually not a very,
I think it's still developing and really fast, but
not the final not but not it
won't be the ultimate version.
Like, so so let's take VEL. M
as an example. So VLM involves the
vision vision representation and to to force the vision
representation aligned with the language space.
But, this caused a fundamental issue that
it does not understand the dynamics of the
how the motion evolves. Or,
sometimes it will like, lose
the detailed understanding
about the the world
behind the image itself.
So even if you are very powerful,
like pi 0.7, but this
still this still mean a main bottleneck
that, if you just input a chunk
of you know, a set of images and try
to predict the future actions,
it's it's it's it's very unlikely that we will
handle a very long horizon task such as, you
know, the household task or
even, miles, long tasks.
So the representation now,
should be like, that
should be one like that you can extract the
dynamics of the world You
can understand you can also understand
what is your capability is. That is
you have to know what is your
knowledge limit. And try to expand this
limit boundary.
And on on on the second hand,
about updating parameters, I think
the I'm my personal
view, I think it would be better if the model can have
this ability to learn how to get
this deal. From itself, like to
because one should know that what fits
what fits himself or
herself best. To to to know
to know what what skill he should learn, from
the given context.
In that case, I think maybe you can leverage
the existing prior models.
Or even you can learn some new skills
by, you know, test during test and training.
And then for some very detailed
information, so such as how to describe
a scene of the the of the entire space,
Maybe you can just leave every detail,
save every detail, into an
into a external storage,
such as a point cloud or Gaussians
or something like that.
So overall, I think, since humans are actually
evolving, like human history is
very long, so the human from thousand
years ago is I think, the skills are very
quite different from what we have nowadays. So
the offline agent should also have this time limit
and they also has to learn how to adapt itself
through what is the current context
the agents are in. Yeah. I
also totally agree. I think there are, like,
more native multimodal also
like a emerging, there are more architecture.
So in this world. So
the agent should also try to adapt to itself.
And maybe, like, just to what
of you just said, like, maybe just in text format
to do some harnessing maybe that is not
not very enough. So, yeah,
because our time is a little bit tight,
so we have to close
at 5PM. So maybe I will directly
jump to the final
question about so like, suppose we meet again,
like, maybe in two years,
like, to say, so what would convince you
that Lifeline agent have really made a real
program? So it's more like,
a new capability or a new benchmarking
result, or, like, a new deployment
setting, etcetera. Maybe, like, we can talk about something
about the future. Yeah.
So Yeah. I can. I can.
Yeah. So from my view, I think this is a very good
question. So I think the best way to
test a fed lifelong agent
really works is to use a real world as a
as a benchmark, because real world itself is
a ultimate benchmark goal.
For the all of the, AGI intel AGI
So, to this end, I think,
if if if if I think
a real lifetime agent really works,
then I should know that whenever I give
give this agent a new task, it
can quickly learn and
adapt to this learn the knowledge
that they think to solve this question, and
try to give the solution
from time to time, or even in a in a iterative
way. And
it also needs to handle this divers, you know,
scenarios that maybe it's never seen before.
Not in the not not the very,
I mean not the domains that actually it
previously seen, but not directly trained. It
will be a very different domain, but it tried to use
this previous learn it knowledge
to help it to try to adapt
to to this field, so such as,
when when you learn how to
drive a car or learn how to play basketball,
this is something that you haven't, yeah, you haven't done
before, but, you never did before, but you you
you try to leverage your previous
prior knowledge and try to adapt to this field quickly.
Yeah. So that would be my view. Yeah. Maybe
other person can use, like, two or
three sentences to, yeah, conceptualize
the idea. Yeah. Yeah.
So I'll take a look at
the problem from a different scale.
These days, for example, process
3,000,000,000 messages a day. And
it doesn't do anything with these 3,000,000,000
messages. It doesn't learn anything.
For me, in two years, if
Frontier models will be such that they learn
from their interactions. And we see
not like 5.1,
5.2, 5.3, but
every day that I log in, it's better than the model
that we had yesterday. That for me
will solve of continual learning.
Chris already does that. No?
Kind of just for the top.
Just for the tub.
I think for me, there are two capabilities
I really wanna see. One is
meta learning capability, that the
model decide what kind of information it
want to learn from, what are the
noisy feedback that it should just ignore.
The second one is meaningful exploration,
not just naive exploration. Let me just
try a slightly different things. Think
the first one, I confident
that we will have something meaningful in two years,
but second one, I'm not sure.
I'll go quick. Cloud code, I don't
have to write Cloud IMD. I don't have to do
anything with it. I just use it and it just learns, and I
don't have to configure anything. Which coding.
Right? Which coding instead
of white coding? Like this
No. No. No. No. I'm I'm I'm I'm I'm
I'm I'm I'm I'm I'm still be giving out prompts. This is like I don't have to tune
all these, like, skills, all these stuff. It just
does it automatically. I think you know, that's
from user point of view, that's gonna be. Let's
just continue learning. Is it like a local
customization would you say? No. No.
No. No. It's it doesn't have to be local. I'm just saying
I don't have to do Like, I I I That's
totally set up, like, like it's gonna
use my conversation history or something, and then like it
just runs. Like, I just need a give
requirements. I don't need to, like, like, actually
do manual work to to help it continue
learn. I don't know if you guys write cloud.md,
Cloud has this auto memory now. So I like
it's a good thing. Previously, you need to write memory.md,
but But Yeah. Like
like acting as a CEO. You don't
have to care all about the details of
what's coming in there. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you so much. I think, yeah,
this is very inspiring discussion.
And, yeah, please stay on the stage for a
little bit. So
we will come to the
final. We will announce the award,
and we have also
yeah, prepared the the certificate for
all of you. Okay. All I did was ask first
each each camera pointing? So
Yeah. So we have
the best paper award
giving to
yeah. Eden. Congratulations.
Congratulations. Thank you. Yeah. For the self
distillation enables continue learning.
And we have three other
outstanding outstanding award. The first
one is for Shinoh
Yeah. Yeah. Thank you.
Will. Yeah. And it's for the
agent head contact stand
engineering paper. And the next one is
expanding the capability of the reinforcement
learning through text feedback. So this is
for Yudan. Yeah. Yeah.
Congratulations.
Congratulations. Yeah. And finally,
it is the paper
for Inact So
congratulations. This is for
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Thank you so
much. Maybe the camera can also
give us also of the four paper
award winners. Yeah. Thank you
so much for attending. And,
yeah, this will also be the final
of our workshop Yeah. And
thank you so much. So hopefully we will have
another addition maybe this
year in San Francisco or in Alice Place,
we will continue our discussion of the
topic. For the Lifeline agent. Yeah. Thank
you so much for attending the workshop today. And
Thank you for organizing. And thank
you all of your Yeah. Thank you so much.